<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Mindfulness on Shane Dowling</title>
    <link>https://shanedowling.com/categories/mindfulness/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Mindfulness on Shane Dowling</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.148.2</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 Mar 2018 18:06:17 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://shanedowling.com/categories/mindfulness/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Four years without Facebook</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/2018-03-26_four-years-without-facebook-7d5285a25913/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Mar 2018 18:06:17 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/2018-03-26_four-years-without-facebook-7d5285a25913/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://shanedowling.com/1__gvkmxCDjT7hqaHPPWYsovg__2x.jpeg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m happy to see the media dog-piling on Facebook so much lately. None of this &amp;rsquo;news&amp;rsquo; seems to actually be conveying much that&amp;rsquo;s new, more that it&amp;rsquo;s started taking what was slowly becoming normalised and framed it in a way to highlight the outrage. I don&amp;rsquo;t particularly like the media&amp;rsquo;s approach but I can&amp;rsquo;t feel too sorry about Facebook. We should be outraged with their on-going behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Four years ago I wrote an &lt;a href=&#34;https://shanedowling.com/de-activating-facebook-for-a-month-f91b49da00a4&#34;&gt;article about de-activating Facebook&lt;/a&gt;, I have not used Facebook since then and I believe I&amp;rsquo;ve permanently deleted my account somewhere along the way. I didn&amp;rsquo;t remove Facebook for it&amp;rsquo;s data hoovering and sharing but simply for it&amp;rsquo;s lack of intrinsic value. There have been points over the years where I felt a little FOMO, but very rarely and never enough to get back onto the site. Perhaps I don&amp;rsquo;t know what I&amp;rsquo;m missing, but from the looks of it on the outside that hasn&amp;rsquo;t been the case.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Leaving no Trace</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/2018-03-19_leaving-no-trace-6ca31ffc0b9/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Mar 2018 14:26:05 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/2018-03-19_leaving-no-trace-6ca31ffc0b9/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://shanedowling.com/1__ybl2a5U__z3REr1FD8qv09Q__2x.jpeg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I was camping along the West Coast of the US, I heard about the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leave_No_Trace&#34;&gt;Leave No Trace&lt;/a&gt; movement and found the idea very much resonated with me. Recently, I&amp;rsquo;ve found myself looking around day to day and wondering where I could start leaving less of a trace. We can all hate on consumerism, but lets face it, well all need to consume a certain amount to live in the modern world. So this isn&amp;rsquo;t a guide on becoming a burlap wearing hermit, it&amp;rsquo;s just a few things I&amp;rsquo;ve come up with for to start applying this idea into my life a little more.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 lessons from 150 days of meditation</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/2018-03-14_10-lessons-from-150-days-of-meditation-b4976d062a20/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Mar 2018 22:06:05 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/2018-03-14_10-lessons-from-150-days-of-meditation-b4976d062a20/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://shanedowling.com/1__GBwIzkZphZlN9GeNW3HAEA__2x.jpeg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been meditating now for 150 days straight, but even before that I was a fairly regular meditator for many years, I had just never kept up with any sort of meaningful streak every single day. My current momentum started from a difficult period in my life and even once that difficulty subsided, there was still a desire to keep going with the streak. 150 days later and I&amp;rsquo;m still happy to maintain it, but figured I&amp;rsquo;d write down a few insights I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten from this whole period.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Promoting mindfulness through the day</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/2014-01-16_promoting-mindfulness-through-the-day-e294cbc78843/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/2014-01-16_promoting-mindfulness-through-the-day-e294cbc78843/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the last year I&amp;rsquo;ve been cultivating a mindfulness habit. Overall,
it has delivered great results. One of the aspects I&amp;rsquo;ve been less than
happy with however, is my ability to carry that mindful state with me
throughout the day. I&amp;rsquo;m unsure if it&amp;rsquo;s because I&amp;rsquo;m a programmer and my
mind has to be so wrapped up in what I&amp;rsquo;m doing that mindfulness will
inevitably get pushed out or if it&amp;rsquo;s simply that full-day mindfulness
isn&amp;rsquo;t possible for me.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tired meditation</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/2013-07-25_tired-meditation-47ed1f094c04/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/2013-07-25_tired-meditation-47ed1f094c04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When I imagine myself doing meditation, I see myself almost leaping out of bed with boundless energy, followed by a full and focused period of breathing exercises. Nothing could be further from the truth. Right now I&amp;rsquo;m working through the Discovery Series on Headspace and it&amp;rsquo;s focusing more on looking at your body and how it feels. Now, a lot of what the meditation suggests is, is to use focus to alleviate the negative
feelings that occur in your body. This is great and it does help a lot but I have a fairly recurring and distracting problem when meditation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
