<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Digital Minimalism on Shane Dowling</title>
    <link>https://shanedowling.com/categories/digital-minimalism/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Digital Minimalism on Shane Dowling</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 16:45:59 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://shanedowling.com/categories/digital-minimalism/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Kindle Scribe to Mastodon</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/kindle-scribe-to-mastodon/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 16:45:59 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/kindle-scribe-to-mastodon/</guid>
      <description>Kindle Scribe to Mastodon Over the holidays, I put together a fun little project to put out status updates on Mastodon. Of course, I used some spare time to make this as overly-engineered as possible.&#xA;Stringing It All Together I wanted this to be event-driven and serverless and to give me some experience toying with Terraform in AWS. Thankfully, what would be the most computationally challenging part is already handled by Amazon.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Make your smartphone a little dumber</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/make-your-smartphone-a-little-dumber/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2023 16:45:59 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/make-your-smartphone-a-little-dumber/</guid>
      <description>For many, MANY years, I&amp;rsquo;ve been an advocate for the simplicity of dumbphones. My go-to? The LightPhone 2. However, modern life sometimes demands the functionalities of a smartphone, such as banking or GPS navigation. Every once in a while, I wish my smartphone would be just a touch simpler, but I can&amp;rsquo;t abandon its smart features entirely. There are times I need them, especially for those updates or browser-based app handshakes.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Keep up to date</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/keep-up-to-date-b90ee98640d4/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/keep-up-to-date-b90ee98640d4/</guid>
      <description>I love keeping up to date with all the latest tech news, but I find that when I follow numerous blogs there&amp;rsquo;s a heavy noise to signal ratio and eventually I get bogged down with all the blog posts coming at me. On top of that I don&amp;rsquo;t particularly like reading from a screen when I can avoid it, I spend so many hours a day reading/writing to computer screens, I always like to take a welcome break.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On wanting</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/on-wanting-8c4ca2f2d314/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/on-wanting-8c4ca2f2d314/</guid>
      <description>Recently I moved jobs and the new company I work for was nice enough to give me a brand new, high-end, retina Macbook Pro. It&amp;rsquo;s a great machineand I&amp;rsquo;ve been reminded how great an operating system OSX actually is. Naturally, I&amp;rsquo;ve been looking at my own machine a little differently. It&amp;rsquo;s a Lenovo Thinkpad X230 with an SSD and 16GBs of RAM. Generally it&amp;rsquo;s faster than I&amp;rsquo;ll need for a long time and I&amp;rsquo;ve had no real issues with it, but after starting to use the Macbook and the terrific software built with it, I wanted it bad.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>De-activating facebook for a month</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/de-activating-facebook-for-a-month-f91b49da00a4/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/de-activating-facebook-for-a-month-f91b49da00a4/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ll keep this one short, because there&amp;rsquo;s a million and one articles about people walking away from the social network. People are writing like they&amp;rsquo;re revolutionaries leading the mass exodus. I even poked fun at it in my internet predictions. Anyway, at the start of the year I figured I&amp;rsquo;d give a month away from facebook a try, partially inspired by Leo Babuta&amp;rsquo;s A Year of Living Without.&#xA;Why I asked myself what value I was actually getting from the service.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Freedom of Limits</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/the-freedom-of-limits-8677931d93e0/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/the-freedom-of-limits-8677931d93e0/</guid>
      <description>Over the course of this blog I intend to show how limitations can in many ways bring positive changes in your life. While limitations can appear under various guises(vegetarianism, minimalism) etc there is a huge number of aspects in your life where you can benefit from limits, just without the grandiose terms behind them.&#xA;Why? If you&amp;rsquo;ve ever attempted to meditate, you&amp;rsquo;ll realise that the human mind is insane. It&amp;rsquo;s cannot help but leap from one random thought to the next, like an irritated monkey in a cage.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
