<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Random on Shane Dowling</title>
    <link>https://shanedowling.com/categories/random/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Random on Shane Dowling</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 02 Jun 2018 16:39:57 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://shanedowling.com/categories/random/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Please don&#39;t do it Github</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/please-dont-do-it-github-5890eb72d12c/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jun 2018 16:39:57 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/please-dont-do-it-github-5890eb72d12c/</guid>
      <description>So Microsoft has been in talks with Github about a potential acquisition. There are several reasons why this is a terrible idea. Github is a pretty solid git repo hosting company, but it has a few core values that are in jeopardy here and I&amp;rsquo;m not sure Microsoft(or anyone) can acquire an entity like Github without severe repercussions.&#xA;Platform agnostic integrations Github has a ton of super useful integrations that help make the life for developers a lot easier.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wild Wild Country – The Soundtrack</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/wild-wild-country-the-soundtrack-bbe397fc1cf4/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Mar 2018 20:16:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/wild-wild-country-the-soundtrack-bbe397fc1cf4/</guid>
      <description>Wild Wild Country – The Soundtrack&#xA;For anyone who hasn&amp;rsquo;t seen Netflix&amp;rsquo;s Wild Wild Country, I highly recommend you watch it. The story told, along with the wealth of footage they got their hands on makes it an incredible watch.&#xA;The soundtrack is also excellent, I&amp;rsquo;ve put together the soundtrack as a playlist on Apple Music, you can find it here. Enjoy!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Short Review of &#39;Freedom from the Known&#39;</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/a-short-review-of-freedom-from-the-known-d22f52f8cdd3/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/a-short-review-of-freedom-from-the-known-d22f52f8cdd3/</guid>
      <description>Freedom from the Known can be a tough book to crack, the lessons offered within are almost dismissed by the arguments made within the book, on top of that it&amp;rsquo;s likely most won&amp;rsquo;t be in a position to even accept what they read as they are reading it. Despite these barriers, there is still wonderful lessons here calling out our own values, our judgements and what is preventing us from being truly free and present in each moment.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Friday Fun — Offline 8tracks playlists using Grooveshark</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/friday-fun-offline-8tracks-playlists-using-grooveshark-34b2512270df/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/friday-fun-offline-8tracks-playlists-using-grooveshark-34b2512270df/</guid>
      <description>A lot of people have been asking about how they might offline their favourite 8track tracks and I&amp;rsquo;ve come up with a rudimentary solution while I was doing some offline coding. On 8tracks I&amp;rsquo;ve found a great playlist series called Cold Machines created by user sowat on 8tracks and I wanted to offline my favourited tracks from these playlists as they&amp;rsquo;re great for coding to.&#xA;As there&amp;rsquo;s no direct way to do this it&amp;rsquo;s a several step process, but an pretty easy one at that.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Counterfeited Blog Post</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/the-counterfeited-blog-post-9d8f32f5d4b4/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/the-counterfeited-blog-post-9d8f32f5d4b4/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been reading E. M. Forster&amp;rsquo;s Aspects of the Novel and in it I came across a discussion on the French writer André Gide, specifically about his book Les faux-monnayeurs(The Counterfeiters).&#xA;The book is a merge of reality and fiction, Gide himself keeps a journal of his life as he writes the book and appears to merge the two. The writer is celebrated in Aspects for hurling himself into the novel and for not being bound by the style at the time or &amp;ldquo;All that is prearranged&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Precision Nutrition Trail Fast</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/precision-nutrition-trail-fast-88a4c01976d5/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/precision-nutrition-trail-fast-88a4c01976d5/</guid>
      <description>I went through the precision nutrition trial fast last Sunday, here&amp;rsquo;s a low-down on how things went through each of the steps. I had trialled this while out and about in central London, but failed at around 5pm, I was disorganised and feeling incredibly dizzy from the crowds and noise, so this time I planned ahead and did this from home.&#xA;10 PM Saturday Had a late dinner at the wonderful Chaat on RedChurch Street in Shoreditch.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Review of The Woman Who Walked Into Doors</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/review-of-the-woman-who-walked-into-doors-7aec5acb710c/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/review-of-the-woman-who-walked-into-doors-7aec5acb710c/</guid>
      <description>Last night I finished Roddy Doyle&amp;rsquo;s The Woman Who Walked Into Doors and I figured I&amp;rsquo;d write a quick review on it. It&amp;rsquo;s a book on the life of an Irish working-class woman named Paula who is struggling with an abusive husband and attempting to keep her family from the brink that her husband creates.&#xA;The details in this book are what make it particularly excellent writing. The lead character recalls incredibly specific details that bring her tragic story to life.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Legitimate ways to support good movies</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/legitimate-ways-to-support-good-movies-2fb11e565d2d/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/legitimate-ways-to-support-good-movies-2fb11e565d2d/</guid>
      <description>Recently I watched Akira Kurosawa&amp;rsquo;s Ikiru, after reading through some of the Criterion info on Kurosawa I realised I&amp;rsquo;d watched a bunch of his movies, I&amp;rsquo;m a huge fan of Seven Samurai.&#xA;The Criterion Collection is a wonderful distribution company and I&amp;rsquo;m a huge fan of a number of their filmmakers, so much so that I wanted to try and support the service more. Since I live fairly lightly in terms of possessions I can&amp;rsquo;t really justify $40 on a DVD or Blu-Ray.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Happy Programmers Day!</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/happy-programmers-day-d14d9063b43f/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/happy-programmers-day-d14d9063b43f/</guid>
      <description>Happy Programmers Day!&#xA;Have a productive one…&#xA;Or you&amp;rsquo;re sacked.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Writing Less</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/writing-less-2757f83c3a48/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/writing-less-2757f83c3a48/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;I didn&amp;rsquo;t have time to write a short letter, so I wrote a long one instead.&amp;rdquo; — Mark Twain&#xA;Lately I&amp;rsquo;ve been struggling with consistently writing. I find it difficult to sit down in the morning and begin to write. Usually ideas fall out of my head and I get into a flow quite quickly but recently, without a clear idea sitting in my head for a period of time I simply can&amp;rsquo;t put pen to paper.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>South Africa</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/south-africa-c688b9070707/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/south-africa-c688b9070707/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;d been in Cape Town for two weeks beforehand, just remotely working and doing some sightseeing around the area. So I had plenty of time for prep for the trip and was pretty relaxed arriving at Ashanti Logde(where the trip starts). The trip was booked through African Budget Safari&amp;rsquo;s which seemed to the cheapest option around. The dates I had originally planned to travel with(and booked) were unavailable and ABS happily changed my dates and gave me a heavy discount(about 25%).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Overlanding</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/overlanding-ac775c297d46/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/overlanding-ac775c297d46/</guid>
      <description>So, for the last 6 weeks I&amp;rsquo;ve been over-landing from Cape Town to Nairobi. I decided to ditch almost all of my tech for the trip. My Samsung Galaxy S3 and my Thinkpad were replaced with an old school phone and a notepad. I also picked up a tiny little Sandisk Sansa Clip MP3 player for the trip. For reading I had my Kindle and a few USB keys for storing files and for Portableapps(which was a disaster I&amp;rsquo;ll write about another time).</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
