<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Shane Dowling</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://shanedowling.com/feeds/all-en.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://shanedowling.com/</id><updated>2022-07-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated><subtitle>Shane Dowling</subtitle><entry><title>Physical vs Logical resource</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/physical-vs-logical-resource.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-07-06T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-07-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2022-07-06:/physical-vs-logical-resource.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Logical ID - The logical ID must be alphanumeric (A-Za-z0-9) and unique
within the template. Use the logical name to reference the resource in
other parts of the template. Physical ID - A physical ID, which is the
actual assigned name for that resource, such as an EC2 instance ID or an …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Logical ID - The logical ID must be alphanumeric (A-Za-z0-9) and unique
within the template. Use the logical name to reference the resource in
other parts of the template. Physical ID - A physical ID, which is the
actual assigned name for that resource, such as an EC2 instance ID or an
S3 bucket name. Use the physical IDs to identify resources outside of
AWS CloudFormation templates, but only after the resources have been
created. Eg EC2 in the console&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="TIL"></category></entry><entry><title>How to manage Podcasts on an iPod Classic on Linux</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/how-to-manage-podcasts-on-an-ipod-classic-on-linux.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2022-02-26:/how-to-manage-podcasts-on-an-ipod-classic-on-linux.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;After my last post generated some interesting discussion on &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=30236251"&gt;Hacker
News&lt;/a&gt;, I figured it
was worth a little guide on how I manage my iPod Classic on a Linux
machine. Thankfully some very clever people put together the drivers and
software to make this a breeze, but there's a few …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After my last post generated some interesting discussion on &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=30236251"&gt;Hacker
News&lt;/a&gt;, I figured it
was worth a little guide on how I manage my iPod Classic on a Linux
machine. Thankfully some very clever people put together the drivers and
software to make this a breeze, but there's a few things you need to
know that took some figuring out for me. So I'll share them here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="connecting-your-ipod"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Connecting your iPod&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This should be the easiest thing to do. Simply connect your iPod to your
machine and it should appear as an external device. Here's my iPod
appearing under Thunar after I plug it in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="./images/ipod_thunar.png" /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="managing-podcasts"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Managing Podcasts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To manage podcasts on my laptop I use
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://gpodder.github.io/"&gt;gPodder&lt;/a&gt;. I'm a huge fan of it. The only
limitation really is there may be podcasts locked to sources like
Spotify, but if you're listening to Podcasts on an iPod you'll hit this
limitation whatever you do. A quick `sudo apt install gpodder` should
install it on most debian-based systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="./images/gpodder.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So grab some decent Podcasts via RSS and download them. On my machine
the media files will appear under `~/gPodder/Downloads`&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="adding-podcasts-to-your-ipod"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Adding Podcasts to your iPod&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once they're downloaded, it's time to add these Podcasts to your iPod,
for this we need &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://wikiless.org/wiki/Gtkpod?lang=en"&gt;gtkpod&lt;/a&gt;.
Again a `sudo apt install gtkpod` should do the job in terms of
installation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what it should look like once you've started gtkpod and
connected your iPod.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="./images/gtkpod_initial.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should already have a Podcasts playlist in gtkpod, if not you will
need to create it. Once you do, this is the playlist to add media to and
any media added will then be recognised as Podcasts on your iPod. If you
don't, it gets lost in your larger media collection(and it won't have
resume support). Next step is to start adding Podcasts to your playlist.
You only need to do this once, then it's just a case of syncing your
media. So highlight the Podcasts playlist like so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="./images/gtkpod_highlight_podcasts.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;then in the menu bar, hit &amp;quot;Music&amp;quot; then &amp;quot;Add Folder&amp;quot; and select the
folder where gPodder downloaded your Podcasts to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="./images/gtkpod_add_folder.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It should start processing your files and adding them to your iPod. It
might be a bit unresponsive for a while. Repeat for any Podcasts you
want to add, making sure you add these folders to the Podcast playlist
in gtkpod. When done, make sure to eject your iPod in gtkpod, then eject
it from your filesystem. Podcasts should now appear on your iPod!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="on-going-podcast-management"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;On-going Podcast management&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that your folders have been added, gtkpod will remember to look in
these locations next time so when you want to grab any new Podcast
episodes and sync them to your iPod, it's pretty simple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open up gPodder and it will check for any new episodes and ask you if
you wish to download them. Use the time to delete any old episodes of
Podcasts you've already listened to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once downloaded, mount your iPod, open gtkpod right click on your
Podcasts playlist and hit &amp;quot;Sync Playlist with dir(s)&amp;quot;, it'll give you
a prompt to say which files with be added and removed. Hit okay and
your iPod will be up to date.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="./images/ipod_sayer.jpeg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that's my process, if you have any suggestion for how you do this
better, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://shanedowling.com/pages/contact.html"&gt;let me know&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="Digital Minimalism"></category></entry><entry><title>Consuming Content Like it's the 90s</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/consuming-content-like-its-the-90s.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2022-02-06:/consuming-content-like-its-the-90s.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It’s the 2020s, we continue to become more connected that we’ve ever
been, and I hate it! I don’t have the self-control needed to handle
these always-on devices. It’s awful. They’re all so incredibly powerful
and give so much in terms of information. I, however …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It’s the 2020s, we continue to become more connected that we’ve ever
been, and I hate it! I don’t have the self-control needed to handle
these always-on devices. It’s awful. They’re all so incredibly powerful
and give so much in terms of information. I, however will be on reddit
or hackernews pretending I’m productive reading about someone else’s
terrificly productive project. I’ve lived with my brain enough to know,
uncontrolled smartphones aren’t really for me. I’ve written elsewhere
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://shanedowling.com/make-the-smartphone-dumb-again.html"&gt;how my smartphone is basically a dumb
one&lt;/a&gt;,
but I’ve tried to replace the various pieces of value my phone delivers
with more dedicated devices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, it’s all about Podcasts and Audiobooks. There’s Spotify,
Overcast, Audible and all these other great Podcast apps, but sigh, they
all involve the black rectangle of addictiveness. I’ve been toying with
Digital Minimalism on and off since reading Cal Newports books and
actually &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://shanedowling.com/category/digital-minimalism.html"&gt;long
before&lt;/a&gt;. I
wanted more dedicated devices as a response to phone’s just doing
everything. I didn’t want to constantly feel around for a single device
to entertain me in limitless ways. So lets see if we can find a
reasonable replacement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I am almost constantly listening to either audiobooks or Podcasts.
With two kids, audio is about the best bet you’ll get in terms of
engaging drama that won’t be interrupted within ten minutes. There are
some excellent Podcasts dramas too. Blackout, and We’re Alive are just
two(especially if you’re into dystopias like myself). So we need a way
to listen to some Podcasts. What are the options available outside of
the black rectangles?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="version-1-minidiscs-terrible-first-idea"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Version 1 – Minidiscs, terrible first idea&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I am a big fan of Minidiscs, I love them as a format and I love that
my guilty please audio listening genre(synthwave!) are still releasing
albums on this format. It’s terrific. There’s a pretty good electron app
to manage tracks, and it’s just such an enjoyable and tactile format. So
lets give Podcasts a try on this thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I gave Podcasts on Minidiscs a real go, even printed out per-podcasts
discs covers, look how nice they look!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="./images/podcast-minidiscs.jpeg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this was a total disaster. The limited audio length was an absolute
killer. Trying to split podcasts and audiobooks amongst multiple discs
was painful. The write speeds being so slow, by the time a podcast was
written to the disc, it felt like the next one would be released. It was
terrible, I love Minidiscs, but no sane person could do this. Any
requirement to that needs frequent writes to a Minidiscs are doomed to
fail. Music and albums would be fine, but anything regularly needing
writing, no change. Learn from my lessons(or maybe you were smart enough
to not do stupid things in the first place)!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="./images/minidisc-and-player.jpeg" /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="version-2-it-s-the-future-ugh"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Version 2 – It's the future! Ugh.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, let's go from year 1992 to 1997 and try one of those futuristic
MP3 players. I decided to pick up a Victure Bluetooth MP3 Player and
yeah, it worked, but the experience was painful. Getting files on was
dead-easy, it just mounted as a filesystem. So the minidisc write
problems are solved, great. However, the experience of navigating and
listening to Podcasts left a LOT to be desired. These things don’t
support podcasts and the UI is just terrible on this tiny screen.
Without Podcast support, there’s no way to resume anything, and hopping
between Podcasts or pausing and leaving the device sucks. With serious
consequences, this maybe could work, but I feel like this would be too
painful for me not to just revert back to the black rectangle of
distractedness. MP3s are good though, this format might just have a
future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="./images/victure.jpeg" /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="version-3-just-right-just-about"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Version 3 – Just right, just about….&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time I opted for a heavy-weight. I didn’t want to mess around with
another cheaply produced modern MP3 player. If I was going MP3 I wanted
it to be the Rolls-Royce of relatively cheap mp3 players. Perhaps made
by the most valuable company on the planet at a time when it’s near
Jesus-like leader was at the peak of his powers. With that in mind, I
opted for an iPod Video 5th generation and in short, Jobs and all those
involved produced an almost perfect product. It’s well-made product,
really, really well-made. Especially considering it’s still going strong
20 years after its initial release. I’m putting it through it’s paces
too, I’ve been using this daily for 6 months, and it’s held up really
well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It supports Podcasts and Audiobooks out of the box, has resume support
and a really nice, easy to use UI. It’s staggering how good this UI is,
all things considered. Time has not seriously improved or developed MP3
products at all. I even have Rockbox installed on my iPod(as I just
assumed it would be better), but it genuinely is a poorer experience. No
Podcast support killed it out of the box for me, and generally it just
seems like it has a number of meaningless bells and whistles but nothing
to improve the actual core offering of the MP3 player.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of a serious evaluation though, I’ve used this iPod for around
6 months now, I listen to Podcasts/Audiobooks on it daily, from a
variety of topics. If you’re looking for a (currently) inexpensive and
also easy way to manage and listening to Podcasts on the go, I cannot
recommend anything better, but if you have any better suggestions, do
reach out, and I’ll happily add them onto the bottom of this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some limitations to this, I obviously need to manage
downloading Podcast and then transfer them to my iPod, but generally
that’s sort of done in the background while I’m doing other things. I’ll
write up a post on managing an iPod here. There’s some effort involved,
but once it’s setup it’s all good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="./images/ipod.jpeg" /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="Digital Minimalism"></category></entry><entry><title>TIL Updating ZSH</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/til-updating-zsh.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2022-01-04:/til-updating-zsh.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;To update Oh-My-ZSH, all I need to run is `omz update`. Didn't even
realise there was an omz command!&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="TIL"></category></entry><entry><title>Activity Nag</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/activity-nag.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2022-01-03:/activity-nag.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Digital Minimalism" src="./images/digital_minimalism.jpeg" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Digital Minimalism&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm trying out a month of Digital Minimalism and I wanted some…
encouragement to ensure I stick to my rules. One of which is to use my
laptop only for specific tasks I know ahead of time, for an hour a day
only. I currently already use Activitywatch …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Digital Minimalism" src="./images/digital_minimalism.jpeg" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Digital Minimalism&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm trying out a month of Digital Minimalism and I wanted some…
encouragement to ensure I stick to my rules. One of which is to use my
laptop only for specific tasks I know ahead of time, for an hour a day
only. I currently already use Activitywatch to track all my activities
on my machine, so I wanted a quick script that would(after an hour) nag
me constantly if I wanted to continue using my machine. So I made
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/shano/activitynag"&gt;ActivityNag&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find all the details around ActivityNag
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/shano/activitynag/blob/main/README.md"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="Digital Minimalism"></category></entry><entry><title>The vagueness of Secular Buddhism</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/the-vagueness-of-secular-buddhism.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2020-11-07:/the-vagueness-of-secular-buddhism.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’m looking for a path to atheist spirituality, and I’ve looking more
into Secular Buddhism. I have to admit, the results aren’t so promising,
many are so vague as to be almost completely useless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m looking for Buddhism minus beliefs, what I keep seeing is much …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’m looking for a path to atheist spirituality, and I’ve looking more
into Secular Buddhism. I have to admit, the results aren’t so promising,
many are so vague as to be almost completely useless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m looking for Buddhism minus beliefs, what I keep seeing is much more
content on beliefs in general, references to Buddhism material but very
little meat. No answers to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="what-can-i-explore-as-something-spiritual"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What can I explore as something spiritual?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="what-ceremonies-can-i-lean-on-to-support-this"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What ceremonies can I lean on to support this?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="what-new-ways-could-i-reframe-my-view-off-the-world"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What new ways could I reframe my view off the world?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll continue to explore and see what I can find to help answer these,
but so far(in the past) I’ve found Stoicism a much more concrete
approach to these questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="Mindfulness"></category></entry><entry><title>Make the smartphone dumb again</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/make-the-smartphone-dumb-again.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2020-11-05:/make-the-smartphone-dumb-again.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have terrible, terrible impulse control. I cannot stop using my phone
as a distraction tool. I simply cannot. We can discuss willpower, or
being a better person, but they don’t work. I have no willpower and
remain a terrible person despite how hard I try. If my phone …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have terrible, terrible impulse control. I cannot stop using my phone
as a distraction tool. I simply cannot. We can discuss willpower, or
being a better person, but they don’t work. I have no willpower and
remain a terrible person despite how hard I try. If my phone can do
something to distract me, I will use it, a lot. Then the loathing sets
in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I needed to turn my super sweet iPhone into something entirely
distraction-less and boring, it’s that, or I throw my phone away(which
I’ve seriously considered but without Whatsapp I just cannot communicate
easily with my family and that is not something I want to add friction
to).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here’s my approach to blocking the noise. (Note: This if for iPhone,
I’m sure Android can do something similar, it’s not like the bulk of
Google’s revenue is tied to you constantly engaging with their
services).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="what-has-been-disabled-uninstalled-from-my-phone"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What has been disabled/uninstalled from my Phone?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="safari-browsers"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Safari/Browsers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="app-store"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;App Store&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="email"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Email&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="games"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Games&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="social-networks"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Social Networks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="todo-apps"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Todo Apps&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="habit-apps"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Habit Apps&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="reading-apps"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reading Apps&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="colors"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Colors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="any-app-that-nags-me-for-anything-that-isnt-very-important"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Any app that nags me for anything that isn’t very important.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All noise that just does not add value to my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="what-remains-on-my-phone"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What remains on my Phone?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="maps"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Maps&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="camera"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Camera&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="podcasts-limit-of-3-for-now"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Podcasts(limit of 3 for now)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="journal-day-one"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Journal(Day One)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="banking-apps"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Banking Apps&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="apple-health"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Apple Health&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="notes"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Notes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="whatsapp"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Whatsapp&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So basically boring tools and Whatsapp. Nothing here would particularly
compel me to check my phone every ten minutes for any sort of update.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="how-do-i-disable-stuff-and-keep-them-disabled"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How do I disable stuff and keep them disabled?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is all great, but I’m a terrible person and once I’ve uninstalled
all of that stuff, I’m basically going to re-installed it all in 5
minutes when terrible me reappears. My solution is lock myself out of my
own phone. Find someone you trust (or if you want these restrictions for
life, someone who hates you) for this process. Here’s how.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uninstall all of the distracting, time-wasting apps you want to
remove.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under Settings, in “Content and Privacy Restrictions”, enable it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get your friend/enemy to set a password that &lt;strong&gt;you don’t know&lt;/strong&gt; but
that &lt;strong&gt;they will remember&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under “Allowed Apps”, disable Safari.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under “Content Restrictions”, disable installing apps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Search “Color Filters” in Settings and turn on “Greyscale”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Woo! We have a drab boring soulless rectangle that gives me exciting
access to my bank.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="replacements"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Replacements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we can talk about getting rid of all of this stuff, but in the end,
if you don’t come up with replacements to that pull for distraction
you’re likely going to crack, beg your friend for the password and
reinstall again. I did, many times. What I needed was replacements and
these seem to have tenuously worked pretty well so far for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My replacements are mostly a kindle and a notebook. Kindle to keep me
entertained when my brain, you know, starts to contemplate things like
life and its lack of meaning or cancer or why good things happen to bad
people. The notebook is for habit reminders, todos and when I get that
pull towards the rectangle to search for a thing. When I’m drawn to
research something, instead of the usual reinstall-fest, I write it down
what I want in my notebook and look it up later on a laptop if it still
matters(it often doesn’t).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="Digital Minimalism"></category></entry><entry><title>TIL - AWS Lambda Environment Vars</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/til-aws-lambda-environment-vars.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2020-11-05:/til-aws-lambda-environment-vars.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In AWS Lambda, if you use ENVIRONMENT VARS they are tied to the lambda
version, so a new deploy is required to update that config change.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="TIL"></category></entry><entry><title>Please, PLEASE make a domain for your own email address.</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/please-please-make-a-domain-for-your-own-email-address.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2020-11-02:/please-please-make-a-domain-for-your-own-email-address.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Don’t have a &lt;a class="reference external" href="mailto:me&amp;#64;gmail.com"&gt;me&amp;#64;gmail.com&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a class="reference external" href="mailto:us&amp;#64;outlook.com"&gt;us&amp;#64;outlook.com&lt;/a&gt;, have a &lt;a class="reference external" href="mailto:me&amp;#64;myname.com"&gt;me&amp;#64;myname.com&lt;/a&gt;
instead! [Google locks people out of their
accounts](&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.businessinsider.com/google-users-locked-out-after-years-2020-10?r=US&amp;amp;IR=T"&gt;https://www.businessinsider.com/google-users-locked-out-after-years-2020-10?r=US&amp;amp;IR=T&lt;/a&gt;),
to me loss of my email address would be a total disaster. This is the
problem with …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Don’t have a &lt;a class="reference external" href="mailto:me&amp;#64;gmail.com"&gt;me&amp;#64;gmail.com&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a class="reference external" href="mailto:us&amp;#64;outlook.com"&gt;us&amp;#64;outlook.com&lt;/a&gt;, have a &lt;a class="reference external" href="mailto:me&amp;#64;myname.com"&gt;me&amp;#64;myname.com&lt;/a&gt;
instead! [Google locks people out of their
accounts](&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.businessinsider.com/google-users-locked-out-after-years-2020-10?r=US&amp;amp;IR=T"&gt;https://www.businessinsider.com/google-users-locked-out-after-years-2020-10?r=US&amp;amp;IR=T&lt;/a&gt;),
to me loss of my email address would be a total disaster. This is the
problem with monopolies and something everyone needs to think more
about. Imagine a world where a comment somewhere on an unrelated social
network wipes out 15 years of email and communication as well as ongoing
access to that email address. That’s today and if you don’t look out for
these things you can be locked out of incredibly important parts of your
own digital world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So a few quick tips:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="use-a-personal-domain-for-email-dont-rely-on-any-one-service-ever-with-a-personal-domain-you-can-keep-your-email-address-and-swap-to-different-suppliers-whenever-you-could-try-fastmail-with-your-me-myname-com-address-and-if-you-dont-like-it-swap-back-to-gmail-if-you-want-try-protonmail-maybe-either-way-your-email-address-never-needs-to-change"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Use a personal domain for email, don’t rely on any one service ever. With a personal domain you can keep your email address and swap to different suppliers whenever. You could try Fastmail with your &lt;a class="reference external" href="mailto:me&amp;#64;myname.com"&gt;me&amp;#64;myname.com&lt;/a&gt; address, and if you don’t like it swap back to Gmail if you want, try Protonmail maybe. Either way, your email address never needs to change.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="always-backup-your-current-email-use-a-client-like-mail-or-thunderbird-and-always-download-your-mail"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Always backup your current email, use a client(like Mail or Thunderbird), and always download your mail.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="dont-use-google-sign-in-up-process-ever-dont-use-any-companies-single-sign-on-with-your-google-account-gone-those-logins-are-totally-doomed-its-far-too-risky"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Don’t use Google Sign-In/Up process ever. Don’t use any companies single sign on. With your Google Account gone, those logins are totally doomed. It’s far too risky.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bonus tip! Take a look at [nomoregoogle.com](&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://nomoregoogle.com"&gt;https://nomoregoogle.com&lt;/a&gt;)
and try to distribute some of your life away from one company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="Tech"></category></entry><entry><title>Quick Review - Long Gone Days</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/quick-review-long-gone-days.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2020-09-28:/quick-review-long-gone-days.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Coming from the AMAZING Bundle for Racial Justice and Equality, Long
Gone Days is a &amp;quot;2D modern-day military RPG set in our current times,
with a focus on language and cultural barriers&amp;quot;'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="looks"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Looks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Love the art-style of the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="music"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Music&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The score is solid and the in-game sounds are fine …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Coming from the AMAZING Bundle for Racial Justice and Equality, Long
Gone Days is a &amp;quot;2D modern-day military RPG set in our current times,
with a focus on language and cultural barriers&amp;quot;'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="looks"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Looks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Love the art-style of the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="music"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Music&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The score is solid and the in-game sounds are fine but unspectacular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="story"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Story&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No spoilers here. The story isn't bad, but it definitely has higher
ideas than it's able to pull off. It also doesn't really capture the
language and cultural barriers effectively in it's dialogue or plot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="gameplay"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Gameplay&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Walking around the pretty world is nice enough, but the motion feels a
bit clunky. The RPG elements are extremely shallow, and the battle
screen is unimpressive. There are sniper sections also which are also
fairly weak. All in all, it's not strong gameplay wise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of language and cultural barriers ties into the gameplay too.
You enter new areas without the ability to communicate with NPCs, that
could really have driven home the message about language barriers but in
reality you pretty quickly find a translator and that's that. It could
have been interwoven into the gameplay further, for example
mis-understanding language could lead to some character mistakes
plot-wise, or it could have been woven more effectively in the gameplay.
Again, it's just a bit shallow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="did-i-finish-it"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Did I finish it?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The true estimation of if a game is decent in this bundle. So for me,
no, after playing for a few hours, upon returning it felt too slow paced
and clunky to want to continue. Perhaps the shallowness gameplay wise is
forgivable, I'd say give it 30 minutes, if you're not sold on wanting to
progress the story the gameplay may not keep you around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>TIL - AWS Summit - ECR</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/til-aws-summit-ecr.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2020-09-28:/til-aws-summit-ecr.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;ECR supports vulnerability scanning of pushed up repo images.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="TIL"></category></entry><entry><title>TIL - AWS Summit - Eventbridge</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/til-aws-summit-eventbridge.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2020-09-28:/til-aws-summit-eventbridge.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Eventbridge can translate a lot of useful internal Amazon events into a
call to say a Lamdba, so you can drive custom behaviour from those
events. For example: high vulnerabilities in your pushed ECR image could
trigger lambda to fire off an alert(or delete the image).&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="TIL"></category></entry><entry><title>TIL - AWS Summit - Fargate Autoscaling</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/til-aws-summit-fargate-autoscaling.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2020-09-28:/til-aws-summit-fargate-autoscaling.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Fargate supports autoscaling options that include `FARGATE` or
`FARGATE&lt;sub&gt;SPOT&lt;/sub&gt;` for spot pricing.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="TIL"></category></entry><entry><title>TIL - AWS Summit - Latency</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/til-aws-summit-latency.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2020-09-28:/til-aws-summit-latency.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;P99 and P95 latency refer to the percentage of requests should be faster
than given latency.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="TIL"></category></entry><entry><title>TIL - AWS Summit - Spot Instances</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/til-aws-summit-spot-instances.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2020-09-28:/til-aws-summit-spot-instances.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Currently, ~5% of spot instances are getting taken out, but their
pricing is 1/3 of an On-Demand instance.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="TIL"></category></entry><entry><title>TIL - Bash Shift</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/til-bash-shift.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2020-09-28:/til-bash-shift.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In `bash`, use `shift` to reassign positional arguments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;```bash $1 $2 $3 ```&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Would become&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;```bash $1 matches old $2 $2 matches old $3 ```&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="TIL"></category></entry><entry><title>TIL - Git Rebase</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/til-git-rebase.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2020-09-28:/til-git-rebase.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In git, during rebase, ours and theirs are reversed. `theirs` is
actually the current branch in the case of rebase.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="TIL"></category></entry><entry><title>TIL - How to match python regex postgis</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/til-how-to-match-python-regex-postgis.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2020-09-28:/til-how-to-match-python-regex-postgis.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Use `(.*)` for matching groups in Python regexes.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="TIL"></category></entry></feed>