<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Shane Dowling - Digital Minimalism</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://shanedowling.com/feeds/digital-minimalism.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://shanedowling.com/</id><updated>2022-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><entry><title>How to manage Podcasts on an iPod Classic on Linux</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/how-to-manage-podcasts-on-an-ipod-classic-on-linux.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2022-02-26:/how-to-manage-podcasts-on-an-ipod-classic-on-linux.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;After my last post generated some interesting discussion on &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=30236251"&gt;Hacker
News&lt;/a&gt;, I figured it
was worth a little guide on how I manage my iPod Classic on a Linux
machine. Thankfully some very clever people put together the drivers and
software to make this a breeze, but there's a few …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After my last post generated some interesting discussion on &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=30236251"&gt;Hacker
News&lt;/a&gt;, I figured it
was worth a little guide on how I manage my iPod Classic on a Linux
machine. Thankfully some very clever people put together the drivers and
software to make this a breeze, but there's a few things you need to
know that took some figuring out for me. So I'll share them here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="connecting-your-ipod"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Connecting your iPod&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This should be the easiest thing to do. Simply connect your iPod to your
machine and it should appear as an external device. Here's my iPod
appearing under Thunar after I plug it in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="./images/ipod_thunar.png" /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="managing-podcasts"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Managing Podcasts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To manage podcasts on my laptop I use
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://gpodder.github.io/"&gt;gPodder&lt;/a&gt;. I'm a huge fan of it. The only
limitation really is there may be podcasts locked to sources like
Spotify, but if you're listening to Podcasts on an iPod you'll hit this
limitation whatever you do. A quick `sudo apt install gpodder` should
install it on most debian-based systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="./images/gpodder.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So grab some decent Podcasts via RSS and download them. On my machine
the media files will appear under `~/gPodder/Downloads`&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="adding-podcasts-to-your-ipod"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Adding Podcasts to your iPod&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once they're downloaded, it's time to add these Podcasts to your iPod,
for this we need &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://wikiless.org/wiki/Gtkpod?lang=en"&gt;gtkpod&lt;/a&gt;.
Again a `sudo apt install gtkpod` should do the job in terms of
installation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what it should look like once you've started gtkpod and
connected your iPod.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="./images/gtkpod_initial.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should already have a Podcasts playlist in gtkpod, if not you will
need to create it. Once you do, this is the playlist to add media to and
any media added will then be recognised as Podcasts on your iPod. If you
don't, it gets lost in your larger media collection(and it won't have
resume support). Next step is to start adding Podcasts to your playlist.
You only need to do this once, then it's just a case of syncing your
media. So highlight the Podcasts playlist like so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="./images/gtkpod_highlight_podcasts.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;then in the menu bar, hit &amp;quot;Music&amp;quot; then &amp;quot;Add Folder&amp;quot; and select the
folder where gPodder downloaded your Podcasts to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="./images/gtkpod_add_folder.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It should start processing your files and adding them to your iPod. It
might be a bit unresponsive for a while. Repeat for any Podcasts you
want to add, making sure you add these folders to the Podcast playlist
in gtkpod. When done, make sure to eject your iPod in gtkpod, then eject
it from your filesystem. Podcasts should now appear on your iPod!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="on-going-podcast-management"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;On-going Podcast management&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that your folders have been added, gtkpod will remember to look in
these locations next time so when you want to grab any new Podcast
episodes and sync them to your iPod, it's pretty simple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open up gPodder and it will check for any new episodes and ask you if
you wish to download them. Use the time to delete any old episodes of
Podcasts you've already listened to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once downloaded, mount your iPod, open gtkpod right click on your
Podcasts playlist and hit &amp;quot;Sync Playlist with dir(s)&amp;quot;, it'll give you
a prompt to say which files with be added and removed. Hit okay and
your iPod will be up to date.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="./images/ipod_sayer.jpeg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that's my process, if you have any suggestion for how you do this
better, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://shanedowling.com/pages/contact.html"&gt;let me know&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="Digital Minimalism"></category></entry><entry><title>Consuming Content Like it's the 90s</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/consuming-content-like-its-the-90s.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2022-02-06:/consuming-content-like-its-the-90s.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It’s the 2020s, we continue to become more connected that we’ve ever
been, and I hate it! I don’t have the self-control needed to handle
these always-on devices. It’s awful. They’re all so incredibly powerful
and give so much in terms of information. I, however …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It’s the 2020s, we continue to become more connected that we’ve ever
been, and I hate it! I don’t have the self-control needed to handle
these always-on devices. It’s awful. They’re all so incredibly powerful
and give so much in terms of information. I, however will be on reddit
or hackernews pretending I’m productive reading about someone else’s
terrificly productive project. I’ve lived with my brain enough to know,
uncontrolled smartphones aren’t really for me. I’ve written elsewhere
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://shanedowling.com/make-the-smartphone-dumb-again.html"&gt;how my smartphone is basically a dumb
one&lt;/a&gt;,
but I’ve tried to replace the various pieces of value my phone delivers
with more dedicated devices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, it’s all about Podcasts and Audiobooks. There’s Spotify,
Overcast, Audible and all these other great Podcast apps, but sigh, they
all involve the black rectangle of addictiveness. I’ve been toying with
Digital Minimalism on and off since reading Cal Newports books and
actually &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://shanedowling.com/category/digital-minimalism.html"&gt;long
before&lt;/a&gt;. I
wanted more dedicated devices as a response to phone’s just doing
everything. I didn’t want to constantly feel around for a single device
to entertain me in limitless ways. So lets see if we can find a
reasonable replacement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I am almost constantly listening to either audiobooks or Podcasts.
With two kids, audio is about the best bet you’ll get in terms of
engaging drama that won’t be interrupted within ten minutes. There are
some excellent Podcasts dramas too. Blackout, and We’re Alive are just
two(especially if you’re into dystopias like myself). So we need a way
to listen to some Podcasts. What are the options available outside of
the black rectangles?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="version-1-minidiscs-terrible-first-idea"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Version 1 – Minidiscs, terrible first idea&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I am a big fan of Minidiscs, I love them as a format and I love that
my guilty please audio listening genre(synthwave!) are still releasing
albums on this format. It’s terrific. There’s a pretty good electron app
to manage tracks, and it’s just such an enjoyable and tactile format. So
lets give Podcasts a try on this thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I gave Podcasts on Minidiscs a real go, even printed out per-podcasts
discs covers, look how nice they look!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="./images/podcast-minidiscs.jpeg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this was a total disaster. The limited audio length was an absolute
killer. Trying to split podcasts and audiobooks amongst multiple discs
was painful. The write speeds being so slow, by the time a podcast was
written to the disc, it felt like the next one would be released. It was
terrible, I love Minidiscs, but no sane person could do this. Any
requirement to that needs frequent writes to a Minidiscs are doomed to
fail. Music and albums would be fine, but anything regularly needing
writing, no change. Learn from my lessons(or maybe you were smart enough
to not do stupid things in the first place)!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="./images/minidisc-and-player.jpeg" /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="version-2-it-s-the-future-ugh"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Version 2 – It's the future! Ugh.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, let's go from year 1992 to 1997 and try one of those futuristic
MP3 players. I decided to pick up a Victure Bluetooth MP3 Player and
yeah, it worked, but the experience was painful. Getting files on was
dead-easy, it just mounted as a filesystem. So the minidisc write
problems are solved, great. However, the experience of navigating and
listening to Podcasts left a LOT to be desired. These things don’t
support podcasts and the UI is just terrible on this tiny screen.
Without Podcast support, there’s no way to resume anything, and hopping
between Podcasts or pausing and leaving the device sucks. With serious
consequences, this maybe could work, but I feel like this would be too
painful for me not to just revert back to the black rectangle of
distractedness. MP3s are good though, this format might just have a
future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="./images/victure.jpeg" /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="version-3-just-right-just-about"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Version 3 – Just right, just about….&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time I opted for a heavy-weight. I didn’t want to mess around with
another cheaply produced modern MP3 player. If I was going MP3 I wanted
it to be the Rolls-Royce of relatively cheap mp3 players. Perhaps made
by the most valuable company on the planet at a time when it’s near
Jesus-like leader was at the peak of his powers. With that in mind, I
opted for an iPod Video 5th generation and in short, Jobs and all those
involved produced an almost perfect product. It’s well-made product,
really, really well-made. Especially considering it’s still going strong
20 years after its initial release. I’m putting it through it’s paces
too, I’ve been using this daily for 6 months, and it’s held up really
well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It supports Podcasts and Audiobooks out of the box, has resume support
and a really nice, easy to use UI. It’s staggering how good this UI is,
all things considered. Time has not seriously improved or developed MP3
products at all. I even have Rockbox installed on my iPod(as I just
assumed it would be better), but it genuinely is a poorer experience. No
Podcast support killed it out of the box for me, and generally it just
seems like it has a number of meaningless bells and whistles but nothing
to improve the actual core offering of the MP3 player.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of a serious evaluation though, I’ve used this iPod for around
6 months now, I listen to Podcasts/Audiobooks on it daily, from a
variety of topics. If you’re looking for a (currently) inexpensive and
also easy way to manage and listening to Podcasts on the go, I cannot
recommend anything better, but if you have any better suggestions, do
reach out, and I’ll happily add them onto the bottom of this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some limitations to this, I obviously need to manage
downloading Podcast and then transfer them to my iPod, but generally
that’s sort of done in the background while I’m doing other things. I’ll
write up a post on managing an iPod here. There’s some effort involved,
but once it’s setup it’s all good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="./images/ipod.jpeg" /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="Digital Minimalism"></category></entry><entry><title>Activity Nag</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/activity-nag.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2022-01-03:/activity-nag.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Digital Minimalism" src="./images/digital_minimalism.jpeg" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Digital Minimalism&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm trying out a month of Digital Minimalism and I wanted some…
encouragement to ensure I stick to my rules. One of which is to use my
laptop only for specific tasks I know ahead of time, for an hour a day
only. I currently already use Activitywatch …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Digital Minimalism" src="./images/digital_minimalism.jpeg" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Digital Minimalism&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm trying out a month of Digital Minimalism and I wanted some…
encouragement to ensure I stick to my rules. One of which is to use my
laptop only for specific tasks I know ahead of time, for an hour a day
only. I currently already use Activitywatch to track all my activities
on my machine, so I wanted a quick script that would(after an hour) nag
me constantly if I wanted to continue using my machine. So I made
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/shano/activitynag"&gt;ActivityNag&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find all the details around ActivityNag
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/shano/activitynag/blob/main/README.md"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="Digital Minimalism"></category></entry><entry><title>Make the smartphone dumb again</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/make-the-smartphone-dumb-again.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2020-11-05:/make-the-smartphone-dumb-again.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have terrible, terrible impulse control. I cannot stop using my phone
as a distraction tool. I simply cannot. We can discuss willpower, or
being a better person, but they don’t work. I have no willpower and
remain a terrible person despite how hard I try. If my phone …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have terrible, terrible impulse control. I cannot stop using my phone
as a distraction tool. I simply cannot. We can discuss willpower, or
being a better person, but they don’t work. I have no willpower and
remain a terrible person despite how hard I try. If my phone can do
something to distract me, I will use it, a lot. Then the loathing sets
in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I needed to turn my super sweet iPhone into something entirely
distraction-less and boring, it’s that, or I throw my phone away(which
I’ve seriously considered but without Whatsapp I just cannot communicate
easily with my family and that is not something I want to add friction
to).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here’s my approach to blocking the noise. (Note: This if for iPhone,
I’m sure Android can do something similar, it’s not like the bulk of
Google’s revenue is tied to you constantly engaging with their
services).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="what-has-been-disabled-uninstalled-from-my-phone"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What has been disabled/uninstalled from my Phone?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="safari-browsers"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Safari/Browsers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="app-store"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;App Store&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="email"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Email&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="games"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Games&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="social-networks"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Social Networks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="todo-apps"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Todo Apps&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="habit-apps"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Habit Apps&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="reading-apps"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reading Apps&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="colors"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Colors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="any-app-that-nags-me-for-anything-that-isnt-very-important"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Any app that nags me for anything that isn’t very important.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All noise that just does not add value to my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="what-remains-on-my-phone"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What remains on my Phone?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="maps"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Maps&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="camera"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Camera&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="podcasts-limit-of-3-for-now"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Podcasts(limit of 3 for now)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="journal-day-one"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Journal(Day One)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="banking-apps"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Banking Apps&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="apple-health"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Apple Health&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="notes"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Notes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="whatsapp"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Whatsapp&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So basically boring tools and Whatsapp. Nothing here would particularly
compel me to check my phone every ten minutes for any sort of update.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="how-do-i-disable-stuff-and-keep-them-disabled"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How do I disable stuff and keep them disabled?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is all great, but I’m a terrible person and once I’ve uninstalled
all of that stuff, I’m basically going to re-installed it all in 5
minutes when terrible me reappears. My solution is lock myself out of my
own phone. Find someone you trust (or if you want these restrictions for
life, someone who hates you) for this process. Here’s how.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uninstall all of the distracting, time-wasting apps you want to
remove.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under Settings, in “Content and Privacy Restrictions”, enable it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get your friend/enemy to set a password that &lt;strong&gt;you don’t know&lt;/strong&gt; but
that &lt;strong&gt;they will remember&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under “Allowed Apps”, disable Safari.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under “Content Restrictions”, disable installing apps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Search “Color Filters” in Settings and turn on “Greyscale”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Woo! We have a drab boring soulless rectangle that gives me exciting
access to my bank.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="replacements"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Replacements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we can talk about getting rid of all of this stuff, but in the end,
if you don’t come up with replacements to that pull for distraction
you’re likely going to crack, beg your friend for the password and
reinstall again. I did, many times. What I needed was replacements and
these seem to have tenuously worked pretty well so far for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My replacements are mostly a kindle and a notebook. Kindle to keep me
entertained when my brain, you know, starts to contemplate things like
life and its lack of meaning or cancer or why good things happen to bad
people. The notebook is for habit reminders, todos and when I get that
pull towards the rectangle to search for a thing. When I’m drawn to
research something, instead of the usual reinstall-fest, I write it down
what I want in my notebook and look it up later on a laptop if it still
matters(it often doesn’t).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="Digital Minimalism"></category></entry><entry><title>Keep up to date</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/keep-up-to-date-b90ee98640d4.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-02-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-02-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2014-02-15:/keep-up-to-date-b90ee98640d4.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I love keeping up to date with all the latest tech news, but I find
that when I follow numerous blogs there's a heavy noise to signal ratio
and eventually I get bogged down with all the blog posts coming at me.
On top of that I don't particularly like …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I love keeping up to date with all the latest tech news, but I find
that when I follow numerous blogs there's a heavy noise to signal ratio
and eventually I get bogged down with all the blog posts coming at me.
On top of that I don't particularly like reading from a screen when I
can avoid it, I spend so many hours a day reading/writing to computer
screens, I always like to take a welcome break.
As a result of these two needs I came up with a neat solution that
allows me to retrieve all relevant tech news each day, that I can read
offline whenever I want.
It requires:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Kindle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;a href="https://kindle4rss.com/"&gt;Kindle4RSS&lt;/a&gt; Account&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://fivefilters.org/content-only/"&gt;Full-Text RSS&lt;/a&gt; (I use the self-hosted service).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kindle4RSS is a terrific service that allows you to deliver RSS
feeds to your kindle on a scheduled basis. The one downside is that a
number of RSS feeds only supply a stub of their content and this isn't very useful if you wish to read articles on your kindle. This is where
full-text RSS comes in. Simply plug the RSS feed you want into
full-text RSS and it will generate a new link that should supply
a full-text alternative to your RSS feed. In general this is a great
compliment to kindlefeeder, you can now read any of your favourite blogs that happen to supply a teaser only in their RSS feed.
So now, how do we supply our kindle with only relevant technical news?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thankfully &lt;code&gt;here&lt;/code&gt;__ is a service that supplies an RSS feed of hacker news articles with a score threshold. Meaning, depending on how many(or few) articles you want to read you choose the minimum score threshold. Thereby holding off the onslaught of low scoring articles. Plug that RSS feed into full-text RSS, then plug that URL into kindlefeeder and you can read all the relevant tech each day wherever and whenever you like.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Digital Minimalism"></category></entry><entry><title>On wanting</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/on-wanting-8c4ca2f2d314.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-02-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-02-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2014-02-08:/on-wanting-8c4ca2f2d314.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__yqRgbrg76yhiaKeopwA06g__2x.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I moved jobs and the new company I work for was nice enough to give me a brand new, high-end, retina Macbook Pro. It's a great machineand I've been reminded how great an operating system OSX actually is. Naturally, I've been looking at my own machine a little differently …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__yqRgbrg76yhiaKeopwA06g__2x.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I moved jobs and the new company I work for was nice enough to give me a brand new, high-end, retina Macbook Pro. It's a great machineand I've been reminded how great an operating system OSX actually is. Naturally, I've been looking at my own machine a little differently. It's a Lenovo Thinkpad X230 with an SSD and 16GBs of RAM. Generally it's faster than I'll need for a long time and I've had no real issues with it, but after starting to use the Macbook and the terrific software built with it, I wanted it bad. One evening I started looking at
pricing/portability and found one I wanted. I also started looking at
software I could use I got excited, about to make a purchase. Then I
stopped. I stopped and forced myself to make a list of all the reasons I
wanted the Macbook that I couldn't get on my currently machine. I made the list as specific as possible, not just "it's pretty" or "all the apps are better", here's what I came up with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://selfcontrolapp.com/"&gt;Self-Control&lt;/a&gt; allows me to completely block websites for hours on end, this gives a nice feeling that the computer is purely for productivity and allows me to focus much better. It helped put my machine at arms length, purely for specific tasks and nothing more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://alternativeto.net/software/concentrate/?platform=mac"&gt;Concentrate&lt;/a&gt; allows me to define specific tasks that automatically runs apps and quit others. I seem to be able to "wire-in" faster than my general process of having to run X,Y,Z before I can start into something. It promotes single-tasking on my machine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.42burnside.com/mindfulmynah/"&gt;Mindful Mynah&lt;/a&gt; has been a nice tool that does seem to help me maintain mindfulness during the day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A nice background pomodoro app.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Productivity focused mail client &lt;a href="http://mindsensehq.com/mailpilot/"&gt;Mail Pilot&lt;/a&gt; has kept my Inbox at zero for the last few weeks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ommwriter.com/"&gt;Ommwriter&lt;/a&gt; is another great tool that allows me to focus on this time specifically on writing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An &lt;a href="https://evernote.com/"&gt;Evernote&lt;/a&gt; client. This one is really significant, all of the linux-based clients are severely lacking. I have serious problems with NeverNote screwing up syncs/losing data. The Mac one is really good and just works.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Things like hiberation/suspend actually work and don't break/screw up on a regular basis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway I decided that instead of just paying hand over fist for a new
Macbook that I'd try to replicate my needs using my existing hardware.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A Taste of Mint&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end I decided to ditch Debian in lieu of &lt;a href="https://linuxmint.com/"&gt;Mint&lt;/a&gt;. I wanted something I could setup quickly as I didn't want to invest a lot of time in this. Ubuntu is in theory a good choice, it has better hardware support over Debian and a wider range of apps available. The problem is I greatly dislike Ubuntu for it's privacy invading actions and for unity, which I still think is a terrible UI. I figured Mint made sense. It's definitely appeased my "It's so pretty" lizard brain and it's clearly stolen a bunch of nice UI stuff from Mac. I actually find Cinnamon a really well designed interface. So on the specific tasks, here's how Mint fared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/zengargoyle/selfcontrol"&gt;Self-Control&lt;/a&gt;. Self-control for Linux turns out to only half work. It blocks the sites, but then crashes and doesn't automatically unblock them. I shall take a look at fixing this if I stick with Mint. I'll see if I can get by with some shell aliases that run the commands I need instead either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.mozilla.org/en-US/thunderbird/"&gt;Thunderbird&lt;/a&gt;. As a replacement for Mail Pilot, sucked. Firstly, for some reason when I pointed it at my mail server it wiped ALL of my emails without download them, luckily I had a backup…. Anyway, after some playing around I got it working, but no, Mail Pilot it isn't.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for Ommwriter, I found something that does the job just not as well, it's called &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UberWriter"&gt;Uberwriter&lt;/a&gt;. Whilst I loved Ommwriter's clicky sound as I typed and the calming music it played, Uberwriter does it's job as a focused writing program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Evernote, I gave &lt;a href="https://github.com/nvbn/everpad"&gt;Everpad&lt;/a&gt; a go, which is okay. However without Unity on Linux Mint I can't seem to search which makes it a little useless. worked out of the box as did bluetooth, so no complains there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end I'm still undecided, in comparison to the Mac it's not a
polished experience and I worry that productivy hits I'll take getting
stuff working will cost me more in the long run but for now I'm happy to
give it a good honest trial, put some cash aside over the next few
months and see how I feel later on. Either way I'm glad I'm making a
patient decision over another rushed tech purchase.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Digital Minimalism"></category></entry><entry><title>De-activating facebook for a month</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/de-activating-facebook-for-a-month-f91b49da00a4.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2014-02-01:/de-activating-facebook-for-a-month-f91b49da00a4.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__nNdLICwvbMSn__IhaHVHYRg__2x.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll keep this one short, because there's a million and one articles about people walking away from the social network. People are writing like they're revolutionaries leading the mass exodus. I even poked fun at it in my &lt;a href="http://139.59.171.97/2014/01/25/internet-predictions-2014/"&gt;internet predictions&lt;/a&gt;. Anyway, at the start of the year I figured I'd …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__nNdLICwvbMSn__IhaHVHYRg__2x.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll keep this one short, because there's a million and one articles about people walking away from the social network. People are writing like they're revolutionaries leading the mass exodus. I even poked fun at it in my &lt;a href="http://139.59.171.97/2014/01/25/internet-predictions-2014/"&gt;internet predictions&lt;/a&gt;. Anyway, at the start of the year I figured I'd give a month away from facebook a try, partially inspired by Leo Babuta's &lt;a href="https://zenhabits.net/without/"&gt;A Year of Living Without&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Why&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I asked myself what value I was actually getting from the service. If I
can't be bothered ringing someone and catching up, then realistically
why would I waste time liking their cat photos? I also questioned the
value of these facebook friends. Am I actually friends with all these
people or is the connection just convenient enough for me to keep them
around? Do I actually want to share something with them or am I just
boasting?
Again, this topic has been discussed ad nauseam, but I'll link &lt;a href="http://www.npr.org/blogs/alltechconsidered/2013/08/19/213568763/researchers-facebook-makes-us-sadder-and-less-satisfied"&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; and quote it's final line, "Direct interactions with other human beings led people to feel better". Again, the article is based on one study, but it adds evidence to a belief I've held for quite some time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Net Effects&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing negative, at all. At no point during this month have I
felt a desire to return to Facebook. Frankly, I love not knowing. It was
very similar sensation to when I stopped following sensationalist media,
my life just gained a little more space. If you're still on the fence
consider de-activating for a month and seeing how much you really miss
it. You can easily re-activate your account any time you want. For me,
put simply I won't be going back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;February 28, 2014&lt;/strong&gt; - Counterfeit Update - Still off
Facebook, still not regretting the decision.
&lt;strong&gt;February 14, 2015&lt;/strong&gt; - Still haven't touched the site. Much to my
benefit.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Digital Minimalism"></category></entry><entry><title>Numbers to replace that smartphone(London Edition)</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/numbers-to-replace-that-smartphone-london-edition-b121face9106.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2014-01-30:/numbers-to-replace-that-smartphone-london-edition-b121face9106.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I made this list of useful phone numbers to replace the apps I used on
my smartphone. However it could also be considered useful for anyone
travelling to London that doesn't want to get screwed with data roaming.
Just use these numbers at any payphone around town. You know, the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I made this list of useful phone numbers to replace the apps I used on
my smartphone. However it could also be considered useful for anyone
travelling to London that doesn't want to get screwed with data roaming.
Just use these numbers at any payphone around town. You know, the big red things tourists take photos next to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__sakBC__uTJj7Fi25IEwu8__Q__2x.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will warn you however this list will force you to have to interact
with other human beings and &lt;strong&gt;shudder&lt;/strong&gt; potentially have a pleasant
conversation with them. If you've ever been on a London tube and looked around at the faces intently staring into smartphones with blaring headphones on, you'll understand. You also may have to walk and/or travel to locations other than your couch, I'm just warning you now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Shopping&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the time I'm buying books, from Amazon, for this I've come up
with two numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.foyles.co.uk/bookstore-charing-cross"&gt;Foyles&lt;/a&gt;-020 7437 5660
You can ring and reserve books or orders ones in that they don't have in
the building. They'll hold them for you till you show up. Also has a
much better search engine than Amazons. "I need that book by that guy
who's on the panel show with the Irish guy" type conversations and the
staff will still somehow manage to root out whatever the hell I'm
talking about. It's a London institution with a decent coffee shop and
music section too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/libraries"&gt;Canada Water Library&lt;/a&gt; - (020) 7766 4745/4747
Or insert whatever library you have near you. They're largely forgotten
these days, but they can still be a useful resource if you still prefer
the feel of a book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Media&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do I do without Netflix on my ipad/iwhatever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://princecharlescinema.com/PrinceCharlesCinema.dll/Home"&gt;Prince Charles Cinema&lt;/a&gt;-020 7494 3654&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Awesome cinema right in the heart of London that's really reasonable. I
think membership is a tenner and movies tend to be around 5–6 pounds.
Also just ring and ask the whoever is on the phone to recommend you
something if you've no clue what you're in the mood for, there's always
something good on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.closeupfilmcentre.com/"&gt;Close-Up&lt;/a&gt;-+44 (0) 20 7739 3634&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An awesome DVD rental place on Brick Lane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Transport&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay &lt;a href="https://citymapper.com/company"&gt;CityMapper&lt;/a&gt; is a really useful app when you're out and about, I do miss it but I have found a pretty cool alternative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://tfl.gov.uk/transport-accessibility/plan-your-journey"&gt;TFL Travel Planner&lt;/a&gt;-0343 222 1234
This is an automated service that allows you to plan journeys over the
phone. It's fairly painless to use and they even text you your route.
Not a bad little service at all, especially when you don't know where
the hell you are or how to get where your going(which happens to me more often than I'd like). You could also, ask another human being for help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;International Calling&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things I did miss was being able to Skype relatives using
their app from pretty much anywhere. This one yet again can be solved,
also thanks to Skype.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.skype.com/en/features/skype-to-go-number/"&gt;Skype to Go&lt;/a&gt; – ??&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically, Skype allows you to setup local numbers that will forward you
to whatever number your like. You'll only pay the local call charge and
whatever Skype charges to make a call. It's a pretty great free service
from Skype.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Comms&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter/Facebook/Whatsapp/Viber/Etc what do I do? Here I'd recommend just calling someone. I'd rather have one conversation with a friend over the phone than a million likes from acquaintances. I've already wrote about &lt;a href="http://139.59.171.97/2014/02/01/deactivate-facebook/"&gt;de-activating for a month&lt;/a&gt; if you're interested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So there's a few numbers I found useful that replace the apps on my
phone. I'm sure you could do something similar for your own city. I'll
maintain this list as I discover new numbers worth putting up. In
particular I'm looking for a service to recommend events around the
city, like a timeout magazine, but a phone number. I'm looking forward
to seeing how far I can push this.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Digital Minimalism"></category></entry><entry><title>Switching to a dumbphone</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/switching-to-a-dumbphone-3b090f8ad709.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-01-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-01-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2014-01-18:/switching-to-a-dumbphone-3b090f8ad709.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h3&gt;Why?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am aware, that while there is a trend towards smart-phones there are
quite a few articles around on the subject of people swapping back to a
dumb-phone or even &lt;a href="http://gizmodo.com/5991495/why-my-iphone-is-better-as-a-dumbphone"&gt;using your smartphone as a dumphone&lt;/a&gt;. Apparently it can &lt;a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/innovations/wp/2013/10/31/why-i-dumped-my-smartphone-for-a-7-year-old-motorola-razr/"&gt;help your marriage&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not that naive. Frankly, my reasons …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;Why?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am aware, that while there is a trend towards smart-phones there are
quite a few articles around on the subject of people swapping back to a
dumb-phone or even &lt;a href="http://gizmodo.com/5991495/why-my-iphone-is-better-as-a-dumbphone"&gt;using your smartphone as a dumphone&lt;/a&gt;. Apparently it can &lt;a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/innovations/wp/2013/10/31/why-i-dumped-my-smartphone-for-a-7-year-old-motorola-razr/"&gt;help your marriage&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not that naive. Frankly, my reasons for swapping away from my
smartphone is pretty pragmatic, it was simply a persistent call to
mindless action. That I carried around in my pocket. Everywhere.
I found myself in a constant state of half-living, meaning half of my
mind is on the present moment and the other half on a device. I've
flipped to it when I'm communicating with people, commuting or even
watching TV. Apparently TV is no longer enough of a distraction for this
half-living brain I seem to have developed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sure I could just not use those features, like the Gizmodo article I
linked to. I tried this, and cut pretty much everything but the useful
stuff out of my phone, it boiled down to maps, public transport apps,
RunKeeper and Whatsapp. However, I still constantly found myself in a
tug of war where I would uninstall, then re-install browsers for an
information fix. Just because it was easy and I could. It got to the
point where I discovered a really small(100KB or so) browser so I could
get my internet fix even faster. I realised my phone wasn't giving me
enough benefit for the mental costs. Maybe I'm particularly weak, I'm
sure others can happily keep their smart-phones at a healthy distance,
but I accepted that I simply couldn't.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As soon as I realised I hadn't the ability to distance myself from my
phone and that this was negatively effecting my mindfulness, I needed to figure out a way solve this. What I wanted to do was maintain some of the useful benefits of a smart-phone minus the distractions. Taking a
cold hard look at the realistic benefits I got from my phone really helped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The features I wanted(not needed) started with GPS-based maps of some sort. London is big, without GPS maps I knew I'd spend a lot of time getting lost, which isn't so bad sometimes but maps are essential when I need to be at a place at a certain time, which happens quite often. I also use RunKeeper a lot and enjoyed looking at my stats and progress, it wasn't a deal-breaker but I worried about my motivation to run. The same with can be said for using Sleep as Android which I used for logging sleep patterns. I like being able to view how many hours I'm sleeping each night, it's a very useful to me and has generally improved my wellbeing. Finally, as I'm a contractor, I spend a lot of time taking photos of receipts for expenses etc, I've found Evernote really useful for this.
Eventually, I decided to get myself a Symbian, so a half
smart/dumb-phone. Specifically the Nokia 6730.
Essentially because it supports 3G and GPS. Symbian also supported Whatsapp, Viber, Endomondo(no RunKeeper unfortunately) and even Evernote. I also picked up a FitBit One, for exercise and sleep logging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Advantages&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I don't browse anymore, ever. Frankly, browsing the web is so painful to do on this phone I've tried once, got nowhere and never again.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The OVI store is terrible. It doesn't even save my username and password, and typing those in on this device is enough of a reason never to install another app.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Google Maps/GPS has been better than I expected. Basically, there's a little more typing but the GPS/maps combo has been spot on for me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Endomondo has been terrific. Granted you can't multi-task with it, so if you get lost you need to stop your run, check your map and start another run. I still thing it's great. I even contributed some code to an app that allows you to convert your RunKeeper data to Endomondo. You can grab it &lt;a href="https://github.com/shano/runkeeper2endomondo"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I also discovered SoundHound is on here, a nice to have little discovery.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My phone is no longer a thing. It's a boring piece of tech in the background. When I need to get in touch with someone, odds are I'll just call them. No twitter, email or facebook. It is just a phone with a few bells and whistles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Fitbit sleep logging shows a little timer of how long I've slept, I found this quite useful if I've woken up too early.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Disadvantages&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Fitbit hasn't been very useful. I could've survived without the sleep logging and it doesn't really capture runs properly. It's trying more to be an overall health system and one that requires a smartphone so you can input a ton of data into. How much water you drink, what calories your taking in etc etc. I didn't need any of this. In hindsight I wouldn't have bothered with it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Evernote client also didn't support my phone. This is quite annoying, it means I can't in the moment grab useful data or take quick snapshots and have them backed up. But the phone's camera is decent enough, so I'm hoping I'll work out a different alternative.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Viber didn't actually support my phone, not a big deal.
That's about it really. I've been using my dumb-phone for the last few
weeks, and I haven't really missed my Samsung SIII, other than Evernote
really. Honestly, considering how distracted I was with the phone I
thought it would be a much more difficult transition. I guess because
I'd reduced my smart-phone down to the bare essentials as it was, I
wasn't losing a tremendous amount of features.
It genuinely looks like the future of my phone tech is going to be a
crappy 4 year old phone running an even crappier 13 year old operating
system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;February 28, 2014 –&lt;/strong&gt; Counterfeit Update - I'm still
using my dumb-phone and loving it. In fact, one Saturday I trialled
using my Samsung S3 for a day and couldn't stand it, I constantly kept
checking it and that drove my crazy. Giving it away as a gift.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Digital Minimalism"></category></entry><entry><title>The Freedom of Limits</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/the-freedom-of-limits-8677931d93e0.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-12-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2013-12-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2013-12-27:/the-freedom-of-limits-8677931d93e0.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over the course of this blog I intend to show how limitations can in
many ways bring positive changes in your life. While limitations can
appear under various guises(vegetarianism, minimalism) etc there is a
huge number of aspects in your life where you can benefit from limits,
just without …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over the course of this blog I intend to show how limitations can in
many ways bring positive changes in your life. While limitations can
appear under various guises(vegetarianism, minimalism) etc there is a
huge number of aspects in your life where you can benefit from limits,
just without the grandiose terms behind them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Why?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you've ever attempted to meditate, you'll realise that the human mind
is insane. It's cannot help but leap from one random thought to the
next, like an irritated monkey in a cage. Seriously, just attempt to
think about your breath for any extended period and you'll realise how
helpless you are to it(unless you're trained of course). I recently watched a documentary by Adam Curtis called &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/eJ3RzGoQC4s"&gt;Century of the Self&lt;/a&gt;. If you haven't watched it, I'd highly recommend it. Essentially it's about the rise of the concept of the self and how corporations have sought to exploit it. I won't go into too much detail but the important parts for this post are that during post-WW2 America, corporations had a genuine fear that they would run out of consumers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That, eventually everyone would have say a car and that would be it,
no-one else needs a car, or a washing machine or a winter coat(These
days it sounds laughable). In the 60s people began a new 'me-centric'
way of behaving that both politicians and corporations had to adapt to.
Politicians did so by pandering to the middle class and corporations by
using market research, categorisation of consumers in lifestyles and
overbearing choice(Appealing to our emotions through marketing/advertising came before this, but is still relevant).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we all discovered we were very special 'inner directed' human beings,
corporations realised pretty quickly that they could exploit our newly
found desire by convincing people they could define themselves through
spending. Think about this for a second, when you bought what you're
wearing right now what sort of questions did you ask. Is this durable?
Is it well made? Is the corporation an ethical entity? Will it survive
the elements? Heck even 'Is this comfortable?' can even get overlooked.
The point is we probably bought what we did as we had an emotional
response to the garment in question. It had a cool design or looked good on me, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are all perfectly valid things to want from a
garment, we gain emotional satisfaction by feeling like we made a unique choice. I'm not going to harp on about spending habits and I've shown how you can apply `limits to what you own `__ but it's good to keep in mind how we can gain an emotional pleasure(and it can be exploited) simply by making a choice and that building a good choice/limitation balance can be beneficial to your wellbeing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you go throughout your day try to discover where you might have
undermined yourself through excessive choice, don't judge yourself just
make a note of it. It might be a humungous todo list, or a wardrobe full
of t-shirts you don't wear. What about a bookshelf full of books you
couldn't string a sentence about, anything that hits you with a minor
twang of guilt as you pass. Using the bookshelf as an example, why not
just donate all the books and just start again, with a new limitation.
'I can't buy a new book till I've finished this one', and see if it fits
or how about trying 'I can only buy a book 7 days after I initially
wanted it', anything to keep the crazy monkey in your head from reaching for the credit card or the buy now button. Whilst I've focused heavily on spending limitations they may not be the case. Here's a list of some of the limitations I've enacted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Follow a maximum of podcasts(Down from 30 that I never listened to)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only two pages of apps on my iPhone(And no subfolders!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Five news-feeds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two books on my kindle at any one time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My 50 items goal generally keeps me from spending frivolously but that
doesn't help with digital purchases. One laptop can contain hundreds of
distractions/guilts. I just got tired of seeing 500+ unread items in
google reader or 100+ podcast episodes I never got around to listening
to. We find it so easy to make a pleasing decision to better ourselves
but not to realise that it might be far more beneficial to us to undo
the original decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Effects&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I listen to all of my podcasts, I can read through my news-feeds
incredibly quickly. I don't buy any old random app/book just because I
can at the click of a button. Through limitations I can better evaluate
what I truly want and as a result I value everything I have that much
more. It's also made me value my own time more that whatever the source 'hey it may not actually be worth my valuable time'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Tips/Tricks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try to re-evaluate your limitations when you find things piling up
again, I can't stress this enough. I initially thought I could handle 20
news-feeds, not so much. So if you're still snowed under with say four
podcasts, then try just one or maybe consider that you're not a podcast
person. Try a new limit and see if the shoe fits and just keep at it,
eventually you'll find the balance you're looking for and maybe figure
out who you are a bit more.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Digital Minimalism"></category></entry></feed>