<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Shane Dowling - Leadership</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://shanedowling.com/feeds/leadership.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://shanedowling.com/</id><updated>2021-08-27T13:32:59+00:00</updated><subtitle>Platform Engineering Manager</subtitle><entry><title>Nonviolent Communication</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/nonviolent-communication-a7bddf8d0805.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-08-27T13:32:59+00:00</published><updated>2021-08-27T13:32:59+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2021-08-27:/nonviolent-communication-a7bddf8d0805.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__Tq3cCMHDxnnkVTxtFSJ6jA.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What is Nonviolent Communication?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nonviolent Communication(NVC) helps us communicate clearly by breaking down and identifying our needs and communicating them compassionately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Why?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NVC can help reduce conflict towards others and ourselves. It can also help us to hear others out and recognise each other's needs and support acting more …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__Tq3cCMHDxnnkVTxtFSJ6jA.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What is Nonviolent Communication?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nonviolent Communication(NVC) helps us communicate clearly by breaking down and identifying our needs and communicating them compassionately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Why?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NVC can help reduce conflict towards others and ourselves. It can also help us to hear others out and recognise each other's needs and support acting more compassionately day to day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a high level, the steps involved are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Observation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be present and listen carefully to what the other person is saying. How is it affecting you? Just observe, don't evaluate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avoid quick immediate judgements like "You never sweep the floor"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use "The last three times I asked you to sweep the floor, it wasn't done"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Feeling&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Express how you feel. Be specific, give narratives if you need to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avoid ambiguous statements like "I feel drained"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Needs&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Identify the needs at the root of your feelings. This can take practice, the objective is to be able to sincerely express yourself directly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Requests&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Express clearly and specifically what you really want. Be specific in the action needed. Express yourself with positive language. Ask for something, don't frame the request as something to stop being done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avoid "You are always X"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use language like "I would like…."&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Listening&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a bonus, you can also use NVC when you are listening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Observation&lt;/strong&gt;-Give the person space to fully express their feelings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Feeling&lt;/strong&gt;-Don't jump to offer advice. Ask questions and help the other person evaluate and understand their feelings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Needs&lt;/strong&gt;-Use the power of reflection. Rephrase what the other person is saying back to them, sometimes what they communicate might not be what they actually need.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Request&lt;/strong&gt;-Confirm and clarify the request after establishing what the need is. Ensure it's clearly understood.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Behaviours&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also behaviours to be mindful of when practising NVC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take responsibility for your feelings. Your reaction to life events determines how you feel, not the event itself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When reacting to conflict, avoid defensive/negative reactions, neither get to the root of the issue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Talk through your own feelings and use the process to identify your emotional response and address the reasons for the conflict.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use NVC to reduce self-judgement. Listen to your judgement and instead of being led by those feelings, ask yourself, "what unmet needs am I expressing here?"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Leadership"></category></entry><entry><title>5 Steps to a better Personal Development Plan(PDP)</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/wrangle-your-personal-development-plan-pdp-into-actionable-objectives-e448649b5db0.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-03-26T15:30:42+00:00</published><updated>2021-03-26T15:30:42+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2021-03-26:/wrangle-your-personal-development-plan-pdp-into-actionable-objectives-e448649b5db0.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__fc4D7D9urHFu0rbm8cpP2Q.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reviewing your PDP can be a somewhat overwhelming process. So many areas of improvement can be highlighted, it can be a real challenge to discover what to focus on. Not only that but you also want to make sure your areas of focus have high impact benefits to the squad …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__fc4D7D9urHFu0rbm8cpP2Q.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reviewing your PDP can be a somewhat overwhelming process. So many areas of improvement can be highlighted, it can be a real challenge to discover what to focus on. Not only that but you also want to make sure your areas of focus have high impact benefits to the squad, so much to think about!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These 5 steps should help give you the direction needed to turn those PDP opportunities into something actionable, demonstrable and focused on what you care about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Step 1-Find the themes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Depending on your PDP, a lot of areas of improvements might be highlighted(or maybe that's just me). They might be categorised as different things, for example competency or skills. It can be overwhelming to try to parse all of that opportunity into something actionable. The first thing I would suggest is to find the themes. Try your best to group your areas of opportunity as best you can, it won't be perfect, but it's helpful to put together some order. That way, you can tackle the theme to demonstrate the competency and show your skills!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example that might help, say there's your Agile skills improvement and also a competency you could demonstrate around execution. Could they live under the theme of delivery? Theming can be challenging, but it's an iterative process that you'll improve on over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Step 2-What gives you energy?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever I've tried to think about what I care about I often struggle. Historically I get wrapped up in the objectives of the team and leave my own preferences to one side, this has gone on for so long in my career, I often struggle to answer the question "What do I even care about?".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing working at Gousto has taught me early on was to ask yourself "What gives you energy?". It's deceptively clever for such a simple statement. Focus less on what you want to care about in the future. Focus on what gives you energy now, what undertakings have given you that energy in the past? Use that to inform your decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that frame of mind pick one or two of your themes that you think will give you energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Step 3-Find the outcomes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that you've come up with the themes you want to put energy into, now is a good time to try to link it to outcomes. What are the outcomes that will help you and the business?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More importantly, can you demonstrate that you personally are improving in this area and that the business is benefiting from it? Come up with as many outcomes as you can here, we'll whittle them down in the next step!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Step 4-Impact and metrics&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So you have some themes and a greater number of outcomes you could progress, what outcomes should you focus on?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One tactic you can take is to ask yourself is why? Ideally, you ask yourself why about 5 times. &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Five_whys"&gt;The Five whys&lt;/a&gt; technique is not perfect, but it will hopefully help challenge you into clarifying why that outcome matters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other approach is to look at is metrics. Do your outcomes move any metrics? If not maybe it's worth initially capturing a metric before executing the outcome. When it comes time to review your PDP, demonstrating metrics have moved as a result of executing your PDP is a pretty compelling sign of progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Step 5-Make a plan&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point the best thing to do is to start breaking down those outcomes and to come up with a plan with your line manager. Hopefully what you now bring to the table is not only what you're going to focus on but also a very clear why you want to focus on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Outcomes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ideally you'll now have the structure in place to really kickstart your PDPs and have much more productive sessions with your line manager. This can also be something you refer back to regularly, particularly in review sessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As time passes you might discover other worthwhile initiatives, now you can evaluate those initiatives with the same process and stack it against your current focus. It's always useful to remind yourself not only of what you want to focus on, but what you decided not to do and why. This should be your north star.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Leadership"></category></entry><entry><title>Learning Python as a Platform Engineer-First Steps</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/learning-python-as-a-platform-engineer-first-steps-911e59dd4af8.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-01-01T14:48:49+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-01T14:48:49+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2021-01-01:/learning-python-as-a-platform-engineer-first-steps-911e59dd4af8.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__t__tjPBb9m6YDhRdn3wKGSg.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've relatively recently moved into a Platform Engineering position after working in very developer oriented teams for many years. What's interesting is that the engineers you work with have much more diverse and interesting backgrounds in terms of their experience, so there's a real opportunity to grow and learn a …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__t__tjPBb9m6YDhRdn3wKGSg.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've relatively recently moved into a Platform Engineering position after working in very developer oriented teams for many years. What's interesting is that the engineers you work with have much more diverse and interesting backgrounds in terms of their experience, so there's a real opportunity to grow and learn a lot more, as opposed to a more homogenous set of developers. With that in mind, I wanted to put together materials on how a more ops focused engineer can up-skill in Python(as that's more my wheel-house), in particular what are the things that would help you move into a more Python-focused role.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Where to start&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beginners who have no experience of Python are going to need to get their head around the fundamentals. I wouldn't avoid reading books, but you're going to get more impact delivering. Prioritise writing and reading code over anything else. One thing I'd always suggest is to try automate parts of your life with code. There's a great book called "Automate the boring stuff with Python" if you need inspiration to focus on delivering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, when I needed a refresher in Python after several years of NodeJS, I started writing scripts that helped me to refresh myself. I wrote a script to alert me of the most up to date bus arrival times from TFL just before I'd usually leave the house in the morning, so I knew what time I had to leave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On an ongoing basis, I maintain a simple Python project on an ongoing-basis that will watch a YouTube channel and automatically download any streams that appear. I use this project to test out things is like to try out, such as new libraries or programming concepts. It's a safe way to try things out before I might suggest using it at work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So to start with, &lt;strong&gt;pick a project&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What to avoid&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't read books and not output anything! It's a trap of feeling productive while avoiding cementing any learnings. Think of it this way, you don't want to "learn to code", what you are is lazy and what you really want is to solve boring problems with code. You're learning to use a hammer, find nails in your life to start banging away at!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also avoid getting bogged down in setup. As an ops engineer, you might lean more into what you're comfortable with. Just get something super basic working and don't waste too much time on setup or use repl.it and forget about it! Heck I even wrote a post on &lt;a href="https://shanedowling.com/why-im-using-an-ipad-as-my-at-home-machine-2fe3e8949bb2"&gt;coding on my iPad&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Set a goal&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't set a vague goal when learning to program, getting "better" doesn't mean anything. Programming is about delivering projects and learning what works and what doesn't. Focus on delivering small projects that help you in any small way and iterate on complexity. Don't be afraid to set clear goals for yourself and share them with others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it helps try to think about it as a maturity vs capabilities. You don't "mature" to be a developer, what would that even mean? Think of it more as adding capabilities to yourself, "I'm capable of writing a Python script, I'm capable of writing some tests, I'm capable of using boto to interact with AWS automatically". Avoid thinking "I'll read a bunch of books and be a developer some day".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So set a goal of delivering a &lt;strong&gt;specific project at a specific date&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Figure it out&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now it's time to start figuring out how to solve this problem you've set for yourself. At this stage I would say, look for what works best for you. Could you learn the basics more from say a book, a series of articles, a Udemy course? I've put some resources at the bottom of this post but this step really only you can define.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one thing I would recommend is getting good at reading documentation, try to read up using the Python docs first before using Google/SO, but it's fine if that's what you need to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Asking for help&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you get stuck, ask for help. Ask colleagues, if you can't ask them, ask on Stackoverflow or find a Python discord or IRC channel for example: &lt;a href="https://pythondiscord.com/"&gt;https://pythondiscord.com/&lt;/a&gt; and reach out. I can only speak for myself, but I always love helping people genuinely trying to learn but just getting blocked. If you can't find any help at those resources and have some cash to spare, you can always use a service like &lt;a href="https://codementor.io"&gt;https://codementor.io&lt;/a&gt; to get the expertise you need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Automate your (platform) life&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a more platform-focused perspective, if you have say, manual things you do in AWS repeatedly, could that be turned into a quick script? Take a look at boto3 and see if there's anything that could save you some time every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some inspiration:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When an incident occurs in the systems you maintain, are there several things you might check depending on the type of incident that occurs? Perhaps you could automate pulling out some key data on your local machine to save some critical time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rotating keys, setting up users, any other admin tasks you could use avoid logging into your cloud platform?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are there parts of your job where the UI of your cloud-provider of choice is a total pain(&lt;em&gt;cough&lt;/em&gt; Cloudwatch… &lt;em&gt;cough&lt;/em&gt;)? Perhaps you could avoid it by programming a solution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Resources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of resources you can use:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://automatetheboringstuff.com"&gt;https://automatetheboringstuff.com&lt;/a&gt;-Great for inspiration to start projects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.twilio.com/quest/learn/python"&gt;https://www.twilio.com/quest/learn/python&lt;/a&gt;-If you can't think of any projects you'd like to start, this looks like a fun way to crank out some lines of code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.fullstackpython.com/"&gt;https://www.fullstackpython.com/&lt;/a&gt;-Deep dive into programming in Python.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mvK0UzFNw1Q"&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mvK0UzFNw1Q&lt;/a&gt;-Great video on where to start and explains why you should focus on delivering projects instead.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://repl.it/"&gt;https://repl.it/&lt;/a&gt;-Don't get bogged down setting your local environment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://codementor.io/"&gt;https://codementor.io/&lt;/a&gt;-Pay to get expert help.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is definitely enough to get a platform engineer started, I'll expand on this series with next steps, so keep an eye! I'll also start documenting how I'm growing from a Developer into a role demanding more Ops capabilities when I feel more comfortable myself.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Leadership"></category></entry></feed>