<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Shane Dowling - Mindfulness</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://shanedowling.com/feeds/mindfulness.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://shanedowling.com/</id><updated>2018-03-26T18:06:17+00:00</updated><subtitle>Shane Dowling</subtitle><entry><title>Four years without Facebook</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/four-years-without-facebook-7d5285a25913.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-03-26T18:06:17+00:00</published><updated>2018-03-26T18:06:17+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2018-03-26:/four-years-without-facebook-7d5285a25913.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__gvkmxCDjT7hqaHPPWYsovg__2x.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm happy to see the media dog-piling on Facebook so much lately. None of this 'news' seems to actually be conveying much that's new, more that it's started taking what was slowly becoming normalised and framed it in a way to highlight the outrage. I don't particularly like the media's …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__gvkmxCDjT7hqaHPPWYsovg__2x.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm happy to see the media dog-piling on Facebook so much lately. None of this 'news' seems to actually be conveying much that's new, more that it's started taking what was slowly becoming normalised and framed it in a way to highlight the outrage. I don't particularly like the media's approach but I can't feel too sorry about Facebook. We should be outraged with their on-going behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Four years ago I wrote an &lt;a href="https://shanedowling.com/de-activating-facebook-for-a-month-f91b49da00a4"&gt;article about de-activating Facebook&lt;/a&gt;, I have not used Facebook since then and I believe I've permanently deleted my account somewhere along the way. I didn't remove Facebook for it's data hoovering and sharing but simply for it's lack of intrinsic value. There have been points over the years where I felt a little FOMO, but very rarely and never enough to get back onto the site. Perhaps I don't know what I'm missing, but from the looks of it on the outside that hasn't been the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm happy to see Facebook die(not that I believe this will be anything like a death bell for them). Ideally, I'd like to see functionality it provides get split up into smaller, focused alternatives, that could be something I'd use again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps this recent outrage is a nice reminder to question the true value of social networks in general, and to what extent we can meaningfully communicate through them. Think about your last few interactions with Facebook, did you feel good? Did you feel engaged with those around you? I certainly didn't.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Mindfulness"></category></entry><entry><title>Leaving no Trace</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/leaving-no-trace-6ca31ffc0b9.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-03-19T14:26:05+00:00</published><updated>2018-03-19T14:26:05+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2018-03-19:/leaving-no-trace-6ca31ffc0b9.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__ybl2a5U__z3REr1FD8qv09Q__2x.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I was camping along the West Coast of the US, I heard about the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leave_No_Trace"&gt;Leave No Trace&lt;/a&gt; movement and found the idea very much resonated with me. Recently, I've found myself looking around day to day and wondering where I could start leaving less of a trace. We can …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__ybl2a5U__z3REr1FD8qv09Q__2x.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I was camping along the West Coast of the US, I heard about the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leave_No_Trace"&gt;Leave No Trace&lt;/a&gt; movement and found the idea very much resonated with me. Recently, I've found myself looking around day to day and wondering where I could start leaving less of a trace. We can all hate on consumerism, but lets face it, well all need to consume a certain amount to live in the modern world. So this isn't a guide on becoming a burlap wearing hermit, it's just a few things I've come up with for to start applying this idea into my life a little more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Transport&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The weather in London has finally started getting a little better, so I'm now alternating running and cycling to work instead of using public transport. Save money, contribute less carbon and free exercise. The benefits are obvious but we all know it's not that simple. Start small and build from there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Food&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a Nespresso machine and looking back, I kind of regret that purchase. They do provide a recycling program(I assume in response to the massive amounts of waste going on), so please do use that if you can. It's still not great and I do feel guilty about that level of waste. I've picked up some re-usable pods and compost the coffee grounds(they're great for plants). I already have an aero-press with a steel filter that provides almost no waste(beyond the coffee itself), so I am tempted to, swap back to that. Will see if the effort becomes a bother again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reducing Waste&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find out what your local authority can take in terms of recycling. For the UK &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/recycling-collections"&gt;here's a postcode finder&lt;/a&gt;, that displays the information you need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;When things break&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Electronics&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's a few things to try before hitting that store:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perhaps the manufacturer has an option to repair the thing. It costs almost no time, so check up on this before doing anything else.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If that's not an option, check out if it's repairable. See if there's some &lt;a href="https://www.ifixit.com/"&gt;ifixit guides&lt;/a&gt; available. I have had a &lt;a href="https://www.ifixit.com/Device/Lenovo_Thinkpad_x230"&gt;Lenovo Thinkpad x230&lt;/a&gt; for several years and have replaced almost everything in it and it's still a great machine. It's currently running as a server but could be pulled back out into more regular usage soon if I ever feel like it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you're not too comfortable with repairs, see if there's a repair cafe nearby where someone could help. There's a recent article &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/mar/15/can-we-fix-it-the-repair-cafes-waging-war-on-throwaway-culture"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; on The Guardian about such places, so take a look and see what options there are.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Clothes&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Repairing clothes is not that difficult, take a look into a course. It's definitely something I'll be doing in the coming months but right now my girlfriend is excellent at clothes repair, so I do rely on here a little…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you're into that, consider going to your local dry cleaners, they will often do clothes repair often at a pretty reasonable price. I've used them myself for various fixes/alterations and never had anything but good experiences.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;When you need to buy something new&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;In General&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a bunch of places where you can buy second hand. eBay, Gumtree, Shpock, Craigslist are all great options when you need something new that doesn't have to be new.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Electronics&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you can, go second hand. The UK has a number of second hand stores: Cex, Envirophone, Cash Converters to name a few. Make use of these places too when you're getting rid of a device, free money and perhaps preventing the sale of another unnecessary new gadget&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are into repairs and definitely need a new phone, take a look into a &lt;a href="https://www.fairphone.com/en/"&gt;Fairphone&lt;/a&gt;. It's an easily fixable Android smartphone created with ethically sourced labour and parts. Definitely worth looking into. Neat things include individual upgrades to parts, want a better camera? Instead of buying a new phone, just buy an upgraded camera and put it into the phone! It's a very cool idea.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take a look at the ifixit score to make life easier if it does go down the drain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Clothes&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check out that local charity shop and see if they don't provide what you're looking for. Give some money to charity, reduce waste and get stuff cheaper. There's really no downside here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hate shopping? Consider looking for Buy it For Life items, there's a &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/BuyItForLife/"&gt;subreddit&lt;/a&gt; dedicated to durable, quality items, so less waste and less boring clothes shopping.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Just buy less&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, so there's a little bit of anti-consumerism going on. I'm not going to bore you landfill stats or other miserable information about waste, that's not the point. Just maybe take some time to contemplate your purchases a little more, perhaps when you feel the urge to buy item X add it to your calendar for 30 days in the future and see where you get to.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Mindfulness"></category></entry><entry><title>10 lessons from 150 days of meditation</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/10-lessons-from-150-days-of-meditation-b4976d062a20.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-03-14T22:06:05+00:00</published><updated>2018-03-14T22:06:05+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2018-03-14:/10-lessons-from-150-days-of-meditation-b4976d062a20.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__GBwIzkZphZlN9GeNW3HAEA__2x.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been meditating now for 150 days straight, but even before that I was a fairly regular meditator for many years, I had just never kept up with any sort of meaningful streak every single day. My current momentum started from a difficult period in my life and even once …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__GBwIzkZphZlN9GeNW3HAEA__2x.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been meditating now for 150 days straight, but even before that I was a fairly regular meditator for many years, I had just never kept up with any sort of meaningful streak every single day. My current momentum started from a difficult period in my life and even once that difficulty subsided, there was still a desire to keep going with the streak. 150 days later and I'm still happy to maintain it, but figured I'd write down a few insights I've gotten from this whole period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For most of my meditation sessions, I've used Headspace. I've worked my way through many their programs, finished Headspace Pro(which incorporates more silence week on week), their daily sessions and have just used it as timer when I didn't want to hear anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over time, I've tried to reflect heavily on what has worked for me and what hasn't.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1. Space matters&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've meditated on trains, planes (and automobiles in fact) and everywhere else in between and while it's great to be able to meditate anywhere, I do have to say that I found my mind definitely casts itself into that relaxed awareness far more easily in the right space. At home, I put some effort in. My flat has wooden floors, so I have a pretty comfy mat with a pretty solid meditation cushion on the floor. During the early morning sessions I often light some incense and a candle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is something I never really focused on before, assuming that I could just focus on my breath and those aids were just hippie nonsense, posing as a mindful person. For me nowadays it's whatever can best help me get into a quiet, contemplating, curious mind. So ignore that self-critical part of yourself that might judge for some incense, or a particular post, whatever gets you in the zone and practicing every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2. The lead up and wind down help&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best time I've found to meditate is first thing in the morning. That's what I've worked out but it may be different for you. When my mind is still relatively quiet, I move around a bit to get some alertness and then sit in silence, it's also a wonderful way to start the day but isn't always possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have to meditate in strange places, the best thing you can do is spend a minute or two just focusing cultivating a genuine curiousity about how you're feeling right now, like ask yourself "How is my breathing?", I've found it helps me keep focused and not take the practice for granted and get more value out of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same is true after meditating, I spend a minute or two just basking in the feeling after a meditation and resolving to try maintain it for as long as I can, which is admittedly, not always very long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3. Incorporate it everywhere&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have also found however, that when I meditated just in the morning, the relaxed, wise energy that came with the practice faded quickly. I started incorporating meditation into various parts of my day. Headspace has a commuting meditation, as well as a walk in the park. There's sessions dedicated to various issues you might have at work, mindful computer usage etc. I've tried a lot of these and I can't recommend any one of them more than any other. They all sort of provide the general benefit of making you aware of your monkey brain and might help to stop feeding that side of you when you get caught up in things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From my own perspective, I gained a lot of insight just trying different things out, all the while still maintaining my morning practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing I can recommend if you have an Apple Watch is the Breathe App. It's a simple timer that vibrates in such a way to help you time your in and out breaths. This is called rhythmic breathing and it's great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a talk on YouTube &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=q06YIWCR2Js"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, that might help convince of you of the value of rhythmic breathing(including measuring the heart rate of a poor guy dragged on stage). It's pretty convincing that rhythmic breathing is definitely something worth trying, there is also probably some alternative you could use on a Phone, I've just found the Apple Watch app is discreet and convenient, so I can do it on the train or work and no-one would even notice I'm simply focusing on my breathing rhythm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;4. If you're mind is too active while meditating&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another sales pitch for rhythmic breathing, when I found my mind was too active and jumping around while I meditated if I switched to rhythmic breathing for a few minutes, I could more easily focus on the original meditation I wanted to work on. This was particularly helpful when I woke up after a stressful dream and my mind was still racing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;5. Don't meditate in bed!!!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This might seem obvious, but on those days where I was feeling pretty lazy, I would attempt a meditation in bed, rather than get up and do it. It's a pretty bad idea and you might as well not bother and get a couple of extra minutes sleep. Seems obvious but it can be a pretty easy thing to convince yourself to try in a half awake state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;6. Silent meditation is different to the apps&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the meditations on Headspace are heavily guided, you can choose to go along the Headspace Pro pack(which I do recommend after a while) or the timed Unguided Meditation, but beyond that most involve a lot of listening to Andy guiding you through the exercise and for the most part I find this great. However, I did notice the difficulty ramping up when I tried to simply sit quietly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During my 150 days I went on an introductory meditation retreat for a weekend. No screens whatsoever and a lot of (surprisingly enjoyable) silent periods. When I arrived I felt like meditation was something I was good at and wouldn't have any problems with the prolonged silent meditations. Boy was I wrong. While Headspace is great at practicing with meditation, just a silent meditation of just you with your own thoughts is still definitely a more challenging experience. Far more noticing of discomfort, a louder mind with no voice to guide it, I frankly struggled sometimes, but in a way the reward. was much greater. I felt like I had delved deeper into facing the monkey mind despite the challenges i faced. Silent meditation is not something I think I could do at home every day but I do think I'll push along with headspace pro again and find more time for silence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;7. Find every opportunity&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sounds similar to the previous lesson of incorporating it everywhere but not exactly. You can focus on the breath everywhere, but you can also focus on different activities. You really can meditate while walking, cleaning, cooking, eating, basically just focusing on your life with a easy relaxed awareness supported by some sort of regular focused meditation would give everyone a huge boost in contentment. Don't get too hung-up on the breath, at the same time those other "mindful moments" certainly are a little more difficult to maintain and I am certainly not there myself, but it is something I try to aspire to each day(when work and life don't get in the way).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;8. Slow down&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the lessons I learned very recently was to slow down, this message came to me during my meditation retreat. The long periods of silence and no technology created an environment that cultivated an excellent setup to meditation practice. When I say this, I mean that feeling of easy awareness really stuck with me for far longer. Our lives are often incompatible with a mindful attitude, but that content, easy feeling I felt during the retreat motivated me to start taking a hard look at my own life and perhaps eliminate as much "busyness" as I could to cultivate a similar feeling. This realisation has come recently and am I certainly only a beginner at this, but will share any insights and things I've tried that have/haven't worked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;9. Don't hold any expectations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you constantly expect meditation to show you something about yourself, or provide that warm fuzzy feeling you will often be disappointed. If there's any expectation to hold it's that you will always find the truth in meditation, and that truth can be extreme pain or the height of pleasure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;10. The Best Advice&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's all I can come up with for now, but the best advice I could probably offer from a wise cartoon monkey(10 points if you get that reference), which is, "Every day it gets a little easier. But you have to do it every day. That's the hard part. But it does get easier.".&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Mindfulness"></category></entry><entry><title>Philosophy as an extension of mindfulness</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/philosophy-as-an-extension-of-mindfulness-8295b123c977.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-04-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-04-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2014-04-20:/philosophy-as-an-extension-of-mindfulness-8295b123c977.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__8__eU80cOXYJfRz3xdJ__9JA.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I read a very interesting &lt;a href="https://robertpaulwolff.blogspot.co.uk/2011/10/one-dimensional-man-mini-tutorial-part.html"&gt;mini-tutorial on Marcuse&lt;/a&gt;
and his book One-Dimensional Man, an apparently brilliant merge of both
Freud and Marx. I'd suggest reading the link and forming you're own
opinions on him. I myself found the tutorial brought on convincing
points, but more than that I found …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__8__eU80cOXYJfRz3xdJ__9JA.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I read a very interesting &lt;a href="https://robertpaulwolff.blogspot.co.uk/2011/10/one-dimensional-man-mini-tutorial-part.html"&gt;mini-tutorial on Marcuse&lt;/a&gt;
and his book One-Dimensional Man, an apparently brilliant merge of both
Freud and Marx. I'd suggest reading the link and forming you're own
opinions on him. I myself found the tutorial brought on convincing
points, but more than that I found myself falling back a re-ignition of
my own rambling interest in philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having been away from it for quite some time, it was nice to put another
filter onto reality, to take a political or socio-economic theory, sit
it behind my eyes and consider the world around me. If it's worth
reading I almost always gain new insights and it helps to formalise my
viewpoints and more importantly take action. I'm well aware I'm not
nearly smart enough to contribute to such a debate but I can make
significant personal decisions with a renewed clarity. Mindfulness is a
wonderful thing, but I'm beginning to realise more and more there's an
extension to this. Not as a directly similar practice but a value in
deeper understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much like the mind-body awareness a daily meditation practice brings, we
are also within structures, processes and systems that demand our
awareness and not simply passive acceptance at face value. Do this and
we risk getting swept up into the norms and that's an easy way to get
manipulated without even realising it. Confused? Check out the link and
you'll understand.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Mindfulness"></category></entry><entry><title>Promoting mindfulness through the day</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/promoting-mindfulness-through-the-day-e294cbc78843.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2014-01-16:/promoting-mindfulness-through-the-day-e294cbc78843.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over the last year I've been cultivating a mindfulness habit. Overall,
it has delivered great results. One of the aspects I've been less than
happy with however, is my ability to carry that mindful state with me
throughout the day. I'm unsure if it's because I'm a programmer and my …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over the last year I've been cultivating a mindfulness habit. Overall,
it has delivered great results. One of the aspects I've been less than
happy with however, is my ability to carry that mindful state with me
throughout the day. I'm unsure if it's because I'm a programmer and my
mind has to be so wrapped up in what I'm doing that mindfulness will
inevitably get pushed out or if it's simply that full-day mindfulness
isn't possible for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lately I've been also trying to drink more water, so I figured I would attempt to combine both and see if there could be any benefits to. I do have to admit, the last few weeks that drinking water had led to more mindful triggers throughout the day. Having my own water bottle, drinking from it, re-filling it has led to me being more present at least during certain moments of the day. It's been quite pleasing and am hoping to maintain this habit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__ngn__AEEBDcU9udW96GF8YQ__2x.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Mindfulness"></category></entry><entry><title>Tired meditation</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/tired-meditation-47ed1f094c04.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2013-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2013-07-25:/tired-meditation-47ed1f094c04.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;When I imagine myself doing meditation, I see myself almost leaping out of bed with boundless energy, followed by a full and focused period of breathing exercises. Nothing could be further from the truth. Right now I'm working through the Discovery Series on Headspace and it's focusing more on looking …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When I imagine myself doing meditation, I see myself almost leaping out of bed with boundless energy, followed by a full and focused period of breathing exercises. Nothing could be further from the truth. Right now I'm working through the Discovery Series on Headspace and it's focusing more on looking at your body and how it feels. Now, a lot of what the meditation suggests is, is to use focus to alleviate the negative
feelings that occur in your body. This is great and it does help a lot but I have a fairly recurring and distracting problem when meditation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You see, because I see meditation as a fundamental habit I always start
my day with it. The problem is that a lot of the time I feel like utter
crap getting out of bed. I'm not the type to leap out of bed, it's a struggle. When I'm sitting and focused internally I notice each and every miserable feeling my body goes through at the start of the day. Say I haven't gotten a good nights sleep, my eyes feel like they're on fire, I get random pains everywhere or sometimes I want to throw up. Oh, and my entire body just wants to slide back to being horizontal just for a few more minutes. This is the ugly side of meditation you don't imagine when you conjure up the image of a yogi sitting cross-legged focused intensely on nothing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My tactics for this are really straight-forward, before I start on the
fundamental habit, I now do two things. A few quick stretches for just a
minute or two and I wash my face. It sounds so simple but the effects
are drastic. It seems to start the waking cycle a little faster, I'm
that little bit more alert and awake. The focus of the meditation moves
from post-bed pains to the more of the legitmate pains/pleasures I'm
more likely to feel during the day. On top of that, the combination
builds up more of the relaxed focus that meditation tries to teach you.
So if you're struggling with meditation in the morning give that a
shot. Also, if there's persistent pains that occur during meditation and
they can be alleviated, do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It may be worth going to see a physio/doctor and if you're really
struggling to alleviate pain. Sometimes the solution can be a yoga
routine, which is simply another form of meditation. Focus is all well and good, but when solvable problems take over your meditation completely, it's a no-brainer. Solve them and
move onto other more difficult issues.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Mindfulness"></category></entry><entry><title>Reducing my possesions</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/reducing-my-possesions-e8ccf43e94ba.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-04-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2011-04-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2011-04-29:/reducing-my-possesions-e8ccf43e94ba.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I decided at the start of the year to reduce my possesions purely as I
found myself incredibly weighted down by what I owned. Unwatched DVDs,
unplayed video games, unread books even unworn clothes do take a mental
toll when deciding what to do with your day, it's pointless guilt …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I decided at the start of the year to reduce my possesions purely as I
found myself incredibly weighted down by what I owned. Unwatched DVDs,
unplayed video games, unread books even unworn clothes do take a mental
toll when deciding what to do with your day, it's pointless guilt from
overconsumption. So, I decided to sell/donate as much as I could stand
and see where it left me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's all based on the &lt;a href="http://mnmlist.com/50-things/"&gt;50 Things challenge&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href="http://mnmlist.com/"&gt;mnmlst&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I won't bother listing what I've gotten rid of, but it certainly was
quite a lot and I do certainly get an incrediby light sense when I look
in my wardrobe and see only a few t-shirts all of which I'm happy to
wear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's my list. It doesn't include things that are apart of the
house(TV, shredders etc).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Tech&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lumux TZ10 Camera&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Android Phone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Philips 21 inch monitor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Clothes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slazenger T-Shirt(Navy)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slazenger T-Shirt(Navy)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slazenger T-Shirt(Red)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slazenger T-Shirt(Blue)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slazenger T-Shirt(Black)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shirt-Blue Check&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shirt-Red Check&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shirt-Black Check&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blue Jeans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blue Jeans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shorts-Green&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nike-Red Hoodie&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blue Hoodie&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Black coat&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Suit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Karrimor Shoes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nike Runners&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adidas Astro-Turf Boots&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Black Shoes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Converse Shoes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Socks(A group)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Underwear(A group)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Running shorts Navy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Running shorts Black&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Running Under-Shorts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pyjamas Trousers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pyjamas Shorts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fleecy Jumper Black&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Misc&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Umbrella&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chessboard&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fender Stratocaster w/ Mini Vox Amp&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Backpack&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clerks Lunchbox&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leathermann&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pen-Knife&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wallet Band&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notebook&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notepad&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Folder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spongebob Moneybox&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Family Photo-Album&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bonsai&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tree&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wire&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spatula&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clippers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brush&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Watering Can&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sprayer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Drawing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notepad(Large)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pencil-Set&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Charcoal-Set&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Travel&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rolling Bag&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Toiletries Case&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Toiletries&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gilette Tech Ball DE Razor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shaving Brush&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Left Hand Side of the Brain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oxford Dictionary of Philosophy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Elements of Style&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Philosophy Bites&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Logical Chess:Move by Move&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;History of Western Philosophy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Mythical Man Month&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Pragmatic Programmer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Code Complete&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll keep updating this as I decide to get rid of more. Hopefully by the
end of the year I'll be down to the magic number.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Removed&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oxford English Dictionary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Walden&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Macbook&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grey Hoodie&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wireless Keyboard&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1TB Iomega Hard Disk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Short-Sleeved Shirt White&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shirt-Green Check&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Long black coat&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Travel Pillow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dune&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Filio&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shorts-Blue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notepad(Small)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sleeping Sheet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bosch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Signposts to Elsewhere&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rain-Jacket&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Complicity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Republic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Programming Collective Intelligence&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Python Reference&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bonsai Basics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Karl Marx:Selected Writings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Treastise of Government&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Brief History of Philosophy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Running T-Shirt White&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arsenal Jersey&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jumper Navy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jumper Black&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Walnut Desk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Books&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You'll notice quite a few books, I find that while the kindle is great
for reading novels, when studying I tend to scribble all over my books
and the kindle really wasn't a suitable replacement. I also use a lot of
study-aid books especially when reading weighty topics. As a result I
still usually buy a copy of the book and download the study aid onto my
kindle. So I am reducing my book intake and I still get to write to my
hearts content! I do still intend to get rid of more books though, in
the end I always try to retain the message of a book in a mindmap, so
really keeping the book long after it's been read is pointless. If I
need to re-read a book I own I can grab a digital copy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Benefits&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other than a pleasant feeling of lightness from minimising your
possesions, you begin to value your purchasing decisions more. For
example instead of thoughtless buying another video game that'd I never
get around to playing, I sold my PS3 and picked up a small chess set and
began to learn the more advanced aspects of the game. I'm enjoying it so
much more. I value the longer term enjoyment from chess as opposed to
the transient pleasure of video games. It's something I'd never consider
before attempting this 50 items system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another obvious benefit is my one in one out system, whereby I need to
get rid of something on that list to replace what I've bought. As a
result I spend far less and value what I have more. When you reflect
seriously on what you spend you begin to notice how much excess we
burden ourselves with. Upon realising this I decided to pick up a copy
of The Life You Can Save by Peter Singer and after reading it I decided
to take as much of the money I was needlessly spending and put it to
charity. If you're considering doing the same I'd stronly suggest
checking out &lt;a href="https://www.givewell.org"&gt;givewell&lt;/a&gt; a fantastic charity review site and the &lt;a href="https://www.thelifeyoucansave.org"&gt;life you can
save&lt;/a&gt;, they might just inspire you to do something very cool!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Tips/Tricks&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've found that whilst I've managed to cut down on my superfluous items
I always came across more useless junk. I've started place all these
junk items on a shelf near the door, once I'd collected enough stuff I
go to the charity shop or recycling depo and get rid of everything. I
found it much easier to put things on the shelf than to immediately give
it away, if you find yourself attached to things unnecessarily it might
be a useful step to take&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Mindfulness"></category></entry></feed>