<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Shane Dowling - Productivity</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://shanedowling.com/feeds/productivity.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://shanedowling.com/</id><updated>2014-02-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><subtitle>Shane Dowling</subtitle><entry><title>A tip for introducing new habits</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/a-tip-for-introducing-new-habits-79186124433a.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-02-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-02-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2014-02-13:/a-tip-for-introducing-new-habits-79186124433a.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;After reading up on &lt;a href="https://pragprog.com/book/ahptl/pragmatic-thinking-and-learning"&gt;Pragmatic Thinking and Learning&lt;/a&gt;
I decided I would implement a habit called Morning Pages. Effectively
you commit to writing several pages of writing each and every morning,
for me I intended to write a blog post unit each day, and decide which
ones were worthy enough …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After reading up on &lt;a href="https://pragprog.com/book/ahptl/pragmatic-thinking-and-learning"&gt;Pragmatic Thinking and Learning&lt;/a&gt;
I decided I would implement a habit called Morning Pages. Effectively
you commit to writing several pages of writing each and every morning,
for me I intended to write a blog post unit each day, and decide which
ones were worthy enough of sharing towards the end of the week. I was
building up a healthy morning routine and figured one more habit
wouldn’t be too much to ask of myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I failed. Repeatedly. Two months in and I’d managed about five totally
random mornings of writing. All of them on weekends. It kept feeling
non-essential compared to my other habits and I felt like the pressure
of getting to work at a reasonable hour build up as I sat down to try
and write. I simply couldn’t commit and I couldn’t focus on writing.
So, in this sorry state I figured out a great way to introduce new
habits that actually immediately worked for me. &lt;strong&gt;All new habits are
done first.&lt;/strong&gt; Simple as that, whenever you have a routine or when you’re about to knuckle down and be productive always start with your newest
habit. It’s the one you have the most tenuous hold on and should be
prioritised accordingly until it can become an establish part of your
routine. I’ve been writing every morning for about a month and a half
now and I’ve only missed one day(due to extreme tiredness). Also because it’s the first thing I do when I wake, I’ve started to incorporate
dreams into creative writing, it’s been very rewarding actually. I think
this habit is here to stay.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Productivity"></category></entry><entry><title>Precision Nutrition Trail Fast</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/precision-nutrition-trail-fast-88a4c01976d5.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2014-02-06:/precision-nutrition-trail-fast-88a4c01976d5.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I went through the &lt;a href="https://www.precisionnutrition.com/intermittent-fasting/chapter-1"&gt;precision nutrition trial fast last&lt;/a&gt; Sunday, here’s a low-down on how things went through each of the steps. I had trialled this while out and about in central London, but failed at around 5pm, I was disorganised and feeling incredibly dizzy from the crowds and …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I went through the &lt;a href="https://www.precisionnutrition.com/intermittent-fasting/chapter-1"&gt;precision nutrition trial fast last&lt;/a&gt; Sunday, here’s a low-down on how things went through each of the steps. I had trialled this while out and about in central London, but failed at around 5pm, I was disorganised and feeling incredibly dizzy from the crowds and noise, so this time I planned ahead and did this from home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;10 PM Saturday&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Had a late dinner at the wonderful Chaat on RedChurch Street in Shoreditch. May as well have an epic last meal, right? The advantage of the late final meal was that I actually managed to ramble in from the street and only waited a minute for a table. I didn’t over-do it in terms of food. I often get hungrier the next morning if I eat a huge meal the night before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;9 AM Saturday&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;- Ran a 10k. This is the part I’m a little apprehensive about. I’m doing a training program to build up to my next half marathon, which includes 10k-15k runs on Sundays. I’m always starving after a run(naturally), so I’m curious to know how my body will tackle this. I also figure if this is a trial fast I should trial it during real life conditions, which would regularly include running.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;10 AM&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;- The post-run hunger has come over me, but the “breakfast” while not
 the most satisfying I’ve ever has taken the edge off.
 mL (1 cup) of green tea and 5 grams BCAA (branched chain amino acids) powder (or take 5 capsules).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1PM&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;- Hunger cravings are on the up causing me to feel a little tender, but
 short breathing exercise and keeping busy seem to help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2PM&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;- I’ve been a vegetarian for over three years, why do I still imagine
 greasy burgers when I get hunger pains?
- Had a cigar to help things along. Is that cheating?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2:30PM&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beginning to get dizzy/spacy, the cigar may be the source. I’ve been using my standing desk and been walking constantly since the morning but now I seem to want prolonged sitting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3PM&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess you’d call this lunchtime, same intake as breakfast. It takes
 the edge off a little. Can’t really sit still anymore, I’m just pacing around but feeling light-headed at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;6PM&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watching movies at the moment which seems to keep the hunger at bay. It’s very much hitting a wall then finding energy from somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;9PM&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bailing an hour early and having a small cup of soup. Put frankly, I felt like I’ve had a temperature for the last few hours and all my body wanted was something wholesome in it, my resistance has totally fallen apart. I felt like I was coming down with an illness and I was worried the lack of food may have brought down my immune system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The illness effect was probably entirely psychosomatic, but I did feel
terrible the last few hours, the light spacious feeling I had earlier in
the day turned pretty horrible. I’d like to repeat this experiment
without the 10km run beforehand and see how it goes. One thing is for
sure, I have a completely new respect for anyone who can regularly fast.
The ways in which this hit my willpower were completely surprising.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Productivity"></category></entry><entry><title>Sleep as the fundamental habit</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/sleep-as-the-fundamental-habit-f9590f13c013.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2014-01-09:/sleep-as-the-fundamental-habit-f9590f13c013.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__8iAA__DadoqBnceEck3kraw__2x.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leo Babuta describes meditation as the fundamental habit, the underlying habits beneath all others. Personally, I disagree. I wrote recently on how I cope with meditation when you haven’t had a particularly good nights sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Realistically washing your face is like taking painkillers after a
serious injury, it’s …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__8iAA__DadoqBnceEck3kraw__2x.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leo Babuta describes meditation as the fundamental habit, the underlying habits beneath all others. Personally, I disagree. I wrote recently on how I cope with meditation when you haven’t had a particularly good nights sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Realistically washing your face is like taking painkillers after a
serious injury, it’s only painting over the cracks of a deeper problem.
Meditation and mindfulness truly can unlock the potential of your day,
but a good nights rests can even more. Sleep is a physical process that
underlies every waking moment. So to actively take the time to develop
good sleep habits should improve every other aspect in your life,
including meditation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I only began to appreciate a good sleep routine when it was gone. Four
months of hopping from towns, cities and countries has destroyed my good sleeping habits. I can’t remember the last time I slept in the same bedmore than two nights in a row. I return to a more permanent base soon enough but even now I’m trying to develop a rough sleep routine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analyzing your sleep patterns and logging how you feel is a great way to
discover what works for you. How many hours do you need? When is your ideal wind-down time? Be curious about it. To help I found &lt;a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.urbandroid.sleep"&gt;Sleep as Android&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://pzizz.com/"&gt;Pzizz&lt;/a&gt;, they’re very helpful but just being curious and exploring your sleeping patterns can do wonders for your well-being. Nailing down a good sleeping habit has been one of the biggest fundamental improvements I’ve made, everything flows from there.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Productivity"></category></entry><entry><title>GYPYSs and unrealistic expectations</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/gypyss-and-unrealistic-expectations-f67a4927d9d6.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2014-01-01:/gypyss-and-unrealistic-expectations-f67a4927d9d6.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/wait-but-why/generation-y-unhappy_b_3930620.html"&gt;This article&lt;/a&gt; was shared with me recently, it’s an excellent read and provides some good reasoning for why people feel that vague sense of living an unaccomplished life. I’ll admit it, I am most definitely a Gypsy. My garden right now it full of flowers of unrealistic expectations …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/wait-but-why/generation-y-unhappy_b_3930620.html"&gt;This article&lt;/a&gt; was shared with me recently, it’s an excellent read and provides some good reasoning for why people feel that vague sense of living an unaccomplished life. I’ll admit it, I am most definitely a Gypsy. My garden right now it full of flowers of unrealistic expectations. I’d begun to discover this while meditating and watching my emotions daily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__dgV1eOnLLrwiaafzuZ__klg__2x.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href="https://www.headspace.com/"&gt;Headspace&lt;/a&gt; there’s a section called the discovery series. You begin to focus on watching your emotions throughout the day and when your mind gets distracted and wanders. More specifically you watch the ways in which you wish things were different. You begin to notice the gulf between reality and fantasy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first I spotted the fantasties and dismissed them entirely. I was
disappointed in myself for being so ridiculous and unrealistic. However,
soon enough I realised that those fantasties had some utility. They
could potentially shape long term goals. In &lt;a href="https://pragprog.com/book/ahptl/pragmatic-thinking-and-learning"&gt;Pragmatic Thinking and
Learning&lt;/a&gt; (a book I’d highly recommend), there is a concept called the Pragmatic Investment Plan, where you essentially break down your longer term goals into where you want to be in say 5 years time and that’s broken down into where you want to be in a year and what tasks can you do right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take a wild guess at where I found the inspiration for where I wanted to
be in 5 years time? It’s pretty fun breaking down some of your dreams
into a potentially attainable setting of SMART goals. Say you’ve started to get into drawing and you want others to see and possibly be moved by your work. Right now you still suck but you dream of the day when something you created was in a gallery or an exhibition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, you’ve found your five year SMART goal. You could have year one be to create a blog and regularly publish a new piece of work. The thing right now you could do is grab that drawing book you held off buying. If nothing else, it’s a start. A few months down the line you might realise you’re not that into drawing or you’re totally into it. Either way to get to that point and either fulfill or dismiss the fantasy it starts with trying it on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sure, we all fantasise about about the craziest things and it’s
sometimes even embarrassing, but there’s real insight there. Sit down
with these fantasies and break them down into attainable chunks, then
act on those chunks. You’ll get a hell of a lot farther than just
sitting there wishing things were different.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Productivity"></category></entry><entry><title>Performance gains by altering your routine</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/performance-gains-by-altering-your-routine-f44365b8972b.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2013-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2013-12-30:/performance-gains-by-altering-your-routine-f44365b8972b.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the mornings I had a very structured routine. The first thing I would
do is meditate as for me, all other habits flow from this. Then after my
meditation I would either go for a run or do some dumbbell based
strength exercises. The reasoning being that as exercising …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the mornings I had a very structured routine. The first thing I would
do is meditate as for me, all other habits flow from this. Then after my
meditation I would either go for a run or do some dumbbell based
strength exercises. The reasoning being that as exercising was also a
quiet periods, I could try extending the mindfulness and clarity gained
from meditation into my exercises and have a better chance of remaining mindful throughout the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typically, this routine has worked out exactly the same every time.
Meaning that I would always feel somewhat tired while meditating and a niggling doubt would re-occur that I was too tired to perform my
meditations effectively. You get a lot of space to dwell on these doubts
while meditating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a response, for a few days I started to exercise before meditation
and I must admit the effect were dramatic. Meditation after running is
akin to trying to focus after taking a pile of happy pills. The
meditation feels better, it seems easier and I’m very positive
throughout the whole experience. I also discovered that meditation
following exercise is a great way to generate ideas. Especially with
writing, I permanently feel like I’m going to run out of ideas but when
you fill yourself with positive energy and then try to sit and think,
the ideas just seemed to flow. It could be simply a mixture of
endorphines being positivity and physical tiredness taking away fears of
having bad idea, whatever it is it seems to be the ideal mental state
for idea generating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, this all sounds very positive but I must admit this alteration of
my routine will only be used sparingly. Firstly, I got distracted quite
a lot with ideas during the meditation, forcing me to write them down
and effectively breaking my focus. Some my my hand would be completely covered in pen marks after a meditation. That’s great, every so often but it got frustrating pretty quickly having to break focus over and over. Secondly, it’s wonderful to watch your breath while you’re full of positive “I love life” energy but that’s not exactly reflective of my
mood throughout the day and when your hope is to extend mindfulness to the rest of your day you want to develop an expectation that you’re only mindful when your very positive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I do fully intend to use this ordering when I’m running low on
ideas but I shall limit it only to then. I’m glad I made the discovery
and intend to continually try new alterations and note the consequences.
So if you’ve got some daily rituals or routines, mix them up and see if
you can gain some unexpected performance gains.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Productivity"></category></entry><entry><title>GSD 2 — Retaining Focus</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/gsd-2-retaining-focus-98ffdabf2a75.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-12-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2013-12-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2013-12-27:/gsd-2-retaining-focus-98ffdabf2a75.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://xmonad.org/"&gt;Xmonad&lt;/a&gt; - Xmonad is a Haskell based window
manager for both Linux and Mac(sorry Windows users). It’s highly
configurable but for me it’s lack of features and application bar crap
is a real advantage. The application your currently working with takes
up the entirety of the screen and …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://xmonad.org/"&gt;Xmonad&lt;/a&gt; - Xmonad is a Haskell based window
manager for both Linux and Mac(sorry Windows users). It’s highly
configurable but for me it’s lack of features and application bar crap
is a real advantage. The application your currently working with takes
up the entirety of the screen and you navigate to other applications
using keyboard shortcuts. Using this and disabling notifications in your
IM/Email/whatever clients forces you to work on the task in front of
you. It’s very pleasing to use after a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.focusatwill.com/"&gt;Focusatwill&lt;/a&gt; - I’ve been a big fan of using the Pomodoro technique and I use focusatwill as an extension to it. Effectively it’s a timer
that plays music that apparently helps keep you focused. Personally I’ve found it quite effective. It pushes for 100 minute stints of focused work before taking a break. As a coder I’m a big fan of this. 25 minute pomodoros got really distracting and were a pain to maintain after a while. 100 minutes lets me keep my mind on whatever level of the coding stack I’m currently on for longer periods. Even focusatwill states that it can take 20 minutes to accumulate enough to begin focus. Plus, if you’re skeptical there’s a free trial period.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Productivity"></category></entry><entry><title>GSD 3 — Keeping your habits in mind</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/gsd-3-keeping-your-habits-in-mind-ded639ef1e39.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-12-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2013-12-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2013-12-27:/gsd-3-keeping-your-habits-in-mind-ded639ef1e39.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So you’ve removed your distractions and figured out how to maintain
focus. You’ve a set of good habits you’d like to being implementing.
Well firstly, read &lt;a href="https://zenhabits.net/sticky/"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;. Don’t jump head first into habits you’ve never gone through before. You’re expectations will be too high …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So you’ve removed your distractions and figured out how to maintain
focus. You’ve a set of good habits you’d like to being implementing.
Well firstly, read &lt;a href="https://zenhabits.net/sticky/"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;. Don’t jump head first into habits you’ve never gone through before. You’re expectations will be too high and sadly, you’ll likely fail. Patience is a virtue.
So, after you’ve chosen the habit you’d like to begin with, here are
some tools to help keep you focused on those good habits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=uk.amimetic.habits"&gt;Habit Streak&lt;/a&gt; - This app helps you achieve your goals with daily habit reminders. The focus here is on streaks. Define habits you can achieve everyday. Personally I find slightly vague is good. For example I don’t intend to run everyday(you need downtime from running), so instead I have a habit to exercise everyday. So I alternate running with strength exercises.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cron-Jobs - Yup, straight up cron-jobs are a great way to remind you to keep your good habits in mind. Make sure you have zenity installed and add this to your local cron with crontab -e. I also use cronjobs to automatically shut down my computer in the evening to prevent me working late and to properly wind-down ensuring a good sleep habit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;/10 * &lt;/em&gt; * * export DISPLAY=:0 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; /usr/bin/zenity -info-text=”Don’t forget that uber important habit”&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Productivity"></category></entry><entry><title>GSD 4 — Reviewing</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/gsd-4-reviewing-8a7ab553a72f.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-12-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2013-12-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2013-12-27:/gsd-4-reviewing-8a7ab553a72f.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So the final process I use to help me get shit done is reviewing. Each
week I do a fairly lengthy review of the last week. I see what habits
have been successful and which have been a struggle to maintain. I look
to see if there are appropriate alterations …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So the final process I use to help me get shit done is reviewing. Each
week I do a fairly lengthy review of the last week. I see what habits
have been successful and which have been a struggle to maintain. I look
to see if there are appropriate alterations I can use to help improve.
Here’s a list of the things I tend to analyse while reviewing, and the
questions I’ve asked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.rescuetime.com/"&gt;RescueTime&lt;/a&gt; - What have I procrastinated on this week? What peak times do I tend to be productive on my computer and when are the troughs? Can I replace this behavior with something slightly more useful?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.habitstreak.com/"&gt;Habit Streak&lt;/a&gt; - This one I find very important. What habits have I maintained and what have failed? I ask myself in a gentle self-analytical way why I couldn’t maintain certain habits and what conditions I can change to improve my chances. Maybe the habits are simply not maintainable? Do I need to stop others and make specific time for new ones? Should I change my schedule? Reviewing is key to maintaining habits like these and the app I use is really straight-forward, exactly what I need.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.urbandroid.sleep"&gt;Sleep as Android&lt;/a&gt;— Am I still maintaining a good sleep habit? Sometimes I try alterations to my routine and work out if there’s a positive or negative effect to my day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Todo List -I just use a notepad and sometimes just dump ideas into Evernote. At the end of the week I collect them up and add them to a todo list or ditch them. Saying no and not indulging ideas you simply don’t have time for it key to this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.instapaper.com/"&gt;Instapaper&lt;/a&gt; - I do some gardening to my reading list and dump anything I felt may have been a valuable read at the time but on reflection isn’t. I have a tendency to throw everything and the kitchen sink at my reading list, so purging this down is essential.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gratefulness - I add in the things that I’m grateful for from the last week. Typically I try write these moments down during the week. It helps to re-affirm the things you find important and appreciate. By doing it and keeping the things you’re grateful for in your mind it helps the review become a more decisive and straightforward process, especially when you have a tendency to hang on to those ideas or wandering thoughts that really have no value.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Projects - What progress have I made in the last week? How has it stacked up compared to other weeks? Did I have a fluid week or was there blockers, how can I approach these if they occur again?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contacts - Are there contacts or people I’ve met recently that I wish to catch up or meet again?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally this is a rough list of what I look at and I’ve found the
process very revealing and incredibly useful. It provides me with a
framework that has kept me focused on my longer-term goals but also on my general health and how I can potentially make systematic improvements in smaller ways on a regular basis. These improvements will accrue and the benefits over time can be phenomenal.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Productivity"></category></entry><entry><title>Principles</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/principles-5cdc28ff6843.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-12-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2013-12-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2013-12-26:/principles-5cdc28ff6843.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Going to spend St.Stephen’s day going over &lt;a href="http://www.bwater.com/Uploads/FileManager/Principles/Bridgewater-Associates-Ray-Dalio-Principles.pdf"&gt;Dalio’s Principles&lt;/a&gt;. I always find the holidays a good time to get a high-level view of things.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Productivity"></category></entry><entry><title>GSD 1 — Reducing Distractions</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/gsd-1-reducing-distractions-a42c7b164ce0.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2013-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2013-08-03:/gsd-1-reducing-distractions-a42c7b164ce0.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Most of my distractions currently come from within. I hit up social
media or news sites. Also my email is a big time waster. I needed a way
to remain connected but while preventing regular access. Here’s what
helped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/viccherubini/get-shit-done"&gt;Get Shit Done&lt;/a&gt; — A cross platform OS level site blocker …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Most of my distractions currently come from within. I hit up social
media or news sites. Also my email is a big time waster. I needed a way
to remain connected but while preventing regular access. Here’s what
helped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/viccherubini/get-shit-done"&gt;Get Shit Done&lt;/a&gt; — A cross platform OS level site blocker. Simply install the script, add your distracting sites and run ‘get-shit-done work’ in a terminal. You only notice sheer number of times you find yourself flicking to those distracting sites when a big error is thrown that the site is unavailable. It’s a learning experience. Your browser however, may cache URL lookups and you may still access distracting sites when I shouldn’t and visa-versa. On Firefox there is an extension called &lt;a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/dns-cache/"&gt;DNS
Cache&lt;/a&gt;. It allows you to prevent Firefox caching DNS entries, I presume this slows down URL requests but I barely noticed a difference and GSD now works as it should.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://status.constantcontact.com/nutshellmail/"&gt;Nutshellmail&lt;/a&gt;— Sends an email as often
as you’d like with all your Facebook/Twitter updates. You know you’ll
get an social media update at some point so why bother flicking over to
Facebook now?&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Productivity"></category></entry><entry><title>Getting Shit Done</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/getting-shit-done-99303b405d8c.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-08-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2013-08-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2013-08-01:/getting-shit-done-99303b405d8c.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I created a number of long term goals recently and have been trying to
work out a system within which I can continue to keep my focus on those long term goals and reduce procrastination. I try to promote a daily focus on long term tasks through reminders and regular …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I created a number of long term goals recently and have been trying to
work out a system within which I can continue to keep my focus on those long term goals and reduce procrastination. I try to promote a daily focus on long term tasks through reminders and regular reviews while reducing procrastination through a set of core tools. I tried multiple tools/tricks and what I’ll post a series on the tools and tricks I used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the topics I’ll post on(and link here):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://medium.com/brightpin/gsd-1-reducing-distractions-a42c7b164ce0?source=linkShare-c3fb4f3f97d3-1515858383"&gt;Reducing Distractions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://medium.com/p/98ffdabf2a75?source=linkShare-c3fb4f3f97d3-1515858422"&gt;Retaining Focus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://medium.com/p/ded639ef1e39?source=linkShare-c3fb4f3f97d3-1515858463"&gt;Keeping your habits in mind&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://medium.com/p/8a7ab553a72f?source=linkShare-c3fb4f3f97d3-1515858504"&gt;Reviewing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Productivity"></category></entry><entry><title>Just Keep Going</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/just-keep-going-eebcba9f4076.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-04-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2011-04-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2011-04-19:/just-keep-going-eebcba9f4076.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Productivity has never been my strong point. I’m the ultimate
procrastinator. I will literally do anything other than the task at
hand. In fact this post is likely being written purely as I don’t want
to study. But, the post itself is useful in it’s function to …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Productivity has never been my strong point. I’m the ultimate
procrastinator. I will literally do anything other than the task at
hand. In fact this post is likely being written purely as I don’t want
to study. But, the post itself is useful in it’s function to push me
forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve gotten attracted to a very simple idea of “Just keep going”. In my
head I imagine the Terminator, after being blown to bits, still getting
up. I suffer from “Goldilocks procrastination”, essentially everything
needs to be just right before anything can happen. On top of that
everything needs to remain perfect for me to maintain it. On paper it’s
insanely obvious that this will fail, but a lesson that’s taken me a
while to learn. If I don’t have all the study materials or if I miss a
run during the week and boom, never again. What’s the point?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So after a huge number of failures I’m moving onto my very light, very
simple “just keep going”. No fancy todo list software, no complicated
GTD systems, no goal tracking software. Literally none of them have
worked for me, purely as I can’t forgive myself for the small failures.
I want to wake up in the morning, pull out a notepad, write whatever
inspires me that day and do it. If I miss a run or am missing something
that’s barely preventing me from doing my task, it’s irrelevant. It’s
the next opportunity that’s important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although a few months in these are my overall goals for 2011&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Become an early riser&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reduce my possesions(50 or less)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weekly blog post here&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Donate more money and time to charity&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Attempt a major philosophical write-up, with intention to apply for a Masters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Become a vegetarian&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Run a 10k(Yeah I’m unfit)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll expand on each of these as the weeks go on. I don’t doubt that this
will be difficult, right now I hold down two jobs which sucks up a huge
amount of time, but by documenting how I’m progressing and the
techniques I use to maintain motivation and find time I hope it’ll help
me and others.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Productivity"></category></entry><entry><title>For any active del.icio.us users I’d highly recommend…</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/for-any-active-del-icio-us-users-id-highly-recommend-d89cee8880c7.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2010-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2010-12-17:/for-any-active-del-icio-us-users-id-highly-recommend-d89cee8880c7.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://pinboard.in" title="http://pinboard.in"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pinboard: social bookmarking for introverts&lt;/strong&gt;
_For a few more bucks a year, Pinboard offers an archiving service which saves a copy of everything you bookmark, gives…_pinboard.in&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="http://pinboard.in"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Productivity"></category></entry><entry><title>Top 10 webapps for programmers</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/top-10-webapps-for-programmers-38c75fba4a63.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-02-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2010-02-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2010-02-16:/top-10-webapps-for-programmers-38c75fba4a63.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h3&gt;Evernote&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although I use evernote as my brain online for everthing, it is
incredibly useful for programmers too. Where I work things like
requirements can be captured on almost anything, so snapping photos of
whiteboards/notepads/beer mats that become OCR searchable is very handy.
On top of that it …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;Evernote&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although I use evernote as my brain online for everthing, it is
incredibly useful for programmers too. Where I work things like
requirements can be captured on almost anything, so snapping photos of
whiteboards/notepads/beer mats that become OCR searchable is very handy.
On top of that it’s nice to have all notes auto stored up on the web(I’d
have a fit if I lost my developer diary over a hard drive crash). The
client application for evernote could be better and I’d consider
Microsoft’s OneNote a much better application but Evernote does
everything I need it too. The killer feature being the iPhone app that
lets me capture text, voice and snapshots everywhere. Coupled with JotNot it gives me a very powerful information capturing device that I simply cannot live without. This is one of the truly killer apps for my iPhone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Dropbox&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why does my hard-drive always die the evening I forget to push my code
up to the git server? Store all code/config files/documents up on a
server always. The benefits are stupidly obvious. It’s soon after
this realise you can start adding free little tricks that you didn’t
think possible. Another plus, I don’t have a static ip with my broadband at home(dyndns doesn’t work due to my isp’s infrastructure, a massive mesh NAT) so &lt;a href="http://lifehacker.com/5175362/start-bittorrent-downloads-at-home-from-any-computer-with-dropbox"&gt;here’s&lt;/a&gt; a cool trick for easily torrenting(or in my case usenetting) files remotely. There’s also something very nice about being all to pull up
any of my important files anywhere there’s a web browser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Gmail&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes it rocks, despite Buzz.. Filters, label and keyboard shortcuts have made this such an obvious choice it’s not even funny. I’d almost forgotten to add Gmail to the list it’s become such an integrated part of my web-use. The programmer related benefits are dissimilar to general user benefits, but thing extended features like keyboard shortcuts etc I probably only of real benefit to the techies who are the only ones bothered to read up on these features. Other than that there’s little to say, odds are I’d mostly be preaching to the converted anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Stackoverflow&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not exactly a web-app but something most programmers cannot live without
and it’s web-based. Arguably this could be number one , but personally I
don’t use this resource as much as the above three. Have a programming
question, odds are insanely high it’ll be answered here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Google Reader&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve all got to keep up with the latest developments in our industry.
Coding Horror, A list apart, trivium, proggit and Bertrand Meyer’s blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also reader has a new feature that supports updates on sites that don’t
actually support RSS(some might question the point in RSS with features
like this….). This feature’s very handy for one of my favourite programmer sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Mindmeister&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use a hell of a lot of mindmaps for storing programming related
knowledge. Almost every technical book I read has mindmaps associated. I
like building mindmaps, it forces me to have a 2nd thought on the
content I’m reading and I have a less painless way of reviewing what
I’ve read. To be honest, mindmeister as an application isn’t perfect. It
doesn’t have folders or any decently readable way of labelling mindmaps.
Very annoying when you’ve got tons of mindmaps to sort through. I’d love
to say that the fairly expensive iPhone app makes up for this(not sure
why it couldn’t be free considering it’s a subscription based service),
but the app for me is almost worthless. There’s nothing wrong with the
app in itself it’s just not a pleasant experience browsing/editing
mindmaps on your iPhone. It seems like I’m singing the praises of
mindmaps over mindmeister itself but other than these few issues
mindmeister is a solid application. As it’s online sharing mindmaps is
also a very handy feature. But if sharing/accessibilty
anywhere doesn’t matter to you I’d recommend something like FreeMind for all your mindmapping needs, even keeping your local mindmaps synced on Dropbox could suit you just fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Pinboard&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pinboard is a very nice online bookmark storage. Very, very simple
bookmarking/to-read lists, fantastically simple tagging features and the
ability to add bookmarks from emails makes this a great service. I keep
all my tech articles up on this service. For an extra charge all my
bookmarks become archived, meaning if I bookmark a site using pinboard
and the site in question goes down the page is still accessible from
pinboard forever. I could do the same using archive.org but having this
feature included in a bookmarking service really makes sense. On top of
that adding bookmarks from google reader, twitter, instapaper and
delicious really adds to the service. Highly recommended bookmarking
service for techies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Rememberthemilk&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember the milk takes the simple idea of todos lists, adds a set of
complex features(due dates, repeating tasks, tagging, folders, sharing
and a lot more). Adds in the ability to add tasks from almost anywhere.
IM, email, phone(if supported), widgets for almost anything(including
gmail), and many apps that support it(tasque/gnome do for linux or a
dashboard widget for osx) and you’ve got RTM. Yet the application itself
never gets bogged down in it’s complexity. ‘Buy milk today’ or ‘Buy milk tuesday’ or ‘Buy milk tue’ or the many other variants of dates and rtm
will likely be able to parse a date out of it. Other nice little tweaks like this makes RTM a great application for the programmer, as I mentioned in books like Passionate and Pragmatic Programmer Programmer there’s a lot of ‘Act On It’s’ some of them have different contexts, for example I might need to do a task weekly at home or do a task everyday in work. Using RTM to handle the adding of all these tasks makes things a &lt;strong&gt;lot&lt;/strong&gt; easier. I also use the pomodoro technique with RTM, using the tagging features I add estimates to my todos (e1,e2,e3) via tags. On top of all the other programming related todos I intend to do(including this post!) this service has made life a lot
easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Grooveshark&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s up for debate whether programmers should listen to music at work or not.
Personally I find music listening to music fine when I actually have to
code, but when it comes to creating a specification or stepping through
code listening to music is a very annoying distraction. When I do
listening to music I always use grooveshark. The UI leaves a lot to be
desired but there’s a music selection that’s 2nd to none, the playlists
are handy too depending on the mood you in. Feeling tired in the
morning? I have a wake-up playlist. Need some background music, there’s
a playlist for that! All very painless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;NutshellMail&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NutshellMail is a service that combines twitter, facebook, linkedin and
myspace updates into a single email that’s sent to you on a daily basis.
I questioned whether I’d use this service when signed up but I’ve come
to love this application. I follow a lot of developers on twitter and
some through facebook and it’s really nice to know your updates will
arrive at a certain time everyday. Instead of jumping on every few
hours, negatively impacting on my productivity, I have a focused time to
get myself updated on all the latest trends. The linkedin support is
handy too for keeping up to date on your professional news also. I could
have added twitter/linkedin to this top ten but at this stage I think
these websites go without saying(and they’re not exactly web
applications in the obvious sense).&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Productivity"></category></entry><entry><title>The Pomodoro Technique</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/the-pomodoro-technique-540acfc74681.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-01-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2010-01-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2010-01-18:/the-pomodoro-technique-540acfc74681.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__is__0RWADKvxo3s4JL63AyQ.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bought a &lt;a href="http://pragprog.com/titles/snfocus/pomodoro-technique-illustrated"&gt;book&lt;/a&gt;, basically because it was a GTD technique that came off the pragmatic bookshelf so I figured I’d give it a shot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Explanation:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give a very brief explanation of the technique. You have a sheet with &lt;strong&gt;Today’s Todos&lt;/strong&gt;, each time you do 25 minutes …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__is__0RWADKvxo3s4JL63AyQ.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bought a &lt;a href="http://pragprog.com/titles/snfocus/pomodoro-technique-illustrated"&gt;book&lt;/a&gt;, basically because it was a GTD technique that came off the pragmatic bookshelf so I figured I’d give it a shot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Explanation:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give a very brief explanation of the technique. You have a sheet with &lt;strong&gt;Today’s Todos&lt;/strong&gt;, each time you do 25 minutes
of work towards your todos you mark a ‘pomodoro’ and take a 5 minute
break. You then clock up pomodoros everyday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then every morning you pick from your \&lt;em&gt;\&lt;/em&gt;activity inventory\&lt;em&gt;\&lt;/em&gt;(an
unsorted list of todos), and pick the highest priority tasks, beside
each task should be an estimate of how many pomodoros it should take.
For exampleI had estimated 2pomdoros for this blog post. So when
selecting your pomodoros for the day you take your pomodoro average (sum
of all the pomodoros you’ve ever done divided by the number of days),
and don’t add more estimated pomodoros than your averages. So for
example my average could be 11 and I could have 3 high priority tasks
each estimated to take 5 pomodoros each, well clearly I would have to
add 2 and find a third that only took 1 pomodoro.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now clearly there’s more to it(they have managed to get several books
out of it). What you log all metrics on is called a report
sheet, so things I log are completed pomodoros, how far off my
estimates were, how many tasks did I fail to do today etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How I use it&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I fully commited to the technique both at home and at work. So in work I
have a large diary and some extra sheets, for my ‘personal’ stuff I use
a small moleskine diary to do the job. There have been dramatic results
on both accounts. In work I noticed a better structure coming around my
day. When people asked me for things I now always delay till I’ve
finished my pomodoro(the book explains how to handle interruptions),
then weight how important the new task was over what I’m currently
working on. I also find myself looking back very satisfied with the work
I’ve done for the day, a personal sense of accomplishment. On top of
that I like the fact if anyone did ask ‘what did you do all last week?’,
I could very easily give a breakdown on what tasks I was working on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like everything else discipline is key. I’ve even noticed myself
slipping the odd time. Say I finish a task in 20 minutes, the technique
calls for &lt;strong&gt;25&lt;/strong&gt; minutes of focused work, so you should now focus on
how you could do the task better or just improve on the task in some
way. This is fine depending on some tasks but some just can’t be done
any better. Going to the bathroom also becomes an interesting game as if
you need to go to the bathroom you should cancel the pomodoro, very
annoying when your bursting to go 22 minutes in. But youdo begin to
relish maintaining an average of sorts. It’s something you work towards
and try increase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;It’s flexible!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now however a problem has become apparent and this is where the
flexibility of the technique comes in. As a programmer I noticed a
‘flow’ that stops as soon as the timer does(that’s the point), I’ve
noticed 25 minutes is not nearly enough time so, as a compromise I can
now alter how my pomodoro works. For this week I’m going to try 2*25
minute programming pomodoros followed by a ten minute break. I could
increase the time of the pomodoro itself (say 25 to 50 minutes) but I’d
rather keep it 25 (busy work such as replying to emails etc doesn’t take
50 minutes).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Kaizen&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In essence the point of the technique is not the 25 minute burst is
actually something called Kaizen, meaning make small improvements
everyday. The constant reviewing of priorities and the daily review of
work done is the real value in this technique. I find measuring metrics
on your own productivity very powerful. If I find I’m doing more with
2*25 minute pomodoros, maybe I’ll try 4 and take a 20 minute break.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be honest I’ve actually found more use for this technique at home
than at work. With work there is structure to your day and deadlines
looming that will always motivate you. At home that project or that
programming language that you’ve wanted to do for months has no
deadlines and just doesn’t magically get done. With my moleskine(and
calendar reminders) I’ve got a constantmotivator to get things done and
do them better next time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can recommend this technique for anyone. To get started all it takes
is 3 sheets of paper(the activity inventory, the report sheet and
today’s todos) and some willpower. The book itself is great and would
highly recommend a purchase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Resources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A decent &lt;a href="http://docs.google.com/viewerurl%3Dhttp://www.pomodorotechnique.com/downloads/pomodoro_cheat_sheet.pdf"&gt;Online Cheatsheet&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/viewer?url=http%3A//www.pomodorotechnique.com/resources/cirillo/ThePomodoroTechnique_v1-3.pdf"&gt;free book&lt;/a&gt; written by the inventor of pomodoro(not the prag prog one I’ve read)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A mindmap I’ve done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one may read very strangely and how I do the technique may not work
for you, but the hats represent a different ‘focus’ and when my
productivity starts to wane imagining the hats works well. I would
suggest using the mindmap after reading the prag programmer book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Productivity"></category></entry></feed>