<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Shane Dowling - Random</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://shanedowling.com/feeds/random.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://shanedowling.com/</id><updated>2014-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><subtitle>Shane Dowling</subtitle><entry><title>Promoting mindfulness through the day</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/promoting-mindfulness-through-the-day-e294cbc78843.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2014-01-16:/promoting-mindfulness-through-the-day-e294cbc78843.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over the last year I’ve been cultivating a mindfulness habit. Overall,
it has delivered great results. One of the aspects I’ve been less than
happy with however, is my ability to carry that mindful state with me
throughout the day. I’m unsure if it’s because I …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over the last year I’ve been cultivating a mindfulness habit. Overall,
it has delivered great results. One of the aspects I’ve been less than
happy with however, is my ability to carry that mindful state with me
throughout the day. I’m unsure if it’s because I’m a programmer and my
mind has to be so wrapped up in what I’m doing that mindfulness will
inevitably get pushed out or if it’s simply that full-day mindfulness
isn’t possible for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lately I’ve been also trying to drink more water, so I figured I would attempt to combine both and see if there could be any benefits to. I do have to admit, the last few weeks that drinking water had led to more mindful triggers throughout the day. Having my own water bottle, drinking from it, re-filling it has led to me being more present at least during certain moments of the day. It’s been quite pleasing and am hoping to maintain this habit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__ngn__AEEBDcU9udW96GF8YQ__2x.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>Legitimate ways to support good movies</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/legitimate-ways-to-support-good-movies-2fb11e565d2d.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2014-01-11:/legitimate-ways-to-support-good-movies-2fb11e565d2d.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__xU2KVV__mC4quGix9krfh4A__2x.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I watched Akira Kurosawa’s Ikiru, after reading
through some of the Criterion info on Kurosawa I realised I’d watched a
bunch of his movies, I’m a huge fan of Seven Samurai.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Criterion Collection is a wonderful distribution company and I’m a
huge fan of …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__xU2KVV__mC4quGix9krfh4A__2x.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I watched Akira Kurosawa’s Ikiru, after reading
through some of the Criterion info on Kurosawa I realised I’d watched a
bunch of his movies, I’m a huge fan of Seven Samurai.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Criterion Collection is a wonderful distribution company and I’m a
huge fan of a number of their filmmakers, so much so that I wanted to
try and support the service more. Since I live fairly lightly in terms
of possessions I can’t really justify $40 on a DVD or Blu-Ray.
Especially since I’ll probably have moved elsewhere and be forced to
ditch the media before I can watch it a second time.
It’s a shame when distribution companies haven’t really adopted digital
distribution. I am aware that Criterion is on Hulu(now something else), but unfortunately as I’m not a US resident I can’t access/support it. If you are and can access it, I highly recommend checking out some of their movies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily I found a more old-school method to (in some small way) support Criterion movies. Near to where I work is a wonderful film-center called Close-Up that has a huge collection of both DVDs and books to rent. I’ll definitely be making use of it for the time being.
If you know of another way I can access the Criterion movies in the
EU(or just without a US credit-card), I’d love to know.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>Fasting</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/fasting-636565d35b97.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2014-01-03:/fasting-636565d35b97.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So I’ve been looking into intermittent fasting lately for several
reasons. Firstly, as a means to get a leaner physique, but also as I’m
looking to do more research into leaner more efficient eating as it is.
I’m also hoping a side effect of it will promote …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So I’ve been looking into intermittent fasting lately for several
reasons. Firstly, as a means to get a leaner physique, but also as I’m
looking to do more research into leaner more efficient eating as it is.
I’m also hoping a side effect of it will promote generally more mindful
eating habits. I came across quite a useful resource in www.precisionnutrition.com. They provide a trail fast plan, which I’m going to attempt once a week for the next few weeks to see how I react to fasting in general. During this time I’ll also do further research into fasting and hopefully work out a strategy that can work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re interested in the topic itself, I’d start with &lt;a href="https://www.precisionnutrition.com/intermittent-fasting"&gt;Experiments with Intermittent Fasting&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://leangains.com/"&gt;www.leangains.com&lt;/a&gt;. It seems the whole topic lacks any hard and fast rules. From my reading the only approach you can take is just try it, log the net effects and make alterations as you see fit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll log how things progress up here.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>Avoid anxiety with gratitude</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/avoid-anxiety-with-gratitude-65eb140928a5.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2014-01-02:/avoid-anxiety-with-gratitude-65eb140928a5.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Christmas holidays are coming to an end. The flash of New Years
fireworks are already beginning to dim in your memory. You might be
returning to work or you’ve already returned. Maybe you’re feeling
disgruntled and little sad that it all went by so fast and what …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Christmas holidays are coming to an end. The flash of New Years
fireworks are already beginning to dim in your memory. You might be
returning to work or you’ve already returned. Maybe you’re feeling
disgruntled and little sad that it all went by so fast and what do you
even have to show for yourself?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today while I was kicking off my morning writing routine, it was turning into a stream of conscious thought. Eventually I just happened to start creating list of all amazing things I’d done over the holidays. It came to a list of 21 events that I really and truly appreciated and there was certainly room for more if I’d thought about it. Looking back and forcing myself to remember them gave me an overwhelmingly contented feeling. The anxiety of returning to the post holiday work world and the fear of the Monday morning blues just faded into excitement about the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On top of that it’s also kicking off a new habit. Once a week while I’m
doing my morning writing I’m going to write up a list of everything I’m
grateful for over the last week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could not recommend doing this exercise more. Right now, just write
out the list of things you’re thankful for over the holidays. It’ll only
take a few minutes, I guarantee if you’re in the right frame of mind you
won’t regret it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>GYPYSs and unrealistic expectations</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/gypyss-and-unrealistic-expectations-f67a4927d9d6.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2014-01-01:/gypyss-and-unrealistic-expectations-f67a4927d9d6.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/wait-but-why/generation-y-unhappy_b_3930620.html"&gt;This article&lt;/a&gt; was shared with me recently, it’s an excellent read and provides some good reasoning for why people feel that vague sense of living an unaccomplished life. I’ll admit it, I am most definitely a Gypsy. My garden right now it full of flowers of unrealistic expectations …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/wait-but-why/generation-y-unhappy_b_3930620.html"&gt;This article&lt;/a&gt; was shared with me recently, it’s an excellent read and provides some good reasoning for why people feel that vague sense of living an unaccomplished life. I’ll admit it, I am most definitely a Gypsy. My garden right now it full of flowers of unrealistic expectations. I’d begun to discover this while meditating and watching my emotions daily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__dgV1eOnLLrwiaafzuZ__klg__2x.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href="https://www.headspace.com/"&gt;Headspace&lt;/a&gt; there’s a section called the discovery series. You begin to focus on watching your emotions throughout the day and when your mind gets distracted and wanders. More specifically you watch the ways in which you wish things were different. You begin to notice the gulf between reality and fantasy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first I spotted the fantasties and dismissed them entirely. I was
disappointed in myself for being so ridiculous and unrealistic. However,
soon enough I realised that those fantasties had some utility. They
could potentially shape long term goals. In &lt;a href="https://pragprog.com/book/ahptl/pragmatic-thinking-and-learning"&gt;Pragmatic Thinking and
Learning&lt;/a&gt; (a book I’d highly recommend), there is a concept called the Pragmatic Investment Plan, where you essentially break down your longer term goals into where you want to be in say 5 years time and that’s broken down into where you want to be in a year and what tasks can you do right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take a wild guess at where I found the inspiration for where I wanted to
be in 5 years time? It’s pretty fun breaking down some of your dreams
into a potentially attainable setting of SMART goals. Say you’ve started to get into drawing and you want others to see and possibly be moved by your work. Right now you still suck but you dream of the day when something you created was in a gallery or an exhibition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, you’ve found your five year SMART goal. You could have year one be to create a blog and regularly publish a new piece of work. The thing right now you could do is grab that drawing book you held off buying. If nothing else, it’s a start. A few months down the line you might realise you’re not that into drawing or you’re totally into it. Either way to get to that point and either fulfill or dismiss the fantasy it starts with trying it on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sure, we all fantasise about about the craziest things and it’s
sometimes even embarrassing, but there’s real insight there. Sit down
with these fantasies and break them down into attainable chunks, then
act on those chunks. You’ll get a hell of a lot farther than just
sitting there wishing things were different.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>The Freedom of Limits</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/the-freedom-of-limits-8677931d93e0.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-12-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2013-12-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2013-12-27:/the-freedom-of-limits-8677931d93e0.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over the course of this blog I intend to show how limitations can in
many ways bring positive changes in your life. While limitations can
appear under various guises(vegetarianism, minimalism) etc there is a
huge number of aspects in your life where you can benefit from limits,
just without …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over the course of this blog I intend to show how limitations can in
many ways bring positive changes in your life. While limitations can
appear under various guises(vegetarianism, minimalism) etc there is a
huge number of aspects in your life where you can benefit from limits,
just without the grandiose terms behind them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Why?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve ever attempted to meditate, you’ll realise that the human mind
is insane. It’s cannot help but leap from one random thought to the
next, like an irritated monkey in a cage. Seriously, just attempt to
think about your breath for any extended period and you’ll realise how
helpless you are to it(unless you’re trained of course). I recently watched a documentary by Adam Curtis called &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/eJ3RzGoQC4s"&gt;Century of the Self&lt;/a&gt;. If you haven’t watched it, I’d highly recommend it. Essentially it’s about the rise of the concept of the self and how corporations have sought to exploit it. I won’t go into too much detail but the important parts for this post are that during post-WW2 America, corporations had a genuine fear that they would run out of consumers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That, eventually everyone would have say a car and that would be it,
no-one else needs a car, or a washing machine or a winter coat(These
days it sounds laughable). In the 60s people began a new ‘me-centric’
way of behaving that both politicians and corporations had to adapt to.
Politicians did so by pandering to the middle class and corporations by
using market research, categorisation of consumers in lifestyles and
overbearing choice(Appealing to our emotions through marketing/advertising came before this, but is still relevant).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we all discovered we were very special ‘inner directed’ human beings,
corporations realised pretty quickly that they could exploit our newly
found desire by convincing people they could define themselves through
spending. Think about this for a second, when you bought what you’re
wearing right now what sort of questions did you ask. Is this durable?
Is it well made? Is the corporation an ethical entity? Will it survive
the elements? Heck even ‘Is this comfortable?’ can even get overlooked.
The point is we probably bought what we did as we had an emotional
response to the garment in question. It had a cool design or looked good on me, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are all perfectly valid things to want from a
garment, we gain emotional satisfaction by feeling like we made a unique choice. I’m not going to harp on about spending habits and I’ve shown how you can apply `limits to what you own `__ but it’s good to keep in mind how we can gain an emotional pleasure(and it can be exploited) simply by making a choice and that building a good choice/limitation balance can be beneficial to your wellbeing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you go throughout your day try to discover where you might have
undermined yourself through excessive choice, don’t judge yourself just
make a note of it. It might be a humungous todo list, or a wardrobe full
of t-shirts you don’t wear. What about a bookshelf full of books you
couldn’t string a sentence about, anything that hits you with a minor
twang of guilt as you pass. Using the bookshelf as an example, why not
just donate all the books and just start again, with a new limitation.
‘I can’t buy a new book till I’ve finished this one’, and see if it fits
or how about trying ‘I can only buy a book 7 days after I initially
wanted it’, anything to keep the crazy monkey in your head from reaching for the credit card or the buy now button. Whilst I’ve focused heavily on spending limitations they may not be the case. Here’s a list of some of the limitations I’ve enacted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Follow a maximum of podcasts(Down from 30 that I never listened to)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only two pages of apps on my iPhone(And no subfolders!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Five news-feeds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two books on my kindle at any one time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My 50 items goal generally keeps me from spending frivolously but that
doesn’t help with digital purchases. One laptop can contain hundreds of
distractions/guilts. I just got tired of seeing 500+ unread items in
google reader or 100+ podcast episodes I never got around to listening
to. We find it so easy to make a pleasing decision to better ourselves
but not to realise that it might be far more beneficial to us to undo
the original decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Effects&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I listen to all of my podcasts, I can read through my news-feeds
incredibly quickly. I don’t buy any old random app/book just because I
can at the click of a button. Through limitations I can better evaluate
what I truly want and as a result I value everything I have that much
more. It’s also made me value my own time more that whatever the source ‘hey it may not actually be worth my valuable time’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Tips/Tricks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try to re-evaluate your limitations when you find things piling up
again, I can’t stress this enough. I initially thought I could handle 20
news-feeds, not so much. So if you’re still snowed under with say four
podcasts, then try just one or maybe consider that you’re not a podcast
person. Try a new limit and see if the shoe fits and just keep at it,
eventually you’ll find the balance you’re looking for and maybe figure
out who you are a bit more.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>Happy Programmers Day!</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/happy-programmers-day-d14d9063b43f.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-09-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2013-09-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2013-09-13:/happy-programmers-day-d14d9063b43f.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Happy Programmers Day!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have a productive one…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or you’re sacked.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>Writing Less</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/writing-less-2757f83c3a48.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-07-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2013-07-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2013-07-29:/writing-less-2757f83c3a48.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I didn’t have time to write a short letter, so I wrote a long one
instead.” — Mark Twain&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lately I’ve been struggling with consistently writing. I find it
difficult to sit down in the morning and begin to write. Usually ideas
fall out of my head and I …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I didn’t have time to write a short letter, so I wrote a long one
instead.” — Mark Twain&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lately I’ve been struggling with consistently writing. I find it
difficult to sit down in the morning and begin to write. Usually ideas
fall out of my head and I get into a flow quite quickly but recently,
without a clear idea sitting in my head for a period of time I simply
can’t put pen to paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also just finished reading Charlie Brooker’s article on “`Reducing
my word emissions“ and I must admit some of his points are pretty convincing. There is a lot of noise on the internet and I suspect a lot of my unwillingness to return to writing is due to this.
I’m also working on a project similar to stackoverflow and I’m truly beginning to appreciate the format of the site. The internet simply has too much noise to signal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m going to try keep a hard limit on my posts of 200 words and see
if the limit can’t help the writers block.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>South Africa</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/south-africa-c688b9070707.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-07-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2013-07-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2013-07-20:/south-africa-c688b9070707.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’d been in Cape Town for two weeks beforehand, just remotely working
and doing some sightseeing around the area. So I had plenty of time for
prep for the trip and was pretty relaxed arriving at Ashanti Logde(where
the trip starts). The trip was booked through African Budget …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’d been in Cape Town for two weeks beforehand, just remotely working
and doing some sightseeing around the area. So I had plenty of time for
prep for the trip and was pretty relaxed arriving at Ashanti Logde(where
the trip starts). The trip was booked through African Budget
Safari’s which seemed to the cheapest option around. The dates I had originally planned to travel with(and booked) were unavailable and ABS happily changed my dates and gave me a heavy discount(about 25%). On top of that I declined the free activities in Cape Town, so I was given free upgrade at Ashanti to my own room. So I can definitely recommend African Budget Safari’s as an agent and also chance your arm and see what discounts you can get.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We met up with others on the trip and waited for the trip leaders. The
group was mostly mid-to-late twenties with two outliers in the
forties/fifties. Still an excellent result as I was worried the group
would have a much older average age. As I traveled I noticed the more
expensive tour groups had a lot of older people traveling and it sounded
like an awful time for younger folk traveling with them. I would highly
recommend finding out a rough average age of the people going on the
trip beforehand, our group was wonderful so living in each other’s
pockets really wasn’t a problem. However, if you get a bad group,
there’s not a lot you can do for 6–8 weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The group was 16 in total, about 8 of which were going the whole 42
days(and then some) to Kenya, so there wasn’t a lot of swapping around
of the group. The trip is split into 3 main sub-trips(but there’s
shorter trips within this also), so I was glad the group remained
consistent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually trip crew arrives, three guys from Zimbabwe. A chef, a driver
and the trip leader. It’s usually those three guys, but we had a trainee
driver with us on this trip(to get his head around the route to
Zimbabwe). They all seemed lovely. We made out local payments and a run through the next few days was done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Cash&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things I was sweating about was having access to local
money. How it was relayed to me was that I would need to have all of my spending money at the start of the trip. This seemed dubious as I really didn’t want to have a ton of cash with me while traveling. The trip
leader alleviated these fears by explaining that there was tons of ATMs
on the way and you can take out as much Rand as you wanted as South
Africa, Namibia, Zimbabwe and most campsites in Botswana would all
accept it. I’d recommend getting a ton of Rand and don’t bother with
Namibian dollars at all(it’s a straight one-to-one currency rate so
there’s no disadvantage and the Rand is more widely accepted). That
seems a lot less complicated. Make sure you have enough USD for Visa’s
and certain activities, most take USD but some(like the Serengeti)
require it, try get this USD in Cape Town as they’ll provide reliable
bills. You can get USD out in Zimbabwe but the quality of the bills can
be really poor and all countries(other than Zimbabwe), won’t accept
dirty bills. Most people on the trip seemed to struggle to get money
converted in Cape Town, that they were residents or that they were
leaving the country in less than 24 hours. It’s tough to find cash,
especially on a Sunday the day before we were leaving. However, I was
recommended a currency exchange place at the V &amp;amp; A Waterfront, that
would convert money. Make sure if you get Rand out of the bank to take a receipt to prove the cash you’re bringing is legit. I didn’t and had to
keep the Rand I’d just taken out and get more USD on my credit card.
Again, wasn’t an issue as everywhere takes Rand, but just to bear this
in mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other than that, the trip leader simply explained that the first few
day. A nervous feeling came over me when he mentioned ‘It’s okay, we
have a late wake-up. We just need to be gone by 7am’. I could see there
was going to be a lot of early starts in my future… So we were all up and out early for day one. We had a huge orange monster of a truck(not bus, truck) for transport. Bags, camping gear and tents go into the bottom, small bags up top where you sit/sleep/drink/live. Each seat had a personal locker where you can lock your stuff with, which was nice, but note that this is not available in all(or even most) of the trucks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were recommended to leave all valuables on the truck, money, passport etc. Our driver slept in the cab of the truck and the crew always kept it secure and I noticed they also keep their own valuables on there, so it certainly seemed a lot safer than on my person or in a tent. The truck itself was pretty chunky but comfortable, which is great considering how long you’ll be in it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without much ceremony we were off.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>Overlanding</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/overlanding-ac775c297d46.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-07-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2013-07-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2013-07-18:/overlanding-ac775c297d46.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, for the last 6 weeks I’ve been over-landing from Cape Town to
Nairobi. I decided to ditch almost all of my tech for the trip. My
Samsung Galaxy S3 and my Thinkpad were replaced with an old school phone
and a notepad. I also picked up a tiny …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, for the last 6 weeks I’ve been over-landing from Cape Town to
Nairobi. I decided to ditch almost all of my tech for the trip. My
Samsung Galaxy S3 and my Thinkpad were replaced with an old school phone
and a notepad. I also picked up a tiny little Sandisk Sansa Clip MP3
player for the trip. For reading I had my Kindle and a few USB keys for
storing files and for Portableapps(which was a disaster I’ll write about
another time). The decision for ditching was simply a need to be away
from the tech and connectedness. I’m in Africa for a reason, and I
simply didn’t want the constant distractions a phone brings me. I
couldn’t help but notice on the way others were clamouring for internet
when they thought it was an option. I appreciated having that option.
Anyway, as a result I have a lot of time to write with the long journeys
during the day and frankly I wish I had more information on the trip to
see where the land lies before starting, so I figured I write this blog
to give others a heads up and I’ve split things up into each
destination.
Here’s the skinny on countries I hit&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;South Africa&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Namibia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bostswana&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Zimbabwe&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Zambia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Malawi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tanzania(and Zanzibar)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kenya&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll fill these in as links when the posts are written.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>Why Study Philosophy</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/why-study-philosophy-1aba210c328b.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2012-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2012-06-26:/why-study-philosophy-1aba210c328b.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I finished my final exam in a course I was taking in
philosophy and I figured now was a good time to explain the question
everyone asks when I tell him what I’m studying. Why study philosophy?
To be honest, my answers were always pretty poor, mostly I …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I finished my final exam in a course I was taking in
philosophy and I figured now was a good time to explain the question
everyone asks when I tell him what I’m studying. Why study philosophy?
To be honest, my answers were always pretty poor, mostly I’d say it was
just an interest, but that never really explained the value I got from
it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I started studying it began as a need to understand the structures
of our society, what drove capitalism or democracy, are there even valid
alternatives to them? Were they actually implemented and if so did they
last long? &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paris_Commune"&gt;The Paris Commune&lt;/a&gt;, a period in 1871 when Paris was run entirely by anarchists, stuck in my mind. How did anarchists run anything? Clearly whatever I thought an anarchist was, was incorrect. On top of that I also wanted to challenge the religious dogmatism around me and needed rational arguments to give a sort of structure to what was angering me in society, this was the basic initial drive towards philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Philosophy is simply a formal combination of challenging what’s around
you within a historical context. A lot of philosophy books read like
history books, you have a huge list of eras, within which is a huge list
of thinkers and you follow and progress through the theories supplied
through the ages. You pick up the terminology, the great thinkers and
most importantly the evolving theories, you begin to see how human
thought evolved through the ages. It’s incredibly interesting, but
what’s most important is how it shapes your view of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m going to try show this using the abstract topic of the self. Bear
with me here. What interested philosophers around the 16th Century was
the dilemmas of morality, and one issue with that was the notion of the
self, which was something tackled by &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Locke"&gt;John Locke&lt;/a&gt;. If you did something
bad many years ago, should you be punished now for it? The problem was
to do with the self over time, did it exist, how so, how do we handle it
in our day-to-day thought? I thought it sounded meaningless and crazy
too. But upon reading into this, great thinkers have actually altered
how I view the world, in surprising ways. For me, it was a philosopher
named &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Derek_Parfit"&gt;Derek Parfit&lt;/a&gt;, who showed using a few thought experiments, that the idea of you being the same self over time is crazy. He argued that even if you met yourself twenty years from now, other than this preconceived notion of the self you wouldn’t be much like this person and in reality you wouldn’t really care about them. Frankly, I’m explaining it badly(I highly recommend
reading Parfit if you can), but once I read through most of Parfit’s work, some set of internal views I had on the world shifted. It’s hard to describe the sensation of having a fundamental view change within, but I can describe the effect. Things like worrying about the future or acquiring things “in case I need it”, become completely irrelevant. I cared less and less about making long term investments that only pay off years later, don’t get me wrong I plan for the future, but I don’t lock myself down into anything I might regret later on. Everything had a more temporary feel about it. More extremely, it actually provided a more comforting view of death in general. Why worry, whoever that person is on his death bed, won’t be much like me, so why care? I’ve heard the Buddist mindset of “now-ness”, being mindful and in the moment, but hearing these empty phrases from these supposed Zen-masters without any rationality just washed over me. The rational argument supplied a belief and it took root, I can’t shake it, maybe I’ll discover someone who trounces Parfit, I’ll look forward to reading it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was just one of those epiphanies I’ve had while studying philosophy. I wanted to keep this fairly short, but there have been several. For morality, I moved from being a libertarian, to Mill’s rule utilitarian, to Kant’s universalizability, to Rawl’s Egalitarianism and finally to Luck Egalitarianism. You don’t need to know any of these terms but this is just to highlight how much a single view of the world can evolve. This effects how I vote, what causes I support, the charities I give to and countless other important choices I make in my life. I’ve had similar changes across other branches of philosophy too. The notion of philosophy may appear dry, dull and pointless but it’s effects aren’t. It’s hard to explain without simply trying it out for a while. If you can, take a course or pick up a book and see if it takes root. If it doesn’t, what have you lost?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, philosophy is a way to challenge the beliefs you’re culturally imbued with. Admittedly, it may not make radical changes in your life but the next decision you make may be done with a little bit more reflection, and as Plato says(and what is probably at the start/end of every article supporting study of philosophy), “the unexamined life is not worth living”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some books I’d recommend are Bertrand Russell’s History of Western
Philosophy or if you can manage it, John Cottingham’s Western
Sophie’s World by Jostein Gaarder or the excellent Zen and the Art of
Motorcycle Maintenance by Pirsig.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>Vegetarian</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/vegetarian-9bb1abb30879.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2011-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2011-05-07:/vegetarian-9bb1abb30879.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Deciding to become vegetarian is not an easy step. I decided to dip my
toe in the water at the start of the year by trying a month of not
eating meat, I would highly recommend everyone try this at least once
just to see what it might be like …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Deciding to become vegetarian is not an easy step. I decided to dip my
toe in the water at the start of the year by trying a month of not
eating meat, I would highly recommend everyone try this at least once
just to see what it might be like. I enjoyed the food I ate that month
so much I’ve decided to keep it up indefinitely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why?&lt;/strong&gt; Personally, I chose vegetarianism after reading Peter Singer’s
“Animal Liberation”, but you may have your own sources of inspiration.
It’s a great book and I would highly recommend it to veggie/non-veggies
alike. It persuaded me to consider the idea of giving up meat and if I’m
ever drawn into an ethical argument about meat-eating I have some decent
arguments to fall back on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to be able to say that I’m a vegetarian purely out of
ethics but that’s simply not the case. In fact being honest I was being
entirely ethically consistent with regard to meat-eating, I would have
to go vegan and right now I find that a step too far. I’m almost certain
that dairy cows and egg producing chickens suffer far more than their
meat-producing equivalents purely due to their lifespan(the average meat
producing chicken lives around 8 weeks).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My real reason for giving up meat was simply boredom. I was bored of
eating the same things at restaurants using the same ingredients for the
same dinners. My relationship with food was a sort of thoughtless and
comfortable, but not interesting. Like I suspect it is for many. I’m
certain we could all make our dishes more interesting but I figured a
grand act would push me to try new things and it certainly has. I now
cook with ingredients I’d never even heard of. In fact before the switch
I would argue I could barely cook at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vegetarianism is simply an inspiring limitation. Oh and also
&lt;a href="http://zenhabits.net/how-to-become-a-vegetarian-the-easy-way/"&gt;zenhabits&lt;/a&gt; has a really sweet list on why you should consider vegetarianism too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How?&lt;/strong&gt; The question is, how do you keep yourself motivated in a world
of meat-eaters. One fun thing I do, is cook a new dish every week until
I have enough dishes that I like that I can keep cooking everyday and
not get bored. Each week just find a new dish that you feel like
making(curry, pasta-based etc), pick up ingredients from the nicest
vegetable shop(having nice vegetables can be key to keeping you
motivated) around you and cook. Some things will be great and some will
be disasters, but it’s all fun. Four months in and I’m already building
a great collection of recipes I find tasty. I’ve even started
my partner will eat, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Effects&lt;/strong&gt; I’m genuinely surprised how much vegetarianism has affected
me. For staters, when people hear about it they become incredibly
interested in it. Why do it? How difficult is it? Am I taking
supplements etc? It’s a great chance to try persuade people to do the
same, I usually try by explaining just how easy the whole thing is. Some
people have been persuaded to try a vegetarian meal once a week, I
figure after that they can make their own enquires into becoming
entirely vegetarian.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m a much healthier eater that I was before. Vegetarianism is a
limitation that increases reflection. As a result you find yourself
dwelling on everything you eat. For me, for the first time in my life I
have this mental checkbox that says, “Does this contain meat?” that I
had to ask every time I wanted to eat something. Very soon after another
question appeared, “Is this healthy?” and if it wasn’t “Do I really want
this?” and in most cases, I really didn’t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to the constant questioning of what I was eating and the fact that
I’ve been trying crazy new ingredients I found myself getting much more
interested in my snacking options. We all snack and it’s something I
can’t forgo at certain points in the day. As I tended to find myself in
alternative food stores perusing random ingredients I tended to pickup
weird nuts or some dried fruit I’d never tried. My snacking has gone
from chocolate, crisps and jellies(I’m a real sucker for those), to
nuts, fruit and cereals. This really was a surprising effect and as I
had originally said to calm myself “You may not be able to eat meat but
at least you can stick with sugary treats if gets you down!”. It’s not
gotten to the stage where when I eat, say a chocolate bar I find it
tastes stale, unpleasant, cheap and for the most part all the same. I
genuinely do not miss them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Difficulties&lt;/strong&gt; One difficult that will arise is social occasions.
Dealing with this is usually a matter of good preparations, but it
doesn’t hurt to have a few minimal ingredients dishes in case of a worst
case scenario. I’d flown home to see my family, who had forgotten I’d
told them I wasn’t eating meat and had thrown a BBQ as the weather was
nice. I went digging and found some potatoes, some vegetables, flour and
pitta bread in the back of a cupboard and threw together some awesome
veggie burgers(I’ll throw up a recipe later). While it didn’t stop
anyone from eating meat, most said they loved them and would have no
problem eating them as a substitute. I highly recommend them with sweet
chilli sauce!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is also the cases where you will just crave meat, that’s almost
unavoidable. It’s a rare occurrence for me, but hangovers are my
kryptonite. I crave a fry in the morning but thankfully I haven’t given
in. Despite the obvious tastiness factor of fried meat, I tried to
figure out why a fry in question was such a difficult one for me to cope
with forgoing. I thought about it and realised that whenever I was
having a fry it was usually with friends, the smell of frying sausages
and bacon coaxing us out of our slumber and around a table chatting
about the prior nights silliness and wolfing down food. I realised the
subtraction of meat from this picture really doesn’t change anything at
all that matters. The point being that, if you stop to think about what
you’re craving you may realise that taste isn’t everything. Though it
also helps that vegetarian fries are awesome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tips&lt;/strong&gt; I found when I first started looking for recipes I was
overwhelmed by choice. Eventually I came across &lt;a href="http://www.bbcgoodfood.com/content/recipes/vegetarian/"&gt;BBC’s good food site&lt;/a&gt;, which
is just decided to awesome food, that’s rated by users. It has a really
good vegetarian sections with some awesome recipes, I’ll share the ones
that have worked for me at a later stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I often find myself with a ton of spare vegetables where recipes have
annoyingly required two onions and I can only find a pack of three. If
you find yourself with the same problem try a recipe that’s very loose
with the ingredients. It might be a soup or a pasta dish with a nice
sauce, for me because I like to use quinoa and lentils in a lot of my
dishes I tried to find something that used both, with a lot of random
vegetables. Eventually I came across this &lt;a href="http://vegweb.com/index.php?topic=39142.0"&gt;recipe&lt;/a&gt;, its super
healthy and really filling. I’d highly recommend a spicy pasta sauce
with it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>The Power of Nightmares</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/the-power-of-nightmares-5717f5a92295.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-12-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2010-12-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2010-12-28:/the-power-of-nightmares-5717f5a92295.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I always wondered why, if the UK/US were at war with terrorism, why they
always made such fantastic declarations about how powerful terrorists
were and that they had infiltrated all elements of society? Surely this
would simply add more gas to the fire and prolong the effect of the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I always wondered why, if the UK/US were at war with terrorism, why they
always made such fantastic declarations about how powerful terrorists
were and that they had infiltrated all elements of society? Surely this
would simply add more gas to the fire and prolong the effect of the
initial attack in question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyhoo I guess my question has been answered, just watched &lt;a href="http://www.archive.org/details/ThePowerOfNightmares"&gt;The Power of
Nightmares&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adam Curtis you rock.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>The problem with God arguments</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/the-problem-with-god-arguments-c9543d98f6c8.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2010-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2010-11-05:/the-problem-with-god-arguments-c9543d98f6c8.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Atheists and theists alike have for centuries attempted to
debate the existence of God, desperately trying to reason out a
conclusive answer. The reality of this struck me while I was reading a
series of MIT lectures notes on arguments for and against the existence
of God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lecture notes …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Atheists and theists alike have for centuries attempted to
debate the existence of God, desperately trying to reason out a
conclusive answer. The reality of this struck me while I was reading a
series of MIT lectures notes on arguments for and against the existence
of God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lecture notes are very well written(so well written in fact the lazy
student in me probably wouldn’t have bothered going to the lectures, if
I had the pleasure of taking the course in question). The course does a
decent job of explaining concepts such as deductive and inductive
reasons and a few other philosophical instruments, but this isn’t the
source of my concern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;question grates on whenever I hear it. Lets take a small village in
England, a shopkeeper has just been murdered and a crowd has formed
around the scene of the crime. The police chief arrives sirens blaring,
barges through the crowd, quickly scans the situation and declares “Did
Mayor Dave do it!?”. Everyone sighs, the Mayor is always blamed in such
cases. No-one remembers why the Mayor is blamed, it’s just what’s done.
The police chief along with his detectives then spend night and day
logically deducing if Mayor Dave is in fact the culprit. They always
come up short.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The obvious problem here is the police chief has taken the entirely
wrong approach, simply by asking the wrong question. I hope you know
where I’m going here, but the obvious alternative is instead to declare
“Lets look at the evidence and follow where it takes us”. Why is this
approach not the same for the creation of existence? Why have we taken
only one, just one of the infinite amount of concepts, entities,
processes, whatever and decided to blow all our time reasoning about
this perfect being? A giant dragon by the name of Bill created the
universe, discuss. Why is this not getting the equilavent levels of
academic debate as Did God do it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pointlessness of these discussions hit me when the MIT lecture
notes went into detail on the specifics of what theists and atheists are
reasoning about. Theists say God is Omnipotent, Omniscient and
Good(OOG), then the atheists spend time arguing that if this is the case
you can infer(eventually) that because there is evil God must not exist.
The theists respond with, ah but if the evils that occur were always
outweighed by the future good generated by the original evil act(and
this is guaranteed by God), then in essence the overall good is
maintained. My counter point here would be, if God guarantees all evils
are outdone by future good, isn’t it our moral obligation to always be
evil? But, I’m not going to be sucked into this rubbish debate. The
atheists have lost even by stepping into the playing field. I think
we’ve all forgotten that invention of God(I’m going back as far as
Dionysus here), was infact to counter a sensible lifestyle, to say screw
you to logic and reason and let emotions run wild. Two thousand years
later and we’ve forgotten this, blowing valid time reasoning about
effectively an emotional revolt against reason. Let the theists produce
all the reasoned arguments they can think of for God and when the exact
same argument doesn’t just as validly apply to Bill the giant Dragon or
the Flying Spaghetti Monster I’ll step up and listen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until then I applaud science and philosophers for at least attempting
to produce valid reasons for the existence of the world around us. It’s
an incredibly slow process, but at least it’s in the right direction.
One that’s lately caught my attention is the `Anthropic
principle.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>Descartes, Second Meditation</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/descartes-second-meditation-f5d3426ef9ee.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-09-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2010-09-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2010-09-20:/descartes-second-meditation-f5d3426ef9ee.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In Descarte’s second meditation, he moves onto classification of the
mind and body. The initial argument is that he must exist, even if there
is absolutely nothing in the world he must exist, even if all existence
is presented by a deceiver, he still must exist to be deceived …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In Descarte’s second meditation, he moves onto classification of the
mind and body. The initial argument is that he must exist, even if there
is absolutely nothing in the world he must exist, even if all existence
is presented by a deceiver, he still must exist to be deceived. He runs
into an interesting question of what defines existence and he
me. This is a good starting point, but doesn’t entirely answer the
question of self. For example, Determinism may entirely circumvent the
essence of self. He also seems to belittle the affects of sensory
perception. If everything I perceive through the senses is a deception,
are my thoughts truly my own or am I being led by a deceiver? Is my
definition of self as a thinking thing even valid? For example, Descarte
effectively defines imagination as “simply contemplating the shape or
image of a corporeal thing”. In essence stating that even imagination
can be corrupted by the deceiver. He closes off the imagination as
superfluous to perception of your own nature. Essentially Descarte is
cutting off any contact to the physical world, even imagination that
begins with a perceived event or corporeal object. However, the mental
acts involved in say sensory perception or imagination, these can be
considered real.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually after repeated questioning he boils down to the reasonable to
“I am a thinking thing”. He separates the corporeal with the mental by
de-construction a piece of wax and stating, surely we cannot be
naturally aware of all states of wax, we use perception through the mind
alone. It is a mental cognitive judgement on the nature of wax, which of
course is prone to error. Descarte has built up the importance of
‘mind’, and more specifically judgements and understanding over say
imagination. He cuts us off with reality and predicates all
understanding of anything(real or not) with the self. So, in every act
of understanding we establish the nature of our own minds a little
further, where his reasoning for this is, I don’t know. Descarte draws
the line at comprehension so overcomes the deceiver argument. If a
deceiver gave me a sample of wax to play with, my comprehension of the
ultimate nature of this wax would be proof of self, not the imagining of
wax and not the physical contact with the wax. Essentially, the
foundation of all comprehension is ‘self’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though I find myself agreeing with many sections of this chapter, it’s
never through Descarte’s reasoning, but purely I agree that they are
acceptable starting points. The question remains, I do not understand
the nature of existence, nor do I understand the true nature of
thoughts, yet we’ve made an inference anyway. Maybe the appearance of
thought is simply the motion of the deceiver, or a computing simulation
in action.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>Reflections on Descartes Meditations</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/reflections-on-descartes-meditations-a03fd614a3f0.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-09-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2010-09-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2010-09-11:/reflections-on-descartes-meditations-a03fd614a3f0.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So I’ve just finished Descarte’s Meditations on First Philosophy and I’m
going to try put up a response to each Meditation in the next few days,
as well as the objections and responses Descarte added after the initial
six meditations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I whole-heartedly accept the I have the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So I’ve just finished Descarte’s Meditations on First Philosophy and I’m
going to try put up a response to each Meditation in the next few days,
as well as the objections and responses Descarte added after the initial
six meditations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I whole-heartedly accept the I have the unfair advantage of about four
centuries of human advancement over Descarte, but I will try my best to
level the playing field. I’ll take each meditation as a separate
argument and accept(to some extent) all initial assertions Descarte
makes in each meditation. So for example in the second meditation
Descarte attempts to reason the existence of God and I’ll dispute any
flawed reasoning he uses, within this meditation. However, he uses this
existence of God to infer further claims in other meditations. For this,
I’ll accept(purely for arguments sake) the existence of God as a valid
assumption and attempt to dismiss again, any flawed reasoning he uses
based on this assumption. To be honest, it’s a testament to the extent
of Descarte’s doubt and refusal to accept but a few initial assumptions
that I can do this effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This for me is mostly an exercise in discovering if I can effectively
detect flawed reasoning and I’d consider Descarte’s book quite a
difficult one purely due to the abstract nature of the arguments(but
this may be purely due to my naivety).&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>The Museum-going Cannibal</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/the-museum-going-cannibal-5d5bb1a3fbd.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-09-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2010-09-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2010-09-11:/the-museum-going-cannibal-5d5bb1a3fbd.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;From the lastest issue of philosophy now. I find it’s on the right side of
harsh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Museum-going Cannibal&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;by Yahia Lababidi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upright specimen, looking to be fine-tuned on weekends by the civilizing
influence of beauty, standing still and reflecting in the refracted
light of another’s encounter with …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;From the lastest issue of philosophy now. I find it’s on the right side of
harsh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Museum-going Cannibal&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;by Yahia Lababidi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upright specimen, looking to be fine-tuned on weekends by the civilizing
influence of beauty, standing still and reflecting in the refracted
light of another’s encounter with the sublime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All polite smiles and hushed appreciation, sliding up to some mounted
painting and tilting its head to sip and drink in the brushstrokes, yet
downright vicious throughout the week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hankering after a bit of meat and blood in the shape of a live woman or
a dead man. Never mind that they know them or not, at times, any old
body warm or cold will do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;as charitable and vulnerable as a winged thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;© Yahia Lababidi 2010&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry></feed>