<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Shane Dowling - Random</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://shanedowling.com/feeds/random.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://shanedowling.com/</id><updated>2020-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><subtitle>Shane Dowling</subtitle><entry><title>Quick Review - Long Gone Days</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/quick-review-long-gone-days.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2020-09-28:/quick-review-long-gone-days.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Coming from the AMAZING Bundle for Racial Justice and Equality, Long
Gone Days is a &amp;quot;2D modern-day military RPG set in our current times,
with a focus on language and cultural barriers&amp;quot;'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="looks"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Looks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Love the art-style of the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="music"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Music&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The score is solid and the in-game sounds are fine …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Coming from the AMAZING Bundle for Racial Justice and Equality, Long
Gone Days is a &amp;quot;2D modern-day military RPG set in our current times,
with a focus on language and cultural barriers&amp;quot;'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="looks"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Looks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Love the art-style of the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="music"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Music&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The score is solid and the in-game sounds are fine but unspectacular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="story"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Story&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No spoilers here. The story isn't bad, but it definitely has higher
ideas than it's able to pull off. It also doesn't really capture the
language and cultural barriers effectively in it's dialogue or plot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="gameplay"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Gameplay&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Walking around the pretty world is nice enough, but the motion feels a
bit clunky. The RPG elements are extremely shallow, and the battle
screen is unimpressive. There are sniper sections also which are also
fairly weak. All in all, it's not strong gameplay wise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of language and cultural barriers ties into the gameplay too.
You enter new areas without the ability to communicate with NPCs, that
could really have driven home the message about language barriers but in
reality you pretty quickly find a translator and that's that. It could
have been interwoven into the gameplay further, for example
mis-understanding language could lead to some character mistakes
plot-wise, or it could have been woven more effectively in the gameplay.
Again, it's just a bit shallow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="did-i-finish-it"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Did I finish it?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The true estimation of if a game is decent in this bundle. So for me,
no, after playing for a few hours, upon returning it felt too slow paced
and clunky to want to continue. Perhaps the shallowness gameplay wise is
forgivable, I'd say give it 30 minutes, if you're not sold on wanting to
progress the story the gameplay may not keep you around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="Random"></category></entry></feed>