<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Shane Dowling - Random</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://shanedowling.com/feeds/random.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://shanedowling.com/</id><updated>2011-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><subtitle>Shane Dowling</subtitle><entry><title>Vegetarian</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/vegetarian-9bb1abb30879.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2011-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2011-05-07:/vegetarian-9bb1abb30879.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Deciding to become vegetarian is not an easy step. I decided to dip my
toe in the water at the start of the year by trying a month of not
eating meat, I would highly recommend everyone try this at least once
just to see what it might be like …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Deciding to become vegetarian is not an easy step. I decided to dip my
toe in the water at the start of the year by trying a month of not
eating meat, I would highly recommend everyone try this at least once
just to see what it might be like. I enjoyed the food I ate that month
so much I’ve decided to keep it up indefinitely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why?&lt;/strong&gt; Personally, I chose vegetarianism after reading Peter Singer’s
“Animal Liberation”, but you may have your own sources of inspiration.
It’s a great book and I would highly recommend it to veggie/non-veggies
alike. It persuaded me to consider the idea of giving up meat and if I’m
ever drawn into an ethical argument about meat-eating I have some decent
arguments to fall back on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to be able to say that I’m a vegetarian purely out of
ethics but that’s simply not the case. In fact being honest I was being
entirely ethically consistent with regard to meat-eating, I would have
to go vegan and right now I find that a step too far. I’m almost certain
that dairy cows and egg producing chickens suffer far more than their
meat-producing equivalents purely due to their lifespan(the average meat
producing chicken lives around 8 weeks).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My real reason for giving up meat was simply boredom. I was bored of
eating the same things at restaurants using the same ingredients for the
same dinners. My relationship with food was a sort of thoughtless and
comfortable, but not interesting. Like I suspect it is for many. I’m
certain we could all make our dishes more interesting but I figured a
grand act would push me to try new things and it certainly has. I now
cook with ingredients I’d never even heard of. In fact before the switch
I would argue I could barely cook at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vegetarianism is simply an inspiring limitation. Oh and also
&lt;a href="http://zenhabits.net/how-to-become-a-vegetarian-the-easy-way/"&gt;zenhabits&lt;/a&gt; has a really sweet list on why you should consider vegetarianism too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How?&lt;/strong&gt; The question is, how do you keep yourself motivated in a world
of meat-eaters. One fun thing I do, is cook a new dish every week until
I have enough dishes that I like that I can keep cooking everyday and
not get bored. Each week just find a new dish that you feel like
making(curry, pasta-based etc), pick up ingredients from the nicest
vegetable shop(having nice vegetables can be key to keeping you
motivated) around you and cook. Some things will be great and some will
be disasters, but it’s all fun. Four months in and I’m already building
a great collection of recipes I find tasty. I’ve even started
my partner will eat, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Effects&lt;/strong&gt; I’m genuinely surprised how much vegetarianism has affected
me. For staters, when people hear about it they become incredibly
interested in it. Why do it? How difficult is it? Am I taking
supplements etc? It’s a great chance to try persuade people to do the
same, I usually try by explaining just how easy the whole thing is. Some
people have been persuaded to try a vegetarian meal once a week, I
figure after that they can make their own enquires into becoming
entirely vegetarian.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m a much healthier eater that I was before. Vegetarianism is a
limitation that increases reflection. As a result you find yourself
dwelling on everything you eat. For me, for the first time in my life I
have this mental checkbox that says, “Does this contain meat?” that I
had to ask every time I wanted to eat something. Very soon after another
question appeared, “Is this healthy?” and if it wasn’t “Do I really want
this?” and in most cases, I really didn’t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to the constant questioning of what I was eating and the fact that
I’ve been trying crazy new ingredients I found myself getting much more
interested in my snacking options. We all snack and it’s something I
can’t forgo at certain points in the day. As I tended to find myself in
alternative food stores perusing random ingredients I tended to pickup
weird nuts or some dried fruit I’d never tried. My snacking has gone
from chocolate, crisps and jellies(I’m a real sucker for those), to
nuts, fruit and cereals. This really was a surprising effect and as I
had originally said to calm myself “You may not be able to eat meat but
at least you can stick with sugary treats if gets you down!”. It’s not
gotten to the stage where when I eat, say a chocolate bar I find it
tastes stale, unpleasant, cheap and for the most part all the same. I
genuinely do not miss them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Difficulties&lt;/strong&gt; One difficult that will arise is social occasions.
Dealing with this is usually a matter of good preparations, but it
doesn’t hurt to have a few minimal ingredients dishes in case of a worst
case scenario. I’d flown home to see my family, who had forgotten I’d
told them I wasn’t eating meat and had thrown a BBQ as the weather was
nice. I went digging and found some potatoes, some vegetables, flour and
pitta bread in the back of a cupboard and threw together some awesome
veggie burgers(I’ll throw up a recipe later). While it didn’t stop
anyone from eating meat, most said they loved them and would have no
problem eating them as a substitute. I highly recommend them with sweet
chilli sauce!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is also the cases where you will just crave meat, that’s almost
unavoidable. It’s a rare occurrence for me, but hangovers are my
kryptonite. I crave a fry in the morning but thankfully I haven’t given
in. Despite the obvious tastiness factor of fried meat, I tried to
figure out why a fry in question was such a difficult one for me to cope
with forgoing. I thought about it and realised that whenever I was
having a fry it was usually with friends, the smell of frying sausages
and bacon coaxing us out of our slumber and around a table chatting
about the prior nights silliness and wolfing down food. I realised the
subtraction of meat from this picture really doesn’t change anything at
all that matters. The point being that, if you stop to think about what
you’re craving you may realise that taste isn’t everything. Though it
also helps that vegetarian fries are awesome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tips&lt;/strong&gt; I found when I first started looking for recipes I was
overwhelmed by choice. Eventually I came across &lt;a href="http://www.bbcgoodfood.com/content/recipes/vegetarian/"&gt;BBC’s good food site&lt;/a&gt;, which
is just decided to awesome food, that’s rated by users. It has a really
good vegetarian sections with some awesome recipes, I’ll share the ones
that have worked for me at a later stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I often find myself with a ton of spare vegetables where recipes have
annoyingly required two onions and I can only find a pack of three. If
you find yourself with the same problem try a recipe that’s very loose
with the ingredients. It might be a soup or a pasta dish with a nice
sauce, for me because I like to use quinoa and lentils in a lot of my
dishes I tried to find something that used both, with a lot of random
vegetables. Eventually I came across this &lt;a href="http://vegweb.com/index.php?topic=39142.0"&gt;recipe&lt;/a&gt;, its super
healthy and really filling. I’d highly recommend a spicy pasta sauce
with it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>The Power of Nightmares</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/the-power-of-nightmares-5717f5a92295.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-12-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2010-12-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2010-12-28:/the-power-of-nightmares-5717f5a92295.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I always wondered why, if the UK/US were at war with terrorism, why they
always made such fantastic declarations about how powerful terrorists
were and that they had infiltrated all elements of society? Surely this
would simply add more gas to the fire and prolong the effect of the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I always wondered why, if the UK/US were at war with terrorism, why they
always made such fantastic declarations about how powerful terrorists
were and that they had infiltrated all elements of society? Surely this
would simply add more gas to the fire and prolong the effect of the
initial attack in question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyhoo I guess my question has been answered, just watched &lt;a href="http://www.archive.org/details/ThePowerOfNightmares"&gt;The Power of
Nightmares&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adam Curtis you rock.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>The problem with God arguments</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/the-problem-with-god-arguments-c9543d98f6c8.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2010-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2010-11-05:/the-problem-with-god-arguments-c9543d98f6c8.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Atheists and theists alike have for centuries attempted to
debate the existence of God, desperately trying to reason out a
conclusive answer. The reality of this struck me while I was reading a
series of MIT lectures notes on arguments for and against the existence
of God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lecture notes …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Atheists and theists alike have for centuries attempted to
debate the existence of God, desperately trying to reason out a
conclusive answer. The reality of this struck me while I was reading a
series of MIT lectures notes on arguments for and against the existence
of God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lecture notes are very well written(so well written in fact the lazy
student in me probably wouldn’t have bothered going to the lectures, if
I had the pleasure of taking the course in question). The course does a
decent job of explaining concepts such as deductive and inductive
reasons and a few other philosophical instruments, but this isn’t the
source of my concern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;question grates on whenever I hear it. Lets take a small village in
England, a shopkeeper has just been murdered and a crowd has formed
around the scene of the crime. The police chief arrives sirens blaring,
barges through the crowd, quickly scans the situation and declares “Did
Mayor Dave do it!?”. Everyone sighs, the Mayor is always blamed in such
cases. No-one remembers why the Mayor is blamed, it’s just what’s done.
The police chief along with his detectives then spend night and day
logically deducing if Mayor Dave is in fact the culprit. They always
come up short.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The obvious problem here is the police chief has taken the entirely
wrong approach, simply by asking the wrong question. I hope you know
where I’m going here, but the obvious alternative is instead to declare
“Lets look at the evidence and follow where it takes us”. Why is this
approach not the same for the creation of existence? Why have we taken
only one, just one of the infinite amount of concepts, entities,
processes, whatever and decided to blow all our time reasoning about
this perfect being? A giant dragon by the name of Bill created the
universe, discuss. Why is this not getting the equilavent levels of
academic debate as Did God do it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pointlessness of these discussions hit me when the MIT lecture
notes went into detail on the specifics of what theists and atheists are
reasoning about. Theists say God is Omnipotent, Omniscient and
Good(OOG), then the atheists spend time arguing that if this is the case
you can infer(eventually) that because there is evil God must not exist.
The theists respond with, ah but if the evils that occur were always
outweighed by the future good generated by the original evil act(and
this is guaranteed by God), then in essence the overall good is
maintained. My counter point here would be, if God guarantees all evils
are outdone by future good, isn’t it our moral obligation to always be
evil? But, I’m not going to be sucked into this rubbish debate. The
atheists have lost even by stepping into the playing field. I think
we’ve all forgotten that invention of God(I’m going back as far as
Dionysus here), was infact to counter a sensible lifestyle, to say screw
you to logic and reason and let emotions run wild. Two thousand years
later and we’ve forgotten this, blowing valid time reasoning about
effectively an emotional revolt against reason. Let the theists produce
all the reasoned arguments they can think of for God and when the exact
same argument doesn’t just as validly apply to Bill the giant Dragon or
the Flying Spaghetti Monster I’ll step up and listen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until then I applaud science and philosophers for at least attempting
to produce valid reasons for the existence of the world around us. It’s
an incredibly slow process, but at least it’s in the right direction.
One that’s lately caught my attention is the `Anthropic
principle.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>Descartes, Second Meditation</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/descartes-second-meditation-f5d3426ef9ee.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-09-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2010-09-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2010-09-20:/descartes-second-meditation-f5d3426ef9ee.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In Descarte’s second meditation, he moves onto classification of the
mind and body. The initial argument is that he must exist, even if there
is absolutely nothing in the world he must exist, even if all existence
is presented by a deceiver, he still must exist to be deceived …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In Descarte’s second meditation, he moves onto classification of the
mind and body. The initial argument is that he must exist, even if there
is absolutely nothing in the world he must exist, even if all existence
is presented by a deceiver, he still must exist to be deceived. He runs
into an interesting question of what defines existence and he
me. This is a good starting point, but doesn’t entirely answer the
question of self. For example, Determinism may entirely circumvent the
essence of self. He also seems to belittle the affects of sensory
perception. If everything I perceive through the senses is a deception,
are my thoughts truly my own or am I being led by a deceiver? Is my
definition of self as a thinking thing even valid? For example, Descarte
effectively defines imagination as “simply contemplating the shape or
image of a corporeal thing”. In essence stating that even imagination
can be corrupted by the deceiver. He closes off the imagination as
superfluous to perception of your own nature. Essentially Descarte is
cutting off any contact to the physical world, even imagination that
begins with a perceived event or corporeal object. However, the mental
acts involved in say sensory perception or imagination, these can be
considered real.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually after repeated questioning he boils down to the reasonable to
“I am a thinking thing”. He separates the corporeal with the mental by
de-construction a piece of wax and stating, surely we cannot be
naturally aware of all states of wax, we use perception through the mind
alone. It is a mental cognitive judgement on the nature of wax, which of
course is prone to error. Descarte has built up the importance of
‘mind’, and more specifically judgements and understanding over say
imagination. He cuts us off with reality and predicates all
understanding of anything(real or not) with the self. So, in every act
of understanding we establish the nature of our own minds a little
further, where his reasoning for this is, I don’t know. Descarte draws
the line at comprehension so overcomes the deceiver argument. If a
deceiver gave me a sample of wax to play with, my comprehension of the
ultimate nature of this wax would be proof of self, not the imagining of
wax and not the physical contact with the wax. Essentially, the
foundation of all comprehension is ‘self’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though I find myself agreeing with many sections of this chapter, it’s
never through Descarte’s reasoning, but purely I agree that they are
acceptable starting points. The question remains, I do not understand
the nature of existence, nor do I understand the true nature of
thoughts, yet we’ve made an inference anyway. Maybe the appearance of
thought is simply the motion of the deceiver, or a computing simulation
in action.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>Reflections on Descartes Meditations</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/reflections-on-descartes-meditations-a03fd614a3f0.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-09-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2010-09-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2010-09-11:/reflections-on-descartes-meditations-a03fd614a3f0.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So I’ve just finished Descarte’s Meditations on First Philosophy and I’m
going to try put up a response to each Meditation in the next few days,
as well as the objections and responses Descarte added after the initial
six meditations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I whole-heartedly accept the I have the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So I’ve just finished Descarte’s Meditations on First Philosophy and I’m
going to try put up a response to each Meditation in the next few days,
as well as the objections and responses Descarte added after the initial
six meditations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I whole-heartedly accept the I have the unfair advantage of about four
centuries of human advancement over Descarte, but I will try my best to
level the playing field. I’ll take each meditation as a separate
argument and accept(to some extent) all initial assertions Descarte
makes in each meditation. So for example in the second meditation
Descarte attempts to reason the existence of God and I’ll dispute any
flawed reasoning he uses, within this meditation. However, he uses this
existence of God to infer further claims in other meditations. For this,
I’ll accept(purely for arguments sake) the existence of God as a valid
assumption and attempt to dismiss again, any flawed reasoning he uses
based on this assumption. To be honest, it’s a testament to the extent
of Descarte’s doubt and refusal to accept but a few initial assumptions
that I can do this effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This for me is mostly an exercise in discovering if I can effectively
detect flawed reasoning and I’d consider Descarte’s book quite a
difficult one purely due to the abstract nature of the arguments(but
this may be purely due to my naivety).&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>The Museum-going Cannibal</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/the-museum-going-cannibal-5d5bb1a3fbd.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-09-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2010-09-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2010-09-11:/the-museum-going-cannibal-5d5bb1a3fbd.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;From the lastest issue of philosophy now. I find it’s on the right side of
harsh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Museum-going Cannibal&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;by Yahia Lababidi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upright specimen, looking to be fine-tuned on weekends by the civilizing
influence of beauty, standing still and reflecting in the refracted
light of another’s encounter with …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;From the lastest issue of philosophy now. I find it’s on the right side of
harsh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Museum-going Cannibal&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;by Yahia Lababidi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upright specimen, looking to be fine-tuned on weekends by the civilizing
influence of beauty, standing still and reflecting in the refracted
light of another’s encounter with the sublime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All polite smiles and hushed appreciation, sliding up to some mounted
painting and tilting its head to sip and drink in the brushstrokes, yet
downright vicious throughout the week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hankering after a bit of meat and blood in the shape of a live woman or
a dead man. Never mind that they know them or not, at times, any old
body warm or cold will do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;as charitable and vulnerable as a winged thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;© Yahia Lababidi 2010&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry></feed>