<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Shane Dowling - Random</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://shanedowling.com/feeds/random.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://shanedowling.com/</id><updated>2018-06-02T16:39:57+00:00</updated><subtitle>Shane Dowling</subtitle><entry><title>Please don't do it Github</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/please-dont-do-it-github-5890eb72d12c.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-06-02T16:39:57+00:00</published><updated>2018-06-02T16:39:57+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2018-06-02:/please-dont-do-it-github-5890eb72d12c.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__cKz__YzMFvM1HgqvzbIBvzw__2x.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So &lt;a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/2-billion-startup-github-could-be-for-sale-microsoft-2018-5"&gt;Microsoft has been in talks with Github&lt;/a&gt; about a potential acquisition. There are several reasons why this is a terrible idea. Github is a pretty solid git repo hosting company, but it has a few core values that are in jeopardy here and I'm not sure Microsoft(or anyone …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__cKz__YzMFvM1HgqvzbIBvzw__2x.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So &lt;a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/2-billion-startup-github-could-be-for-sale-microsoft-2018-5"&gt;Microsoft has been in talks with Github&lt;/a&gt; about a potential acquisition. There are several reasons why this is a terrible idea. Github is a pretty solid git repo hosting company, but it has a few core values that are in jeopardy here and I'm not sure Microsoft(or anyone) can acquire an entity like Github without severe repercussions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Platform agnostic integrations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Github has a ton of super useful integrations that help make the life for developers a lot easier. Tools like appveyor, travis-ci, coverall, readthedocs, codacy are really useful and what's so great is you free to run them wherever you like. How can Microsoft make the business case to keep platform agnostic integrations that are aiding competitors? Maybe they won't ban them, but they may become very much second class citizens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't believe me? Some examples of Microsoft not giving a single crap about anyone outside Microsoft products..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Having to use &lt;a href="https://tel.red/linux.php"&gt;Sky&lt;/a&gt; as there's no Skype for Business on Linux&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://blog.sunrise.am/"&gt;Sunrise to Outlook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theverge.com/2015/1/29/7936081/microsoft-outlook-app-ios-android-features"&gt;Accompli to Outlook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are certainly more examples, but the day I need to sign into a Microsoft account to use Github or can only deploy to Azure platforms for build tools, will be the day I stop bothering to use it and this is a real concern I have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The connection to open source&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Github repos are by default open and if you wish to pay a monthly fee they can be made private, this alone has simply been amazing for open source and why Github has been the platform of choice for most open source projects. There's also a great issue tracker, wikis, support for markdown readmes etc. We've all benefitted from such a great setup for open source projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microsoft has been doing good work in the open source space for the last few years, but anyone can see this is a recent development and purely for business reasons to regain much of the damage done in the 90s. When Microsoft attended Linux conferences they've &lt;a href="https://www.samba.org/samba/news/articles/low_point/column08.html"&gt;come dressed as Darth Vader&lt;/a&gt;, the dark corporate entity against the rebels of open source. Now they're planning to purchase the entity hosting the largest repository of open source code that has ever existed? If the strong connection to open source goes, the coolness factor takes a hit and so does Github's community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Coolness&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microsoft is not cool. God love them, they're trying their best, and I don't hate Microsoft at all. They've always given a shit about developers. I recently gave VSCode a whirl and was impressed. However, can you imagine Windows and Microsoft services getting hooked into Github all over the place? Collaborate with your open source developers over (ugh) Skype, auto-deploy your repo to Azure, or tie your Github account into your Linkedin one so recruiters can find more evidence you're perfect for that Java role because of some decade old Java repo from college. If anyone thinks this is insane I give you this monstrosity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__8tn6DDr1phm4CJnvPvr__0A__2x.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, migrating to another git host(cough &lt;a href="https://about.gitlab.com/"&gt;gitlab&lt;/a&gt;) might be a bit of a pain but it's really not that much work, mostly because git is so awesome. So Microsoft is really going to have to play this one carefully. I imagine a lot of Stallman's army will leave the moment Github agrees to such an acquisition, in fact Gnome has moved to Gitlab as they feel it matches them &lt;a href="https://about.gitlab.com/2018/05/31/welcome-gnome-to-gitlab/"&gt;more in spirit&lt;/a&gt;. Can you imagine many open source projects aligning with Microsoft 'in spirit'? Open source as a movement naturally rebels against centralised systems, how Microsoft can purchase its way into the hearts of developers is a hard thing to see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Edit: Update&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So there's been a &lt;a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2018-06-03/microsoft-is-said-to-have-agreed-to-acquire-coding-site-github"&gt;confirmation from Microsoft,&lt;/a&gt; color me skeptical. The best case scenario is Microsoft gives it the lightest possible touch. The question is if Microsoft's recent efforts with Github provide enough positive energy to maintain goodwill towards Github or if Gitlab becomes the de-facto FOSS git repo and let's be honest, the de-facto git repo hosting company of choice down the line.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>Wild Wild Country – The Soundtrack</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/wild-wild-country-the-soundtrack-bbe397fc1cf4.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-03-29T20:16:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-03-29T20:16:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2018-03-29:/wild-wild-country-the-soundtrack-bbe397fc1cf4.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Wild Wild Country – The Soundtrack&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1____IGWS6a7nQTfKgT6H5FQZw__2x.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For anyone who hasn't seen Netflix's &lt;a href="https://www.netflix.com/title/80145240?s=i&amp;amp;trkid=14170286"&gt;Wild Wild Country&lt;/a&gt;, I highly recommend you watch it. The story told, along with the wealth of footage they got their hands on makes it an incredible watch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The soundtrack is also excellent, I've put together the soundtrack as …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Wild Wild Country – The Soundtrack&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1____IGWS6a7nQTfKgT6H5FQZw__2x.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For anyone who hasn't seen Netflix's &lt;a href="https://www.netflix.com/title/80145240?s=i&amp;amp;trkid=14170286"&gt;Wild Wild Country&lt;/a&gt;, I highly recommend you watch it. The story told, along with the wealth of footage they got their hands on makes it an incredible watch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The soundtrack is also excellent, I've put together the soundtrack as a playlist on Apple Music, you can find it &lt;a href="https://itunes.apple.com/gb/playlist/wild-wild-country-soundtrack/pl.u-4Jomzk2tMMl6Gm"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>A Short Review of 'Freedom from the Known'</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/a-short-review-of-freedom-from-the-known-d22f52f8cdd3.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-10-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-10-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2017-10-13:/a-short-review-of-freedom-from-the-known-d22f52f8cdd3.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__jQR__j9gf6__MDS8XZSsef0A.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Freedom from the Known can be a tough book to crack, the lessons offered within are almost dismissed by the arguments made within the book, on top of that it's likely most won't be in a position to even accept what they read as they are reading it. Despite these …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__jQR__j9gf6__MDS8XZSsef0A.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Freedom from the Known can be a tough book to crack, the lessons offered within are almost dismissed by the arguments made within the book, on top of that it's likely most won't be in a position to even accept what they read as they are reading it. Despite these barriers, there is still wonderful lessons here calling out our own values, our judgements and what is preventing us from being truly free and present in each moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Authority&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Krishnamurti opens by trying to list out what are the things in life preventing us from true freedom. The list becomes more radical as time goes on. Here is a far from exhaustive list.
-Second-hand words, such as books which cause us to become second-hand people. A sort of circular logic here.
-Religious leaders and promise of something beyond this little life
-"That is our daily life and in that, there is no hope, and therefore every form of philosophy, every form of theological concept, is merely an escape from the actual reality of what is."
-Nationalism
-Tradition
-Pleasure
-Memory
-Fear
-Belief
-Relationships based on an 'image of the other end'
-What we should be
-Time -&amp;gt; "When I say I know you, I mean I knew you yesterday. I do not know you actually now."
-The observer/observed division
-Thought
This goes as far as "There is no guide, no teacher, no authority. There is only you-your relationship with others and with the world-there is nothing else." but even then we also need to dismiss the current 'you', "Forget all you know about yourself; forget all you have ever thought about yourself; we are going to start as if we knew nothing."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Krishnamurti spends a lot of time explaining what we shouldn't do, how we should not behave, the elements of this book that drive us towards what we should do are to some extent frustratingly brief. However this can be explained as 'showing us the path' as opposed to pointing out every bend on the way, but he might argue that there even is a path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Lack of Sympathy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe it's arguable but Krishnamurti sounds like he believes not many are willing to change, "those who are fairly secure socially and economically or who hold dogmatic beliefs and are content to accept themselves and things as they are or in a slightly modified form" are left out in the cold. That leaves a lot of people out in the cold. Despite this, I would argue if you are in this position it's still worth pursuing this book. Krishnamurti does an excellent job of calling out the baggage each of us holds that keeps us from being truly free in his definition, and while he may argue that we cannot go in half-hearted, casting aside some of the things holding us back from a present without judgement is worth pursuing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would also argue there is a lack of psychological sympathy here. Krishnamurti's goals are painfully simple and yet incredibly difficult to achieve. His response is also to achieve these things in the immediate. Do it now, without much care for human psychology or the difficulty involved in re-shaping your entire worldview in such a radical way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The 'Goal'&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What's left after dismissing these elements of our own minds? In Krishnamurti's words, "What is important is not a philosophy of life but to observe what is actually taking place in our daily life, inwardly and outwardly." And "Freedom is a state of mind-not freedom from something but a sense of freedom, a freedom to doubt and question everything and therefore so intense, active and vigorous that it throws away every form of dependence, slavery, conformity and acceptance." There is essentially a psychological death that will free us to observe the new and to truly live. "To die is to have a mind that is completely empty of itself, empty of its daily longings, pleasures and agonies. Death is a renewal, a mutation, in which thought does not function at all because thought is old. When there is death there is something totally new. Freedom from the known is death, and then you are living."&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>Friday Fun — Offline 8tracks playlists using Grooveshark</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/friday-fun-offline-8tracks-playlists-using-grooveshark-34b2512270df.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2014-07-25:/friday-fun-offline-8tracks-playlists-using-grooveshark-34b2512270df.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A lot of people have been asking about how they might offline their
favourite 8track tracks and I've come up with a rudimentary solution
while I was doing some offline coding. On 8tracks I've found a great
playlist series called Cold Machines created by user sowat on 8tracks and I …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A lot of people have been asking about how they might offline their
favourite 8track tracks and I've come up with a rudimentary solution
while I was doing some offline coding. On 8tracks I've found a great
playlist series called Cold Machines created by user sowat on 8tracks and I wanted to offline my favourited tracks from these playlists as they're great for
coding to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As there's no direct way to do this it's a several step process, but an
pretty easy one at that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use &lt;a href="http://8trackshelper.appspot.com/"&gt;8trackshelper&lt;/a&gt; to generate a plain-text copy of your favourite tracks, simply paste in your username.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then paste the plaintext list into &lt;a href="http://groovylists.com/?do=plaintext"&gt;groovylist's plaintext importer&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This will create a temporary playlist which you can add to an existing playlist or create a new one&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally, download &lt;a href="http://groovesquid.com/"&gt;groovesquid&lt;/a&gt; and have it offline your newly created playlist.(Note: I could not get the Mac variant to run as it was damaged, I simply downloaded the jar file and ran 'java -jar Groovesquid.jar' via the command line to get it up and running)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Success!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only minor complexity might be if you have more than 200 songs,
you'll need to split it up when pasting into groovylist but that's
pretty easy to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that's it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>The Counterfeited Blog Post</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/the-counterfeited-blog-post-9d8f32f5d4b4.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2014-02-22:/the-counterfeited-blog-post-9d8f32f5d4b4.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__FbR__Xju3pqCkl2d7OhLEFg.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been reading &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aspects_of_the_Novel"&gt;E. M. Forster's Aspects of the Novel&lt;/a&gt; and in it I came across a discussion on the French writer André Gide, specifically about his book &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Counterfeiters_%28novel%29"&gt;Les faux-monnayeurs(The Counterfeiters)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book is a merge of reality and fiction, Gide himself keeps a journal
of his life as …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__FbR__Xju3pqCkl2d7OhLEFg.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been reading &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aspects_of_the_Novel"&gt;E. M. Forster's Aspects of the Novel&lt;/a&gt; and in it I came across a discussion on the French writer André Gide, specifically about his book &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Counterfeiters_%28novel%29"&gt;Les faux-monnayeurs(The Counterfeiters)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book is a merge of reality and fiction, Gide himself keeps a journal
of his life as he writes the book and appears to merge the two. The
writer is celebrated in Aspects for hurling himself into the novel and
for not being bound by the style at the time or "All that is
prearranged".
There's a good example of it in this passage. When brought into a
discussion about the book Edouard(who is Gide's representation in the
book) responds on it's subject. I suggest you read this passage but keep
blogging in your mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"And what is its subject?" asked Sophroniska.
"There is none," said Edouard sharply. "My novel has no subject. No doubt that sounds foolish. Let us say, if you prefer, that it will not have 'a' subject.... 'A slice of life,' the naturalistic school used to say. The mistake that school made was always to cut its slice in the same direction, always lengthwise, in the direction of time. Why not cut it up and down? Or across? As for me, I don't want to cut it at all. You see what I mean. I want to put everything into my novel and not snip off my material either here or there. I have been working for a year, and there is nothing I haven't put in: all I see, all I know, all I can learn from other people's lives and my own."
"My poor man, you will bore your readers to death," cried Laura, unable to restrain her mirth. "Not at all. To get my effect, I am inventing, as my central character, a novelist, and the subject of my book will be the struggle between what reality offers him and what he tries to make of the offer."
"Have you planned out this book?" asked Sophroniska, trying to keep grave. "Of course not." "Why 'of course'?" "For a book of this type any plan would be unsuitable. The whole of it would go wrong if I decided any detail ahead. I am waiting for reality to dictate to me." "But I thought you wanted to get away from reality." "My novelist wants to get away, but I keep pulling him back. To tell proposed by reality, and the ideal reality." "Do tell us the name of this book," said Laura, in despair. "Very well. Tell it them, Bernard." "Les Faux Monnayeurs," said Bernard. "And now will you please tell us who these faux monnayeurs are." "I haven't the least idea." Bernard and Laura looked at each other and then at Sophroniska. There was the sound of a deep sigh. The fact was that ideas about money, depreciation, inflation, forgery, etc., had gradually invaded Edouard's book - just as theories of clothing invade Sartor Resartus and even assume the functions of characters. "Has any of you ever had hold of a false coin? " he asked after a pause. "Imagine a ten-franc piece, gold, false. It is actually worth a couple of sous, but it will remain worth ten francs until it is found out. Suppose I begin with the idea that — " "But why begin with an idea?" burst out Bernard, who was by now in a state of exasperation. "Why not begin with a fact? If you introduce the fact properly, the idea will follow of itself. If I was writing your Faux Monnayeurs I should begin with a piece of false money, with the ten-franc piece you were speaking of, and here it is! " So saying, Bernard pulled a ten-franc piece out of his pocket and flung it on the table. "There," he remarked. "It rings all right. I got it this morning from the grocer. It's worth more than a couple of sous, as it's
coated in gold, but it's actually made of glass. It will become quite transparent in time. No—don't rub it—you're going to spoil my false coin." Edouard had taken it and was examining it with the utmost attention. "How did the grocer get it?" "He doesn't know. He passed it on me for a joke, and then enlightened me, being a decent fellow. He let me have it for five francs. I thought that, since you were writing Les Faux Monnayeurs, you ought to see what false money is like, so I got it to show you. Now that you have looked at it, give it me back. I am sorry to see that reality has no interest for you." a pity," remarked Bernard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whilst reading this I couldn't help but think of bloggers in general.
Reality interests bloggers, it's what we typically write about. However
reality too sometimes puts us out. A lot of bloggers(myself included)
tend to write about things were really excited about, that's
understandable. Why would you write about things you don't find
interesting? The problem however is how we present our reality. People
tend to get a snapshot of things at the peak of the writer's enthusiasm.
So things become overly positive (or overly negative depending on their
personality).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I may write a post about an incredibly productive trick I've found only
to find a month later it's stopped working. Or some step I took in
simplifying has ended making everything more complicated. Either way
we're still trying to pawn off a counterfeit coin as real and it's
something that should be addressed. These posts are snapshots in time
but that's not how life works. For myself I'm hoping to cultivate a
habit of reviewing my last month of posts and adding addendums in the
hope there is a slightly more honest looking coin on the screen.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>Precision Nutrition Trail Fast</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/precision-nutrition-trail-fast-88a4c01976d5.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2014-02-06:/precision-nutrition-trail-fast-88a4c01976d5.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I went through the &lt;a href="https://www.precisionnutrition.com/intermittent-fasting/chapter-1"&gt;precision nutrition trial fast last&lt;/a&gt; Sunday, here's a low-down on how things went through each of the steps. I had trialled this while out and about in central London, but failed at around 5pm, I was disorganised and feeling incredibly dizzy from the crowds and noise …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I went through the &lt;a href="https://www.precisionnutrition.com/intermittent-fasting/chapter-1"&gt;precision nutrition trial fast last&lt;/a&gt; Sunday, here's a low-down on how things went through each of the steps. I had trialled this while out and about in central London, but failed at around 5pm, I was disorganised and feeling incredibly dizzy from the crowds and noise, so this time I planned ahead and did this from home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;10 PM Saturday&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Had a late dinner at the wonderful Chaat on RedChurch Street in Shoreditch. May as well have an epic last meal, right? The advantage of the late final meal was that I actually managed to ramble in from the street and only waited a minute for a table. I didn't over-do it in terms of food. I often get hungrier the next morning if I eat a huge meal the night before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;9 AM Saturday&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ran a 10k. This is the part I'm a little apprehensive about. I'm doing a training program to build up to my next half marathon, which includes 10k-15k runs on Sundays. I'm always starving after a run(naturally), so I'm curious to know how my body will tackle this. I also figure if this is a trial fast I should trial it during real life conditions, which would regularly include running.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;10 AM&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The post-run hunger has come over me, but the "breakfast" while not the most satisfying I've ever has taken the edge off. mL (1 cup) of green tea and 5 grams BCAA (branched chain amino acids) powder (or take 5 capsules).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1PM&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hunger cravings are on the up causing me to feel a little tender, but short breathing exercise and keeping busy seem to help.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2PM&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I've been a vegetarian for over three years, why do I still imagine greasy burgers when I get hunger pains?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Had a cigar to help things along. Is that cheating?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2:30PM&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beginning to get dizzy/spacy, the cigar may be the source. I've been using my standing desk and been walking constantly since the morning but now I seem to want prolonged sitting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3PM&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess you'd call this lunchtime, same intake as breakfast. It takes the edge off a little. Can't really sit still anymore, I'm just pacing around but feeling light-headed at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;6PM&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watching movies at the moment which seems to keep the hunger at bay. It's very much hitting a wall then finding energy from somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;9PM&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bailing an hour early and having a small cup of soup. Put frankly, I felt like I've had a temperature for the last few hours and all my body wanted was something wholesome in it, my resistance has totally fallen apart. I felt like I was coming down with an illness and I was worried the lack of food may have brought down my immune system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The illness effect was probably entirely psychosomatic, but I did feel
terrible the last few hours, the light spacious feeling I had earlier in
the day turned pretty horrible. I'd like to repeat this experiment
without the 10km run beforehand and see how it goes. One thing is for
sure, I have a completely new respect for anyone who can regularly fast.
The ways in which this hit my willpower were completely surprising.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>Internet Predictions for 2014 that didn't make it</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/internet-predictions-for-2014-that-didnt-make-it-ac552337f3a0.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-01-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-01-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2014-01-25:/internet-predictions-for-2014-that-didnt-make-it-ac552337f3a0.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__nhvDe6sbdxDYdqb03gItVQ.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bitcoin finally crashes forcing the Winklevoss twins to play themselves in a movie where viewers can watch a hooded Jessie Eisenberg slowly turn pale and descend to evil ala the Emperor from Star Wars.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The UK's porn blocking bill forces teens to re-learn the lost art of the forged parental …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__nhvDe6sbdxDYdqb03gItVQ.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bitcoin finally crashes forcing the Winklevoss twins to play themselves in a movie where viewers can watch a hooded Jessie Eisenberg slowly turn pale and descend to evil ala the Emperor from Star Wars.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The UK's porn blocking bill forces teens to re-learn the lost art of the forged parental signature. Mass confusion arises when it's discovered the unblock has already been requested by Dad. Millions of shame-filled Dads are suddenly forced to claim to be major supporters of net-neutrality leading Anonymous membership numbers to swell with 'red-faced' Dads who 'can totally hack' as they 'once set-up the DVD player without the manual'.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"Oh, I deleted my facebook account" becomes the new most annoying smug response, finally replacing "Oh I got rid of my TV ages ago".&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Social networks embrace 3d printing and inadvertently bring about a new era(and dimension) to the sending of unrequested dick-picks. Perverts rejoice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally, Anonymous give up trying to circumvent NSA spying using encryption and instead attempt to fill social networks with pointless content using automated bots, hoping to overrun the NSA data capturing systems in an operation codenamed, 'Clogged Pipes'. The bots strategies include retweeting infographics from 2011 and using trending topics as a call to arms to post inane 'me too' style tweets. Surprisingly the overall quality of content actually increases due to the bot's basic understanding of grammar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>Review of The Woman Who Walked Into Doors</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/review-of-the-woman-who-walked-into-doors-7aec5acb710c.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-01-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-01-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2014-01-23:/review-of-the-woman-who-walked-into-doors-7aec5acb710c.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__6XmyAy6zsOLl0UDSPzgn1A.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last night I finished Roddy Doyle's The Woman Who Walked Into Doors and
I figured I'd write a quick review on it. It's a book on the life of an
Irish working-class woman named Paula who is struggling with an abusive
husband and attempting to keep her family from the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__6XmyAy6zsOLl0UDSPzgn1A.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last night I finished Roddy Doyle's The Woman Who Walked Into Doors and
I figured I'd write a quick review on it. It's a book on the life of an
Irish working-class woman named Paula who is struggling with an abusive
husband and attempting to keep her family from the brink that her
husband creates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The details in this book are what make it particularly excellent
writing. The lead character recalls incredibly specific details that
bring her tragic story to life. There's a few mildly absurd elements to
the book, but they're grounded in the unrelenting reality the lead
character describes. A chipped plate, the heat from a bag of chips on a
cold day, an attempt to describe the burning sensation of being
repeatedly kicked in the back. These elements are what kept me turning
the pages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The build-up towards the end is also pretty incredible, the character
becomes whole in the utter despair she describes and the fortitude she
shows feels staggering. She's both incredibly vulnerable yet seems to
have no end to her strength.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the downsides of the book is that while you will eventually come
to fall for the lead character, her development takes a little too long.
For most of the book you'll feel constantly distant with Paula until she
eventually shares the true reality and despair of her situation. It's
not too much of a downside, it all pays off eventually and this downside
may simply mean the book needs a re-read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd recommend this one to someone that can handle a harsh unrelenting
book. You'll be rewarded, but it comes at a price.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>Legitimate ways to support good movies</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/legitimate-ways-to-support-good-movies-2fb11e565d2d.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2014-01-11:/legitimate-ways-to-support-good-movies-2fb11e565d2d.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__xU2KVV__mC4quGix9krfh4A__2x.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I watched Akira Kurosawa's Ikiru, after reading
through some of the Criterion info on Kurosawa I realised I'd watched a
bunch of his movies, I'm a huge fan of Seven Samurai.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Criterion Collection is a wonderful distribution company and I'm a
huge fan of a number of their …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/1__xU2KVV__mC4quGix9krfh4A__2x.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I watched Akira Kurosawa's Ikiru, after reading
through some of the Criterion info on Kurosawa I realised I'd watched a
bunch of his movies, I'm a huge fan of Seven Samurai.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Criterion Collection is a wonderful distribution company and I'm a
huge fan of a number of their filmmakers, so much so that I wanted to
try and support the service more. Since I live fairly lightly in terms
of possessions I can't really justify $40 on a DVD or Blu-Ray.
Especially since I'll probably have moved elsewhere and be forced to
ditch the media before I can watch it a second time.
It's a shame when distribution companies haven't really adopted digital
distribution. I am aware that Criterion is on Hulu(now something else), but unfortunately as I'm not a US resident I can't access/support it. If you are and can access it, I highly recommend checking out some of their movies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily I found a more old-school method to (in some small way) support Criterion movies. Near to where I work is a wonderful film-center called Close-Up that has a huge collection of both DVDs and books to rent. I'll definitely be making use of it for the time being.
If you know of another way I can access the Criterion movies in the
EU(or just without a US credit-card), I'd love to know.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>Fasting</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/fasting-636565d35b97.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2014-01-03:/fasting-636565d35b97.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So I've been looking into intermittent fasting lately for several
reasons. Firstly, as a means to get a leaner physique, but also as I'm
looking to do more research into leaner more efficient eating as it is.
I'm also hoping a side effect of it will promote generally more mindful …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So I've been looking into intermittent fasting lately for several
reasons. Firstly, as a means to get a leaner physique, but also as I'm
looking to do more research into leaner more efficient eating as it is.
I'm also hoping a side effect of it will promote generally more mindful
eating habits. I came across quite a useful resource in www.precisionnutrition.com. They provide a trail fast plan, which I'm going to attempt once a week for the next few weeks to see how I react to fasting in general. During this time I'll also do further research into fasting and hopefully work out a strategy that can work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're interested in the topic itself, I'd start with &lt;a href="https://www.precisionnutrition.com/intermittent-fasting"&gt;Experiments with Intermittent Fasting&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://leangains.com/"&gt;www.leangains.com&lt;/a&gt;. It seems the whole topic lacks any hard and fast rules. From my reading the only approach you can take is just try it, log the net effects and make alterations as you see fit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll log how things progress up here.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>Avoid anxiety with gratitude</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/avoid-anxiety-with-gratitude-65eb140928a5.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2014-01-02:/avoid-anxiety-with-gratitude-65eb140928a5.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Christmas holidays are coming to an end. The flash of New Years
fireworks are already beginning to dim in your memory. You might be
returning to work or you've already returned. Maybe you're feeling
disgruntled and little sad that it all went by so fast and what do you …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Christmas holidays are coming to an end. The flash of New Years
fireworks are already beginning to dim in your memory. You might be
returning to work or you've already returned. Maybe you're feeling
disgruntled and little sad that it all went by so fast and what do you
even have to show for yourself?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today while I was kicking off my morning writing routine, it was turning into a stream of conscious thought. Eventually I just happened to start creating list of all amazing things I'd done over the holidays. It came to a list of 21 events that I really and truly appreciated and there was certainly room for more if I'd thought about it. Looking back and forcing myself to remember them gave me an overwhelmingly contented feeling. The anxiety of returning to the post holiday work world and the fear of the Monday morning blues just faded into excitement about the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On top of that it's also kicking off a new habit. Once a week while I'm
doing my morning writing I'm going to write up a list of everything I'm
grateful for over the last week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could not recommend doing this exercise more. Right now, just write
out the list of things you're thankful for over the holidays. It'll only
take a few minutes, I guarantee if you're in the right frame of mind you
won't regret it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>Vegetarian</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/vegetarian-3c437a98aa85.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-12-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2013-12-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2013-12-27:/vegetarian-3c437a98aa85.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Deciding to become vegetarian is not an easy step. I decided to dip my
toe in the water several years ago by trying a month of not eating meat,
I would highly recommend everyone try this at least once just to see
what it might be like. I enjoyed the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Deciding to become vegetarian is not an easy step. I decided to dip my
toe in the water several years ago by trying a month of not eating meat,
I would highly recommend everyone try this at least once just to see
what it might be like. I enjoyed the food I ate that month so much I've
decided to keep it up indefinitely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Why?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, I chose vegetarianism after reading Peter Singer's "Animal Liberation", but you may have your own sources of inspiration.
It's a great book and I would highly recommend it to veggie/non-veggies
alike. It persuaded me to consider the idea of giving up meat and if I'm
ever drawn into an ethical argument about meat-eating I have some decent arguments to fall back on. I would like to be able to say that I'm a vegetarian purely out of ethics but that's simply not the case. In fact being honest I was being entirely ethically consistent with regard to meat-eating, I would have to go vegan and right now I find that a step too far. I'm almost certain that dairy cows and egg producing chickens suffer far more than their meat-producing equivalents purely due to their lifespan(the average meat producing chicken lives around 8 weeks).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My real reason for giving up meat was simply boredom. I was bored of
eating the same things at restaurants using the same ingredients for the
same dinners. My relationship with food was a sort of thoughtless and
comfortable, but not interesting. Like I suspect it is for many. I'm
certain we could all make our dishes more interesting but I figured a
grand act would push me to try new things and it certainly has. I now
cook with ingredients I'd never even heard of. In fact before the switch
I would argue I could barely cook at all. Vegetarianism is simply an inspiring limitation. Oh and also &lt;a href="https://zenhabits.net/plant-fueled/"&gt;zenhabits&lt;/a&gt; has a really sweet list on why you should consider vegetarianism too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question I found myself asking is, how do you keep yourself motivated in a world of meat-eaters. One fun thing I do, is cook a new dish every week until I have enough dishes that I like that I can keep cooking everyday and not get bored. Each week just find a new dish that you feel like making(curry, pasta-based etc), pick up ingredients from the nicest vegetable shop(having nice vegetables can be key to keeping you motivated) around you and cook. Some things will be great and some will be disasters, but it's all fun. Four months in and I'm already building a great collection of recipes I find tasty. I've even started a list
my partner will eat, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Effects&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm genuinely surprised how much vegetarianism has affected
me. For staters, when people hear about it they become incredibly
interested in it. Why do it? How difficult is it? Am I taking
supplements etc? It's a great chance to try persuade people to do the
same, I usually try by explaining just how easy the whole thing is. Some
people have been persuaded to try a vegetarian meal once a week, I
figure after that they can make their own enquires into becoming
entirely vegetarian.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm a much healthier eater that I was before. Vegetarianism is a
limitation that increases reflection. As a result you find yourself
dwelling on everything you eat. For me, for the first time in my life I
have this mental checkbox that says, "Does this contain meat?" that I
had to ask every time I wanted to eat something. Very soon after another question appeared, "Is this healthy?" and if it wasn't "Do I really want this?" and in most cases, I really didn't.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to the constant questioning of what I was eating and the fact that
I've been trying crazy new ingredients I found myself getting much more
interested in my snacking options. We all snack and it's something I
can't forgo at certain points in the day. As I tended to find myself in
alternative food stores perusing random ingredients I tended to pickup
weird nuts or some dried fruit I'd never tried. My snacking has gone
from chocolate, crisps and jellies(I'm a real sucker for those), to
nuts, fruit and cereals. This really was a surprising effect and as I
had originally said to calm myself "You may not be able to eat meat but
at least you can stick with sugary treats if gets you down!". It's not
gotten to the stage where when I eat, say a chocolate bar I find it
tastes stale, unpleasant, cheap and for the most part all the same. I
genuinely do not miss them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Difficulties&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One difficulty that will arise is social occasions.
Dealing with this is usually a matter of good preparations, but it
doesn't hurt to have a few minimal ingredients dishes in case of a worst
case scenario. I'd flown home to see my family, who had forgotten I'd
told them I wasn't eating meat and had thrown a BBQ as the weather was nice. I went digging and found some potatoes, some vegetables, flour and pitta bread in the back of a cupboard and threw together some awesome veggie burgers(I'll throw up a recipe later). While it didn't stop
anyone from eating meat, most said they loved them and would have no
problem eating them as a substitute. I highly recommend them with sweet chilli sauce!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is also the cases where you will just crave meat, that's almost
unavoidable. It's a rare occurrence for me, but hangovers are my
kryptonite. I crave a fry in the morning but thankfully I haven't given
in. Despite the obvious tastiness factor of fried meat, I tried to
figure out why a fry in question was such a difficult one for me to cope
with forgoing. I thought about it and realised that whenever I was
having a fry it was usually with friends, the smell of frying sausages
and bacon coaxing us out of our slumber and around a table chatting
about the prior nights silliness and wolfing down food. I realised the
subtraction of meat from this picture really doesn't change anything at
all that matters. The point being that, if you stop to think about what
you're craving you may realise that taste isn't everything. Though it
also helps that vegetarian fries are awesome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Tips&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found when I first started looking for recipes I was overwhelmed by choice. Eventually I came across &lt;a href="https://www.bbcgoodfood.com"&gt;BBC's good food site&lt;/a&gt;, which is just decided to awesome food, that's rated by users. It has a really good vegetarian sections with some awesome recipes, I'll share the ones that have worked for me at a later stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I often find myself with a ton of spare vegetables where recipes have annoyingly required two onions and I can only find a pack of three. If you find yourself with the same problem try a recipe that's very loose with the ingredients. It might be a soup or a pasta dish with a nice sauce, for me because I like to use quinoa and lentils in a lot of my dishes I tried to find something that used both, with a lot of random vegetables.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>Happy Programmers Day!</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/happy-programmers-day-d14d9063b43f.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-09-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2013-09-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2013-09-13:/happy-programmers-day-d14d9063b43f.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Happy Programmers Day!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have a productive one…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or you're sacked.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>Writing Less</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/writing-less-2757f83c3a48.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-07-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2013-07-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2013-07-29:/writing-less-2757f83c3a48.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"I didn't have time to write a short letter, so I wrote a long one
instead." — Mark Twain&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lately I've been struggling with consistently writing. I find it
difficult to sit down in the morning and begin to write. Usually ideas
fall out of my head and I get into …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"I didn't have time to write a short letter, so I wrote a long one
instead." — Mark Twain&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lately I've been struggling with consistently writing. I find it
difficult to sit down in the morning and begin to write. Usually ideas
fall out of my head and I get into a flow quite quickly but recently,
without a clear idea sitting in my head for a period of time I simply
can't put pen to paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also just finished reading Charlie Brooker's article on "`Reducing
my word emissions" and I must admit some of his points are pretty convincing. There is a lot of noise on the internet and I suspect a lot of my unwillingness to return to writing is due to this.
I'm also working on a project similar to stackoverflow and I'm truly beginning to appreciate the format of the site. The internet simply has too much noise to signal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm going to try keep a hard limit on my posts of 200 words and see
if the limit can't help the writers block.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>South Africa</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/south-africa-c688b9070707.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-07-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2013-07-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2013-07-20:/south-africa-c688b9070707.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'd been in Cape Town for two weeks beforehand, just remotely working
and doing some sightseeing around the area. So I had plenty of time for
prep for the trip and was pretty relaxed arriving at Ashanti Logde(where
the trip starts). The trip was booked through African Budget
Safari's …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'd been in Cape Town for two weeks beforehand, just remotely working
and doing some sightseeing around the area. So I had plenty of time for
prep for the trip and was pretty relaxed arriving at Ashanti Logde(where
the trip starts). The trip was booked through African Budget
Safari's which seemed to the cheapest option around. The dates I had originally planned to travel with(and booked) were unavailable and ABS happily changed my dates and gave me a heavy discount(about 25%). On top of that I declined the free activities in Cape Town, so I was given free upgrade at Ashanti to my own room. So I can definitely recommend African Budget Safari's as an agent and also chance your arm and see what discounts you can get.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We met up with others on the trip and waited for the trip leaders. The
group was mostly mid-to-late twenties with two outliers in the
forties/fifties. Still an excellent result as I was worried the group
would have a much older average age. As I traveled I noticed the more
expensive tour groups had a lot of older people traveling and it sounded
like an awful time for younger folk traveling with them. I would highly
recommend finding out a rough average age of the people going on the
trip beforehand, our group was wonderful so living in each other's
pockets really wasn't a problem. However, if you get a bad group,
there's not a lot you can do for 6–8 weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The group was 16 in total, about 8 of which were going the whole 42
days(and then some) to Kenya, so there wasn't a lot of swapping around
of the group. The trip is split into 3 main sub-trips(but there's
shorter trips within this also), so I was glad the group remained
consistent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually trip crew arrives, three guys from Zimbabwe. A chef, a driver
and the trip leader. It's usually those three guys, but we had a trainee
driver with us on this trip(to get his head around the route to
Zimbabwe). They all seemed lovely. We made out local payments and a run through the next few days was done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Cash&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things I was sweating about was having access to local
money. How it was relayed to me was that I would need to have all of my spending money at the start of the trip. This seemed dubious as I really didn't want to have a ton of cash with me while traveling. The trip
leader alleviated these fears by explaining that there was tons of ATMs
on the way and you can take out as much Rand as you wanted as South
Africa, Namibia, Zimbabwe and most campsites in Botswana would all
accept it. I'd recommend getting a ton of Rand and don't bother with
Namibian dollars at all(it's a straight one-to-one currency rate so
there's no disadvantage and the Rand is more widely accepted). That
seems a lot less complicated. Make sure you have enough USD for Visa's
and certain activities, most take USD but some(like the Serengeti)
require it, try get this USD in Cape Town as they'll provide reliable
bills. You can get USD out in Zimbabwe but the quality of the bills can
be really poor and all countries(other than Zimbabwe), won't accept
dirty bills. Most people on the trip seemed to struggle to get money
converted in Cape Town, that they were residents or that they were
leaving the country in less than 24 hours. It's tough to find cash,
especially on a Sunday the day before we were leaving. However, I was
recommended a currency exchange place at the V &amp;amp; A Waterfront, that
would convert money. Make sure if you get Rand out of the bank to take a receipt to prove the cash you're bringing is legit. I didn't and had to
keep the Rand I'd just taken out and get more USD on my credit card.
Again, wasn't an issue as everywhere takes Rand, but just to bear this
in mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other than that, the trip leader simply explained that the first few
day. A nervous feeling came over me when he mentioned 'It's okay, we
have a late wake-up. We just need to be gone by 7am'. I could see there
was going to be a lot of early starts in my future… So we were all up and out early for day one. We had a huge orange monster of a truck(not bus, truck) for transport. Bags, camping gear and tents go into the bottom, small bags up top where you sit/sleep/drink/live. Each seat had a personal locker where you can lock your stuff with, which was nice, but note that this is not available in all(or even most) of the trucks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were recommended to leave all valuables on the truck, money, passport etc. Our driver slept in the cab of the truck and the crew always kept it secure and I noticed they also keep their own valuables on there, so it certainly seemed a lot safer than on my person or in a tent. The truck itself was pretty chunky but comfortable, which is great considering how long you'll be in it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without much ceremony we were off.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>Overlanding</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/overlanding-ac775c297d46.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-07-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2013-07-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2013-07-18:/overlanding-ac775c297d46.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, for the last 6 weeks I've been over-landing from Cape Town to
Nairobi. I decided to ditch almost all of my tech for the trip. My
Samsung Galaxy S3 and my Thinkpad were replaced with an old school phone
and a notepad. I also picked up a tiny little …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, for the last 6 weeks I've been over-landing from Cape Town to
Nairobi. I decided to ditch almost all of my tech for the trip. My
Samsung Galaxy S3 and my Thinkpad were replaced with an old school phone
and a notepad. I also picked up a tiny little Sandisk Sansa Clip MP3
player for the trip. For reading I had my Kindle and a few USB keys for
storing files and for Portableapps(which was a disaster I'll write about
another time). The decision for ditching was simply a need to be away
from the tech and connectedness. I'm in Africa for a reason, and I
simply didn't want the constant distractions a phone brings me. I
couldn't help but notice on the way others were clamouring for internet
when they thought it was an option. I appreciated having that option.
Anyway, as a result I have a lot of time to write with the long journeys
during the day and frankly I wish I had more information on the trip to
see where the land lies before starting, so I figured I write this blog
to give others a heads up and I've split things up into each
destination.
Here's the skinny on countries I hit&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;South Africa&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Namibia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bostswana&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Zimbabwe&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Zambia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Malawi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tanzania(and Zanzibar)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kenya&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll fill these in as links when the posts are written.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>Why Study Philosophy</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/why-study-philosophy-1aba210c328b.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2012-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2012-06-26:/why-study-philosophy-1aba210c328b.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I finished my final exam in a course I was taking in
philosophy and I figured now was a good time to explain the question
everyone asks when I tell him what I'm studying. Why study philosophy?
To be honest, my answers were always pretty poor, mostly I'd say …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I finished my final exam in a course I was taking in
philosophy and I figured now was a good time to explain the question
everyone asks when I tell him what I'm studying. Why study philosophy?
To be honest, my answers were always pretty poor, mostly I'd say it was
just an interest, but that never really explained the value I got from
it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I started studying it began as a need to understand the structures
of our society, what drove capitalism or democracy, are there even valid
alternatives to them? Were they actually implemented and if so did they
last long? &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paris_Commune"&gt;The Paris Commune&lt;/a&gt;, a period in 1871 when Paris was run entirely by anarchists, stuck in my mind. How did anarchists run anything? Clearly whatever I thought an anarchist was, was incorrect. On top of that I also wanted to challenge the religious dogmatism around me and needed rational arguments to give a sort of structure to what was angering me in society, this was the basic initial drive towards philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Philosophy is simply a formal combination of challenging what's around
you within a historical context. A lot of philosophy books read like
history books, you have a huge list of eras, within which is a huge list
of thinkers and you follow and progress through the theories supplied
through the ages. You pick up the terminology, the great thinkers and
most importantly the evolving theories, you begin to see how human
thought evolved through the ages. It's incredibly interesting, but
what's most important is how it shapes your view of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm going to try show this using the abstract topic of the self. Bear
with me here. What interested philosophers around the 16th Century was
the dilemmas of morality, and one issue with that was the notion of the
self, which was something tackled by &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Locke"&gt;John Locke&lt;/a&gt;. If you did something
bad many years ago, should you be punished now for it? The problem was
to do with the self over time, did it exist, how so, how do we handle it
in our day-to-day thought? I thought it sounded meaningless and crazy
too. But upon reading into this, great thinkers have actually altered
how I view the world, in surprising ways. For me, it was a philosopher
named &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Derek_Parfit"&gt;Derek Parfit&lt;/a&gt;, who showed using a few thought experiments, that the idea of you being the same self over time is crazy. He argued that even if you met yourself twenty years from now, other than this preconceived notion of the self you wouldn't be much like this person and in reality you wouldn't really care about them. Frankly, I'm explaining it badly(I highly recommend
reading Parfit if you can), but once I read through most of Parfit's work, some set of internal views I had on the world shifted. It's hard to describe the sensation of having a fundamental view change within, but I can describe the effect. Things like worrying about the future or acquiring things "in case I need it", become completely irrelevant. I cared less and less about making long term investments that only pay off years later, don't get me wrong I plan for the future, but I don't lock myself down into anything I might regret later on. Everything had a more temporary feel about it. More extremely, it actually provided a more comforting view of death in general. Why worry, whoever that person is on his death bed, won't be much like me, so why care? I've heard the Buddist mindset of "now-ness", being mindful and in the moment, but hearing these empty phrases from these supposed Zen-masters without any rationality just washed over me. The rational argument supplied a belief and it took root, I can't shake it, maybe I'll discover someone who trounces Parfit, I'll look forward to reading it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was just one of those epiphanies I've had while studying philosophy. I wanted to keep this fairly short, but there have been several. For morality, I moved from being a libertarian, to Mill's rule utilitarian, to Kant's universalizability, to Rawl's Egalitarianism and finally to Luck Egalitarianism. You don't need to know any of these terms but this is just to highlight how much a single view of the world can evolve. This effects how I vote, what causes I support, the charities I give to and countless other important choices I make in my life. I've had similar changes across other branches of philosophy too. The notion of philosophy may appear dry, dull and pointless but it's effects aren't. It's hard to explain without simply trying it out for a while. If you can, take a course or pick up a book and see if it takes root. If it doesn't, what have you lost?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, philosophy is a way to challenge the beliefs you're culturally imbued with. Admittedly, it may not make radical changes in your life but the next decision you make may be done with a little bit more reflection, and as Plato says(and what is probably at the start/end of every article supporting study of philosophy), "the unexamined life is not worth living".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some books I'd recommend are Bertrand Russell's History of Western
Philosophy or if you can manage it, John Cottingham's Western
Sophie's World by Jostein Gaarder or the excellent Zen and the Art of
Motorcycle Maintenance by Pirsig.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>Vegetarian</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/vegetarian-9bb1abb30879.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2011-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2011-05-07:/vegetarian-9bb1abb30879.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Deciding to become vegetarian is not an easy step. I decided to dip my
toe in the water at the start of the year by trying a month of not
eating meat, I would highly recommend everyone try this at least once
just to see what it might be like …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Deciding to become vegetarian is not an easy step. I decided to dip my
toe in the water at the start of the year by trying a month of not
eating meat, I would highly recommend everyone try this at least once
just to see what it might be like. I enjoyed the food I ate that month
so much I've decided to keep it up indefinitely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why?&lt;/strong&gt; Personally, I chose vegetarianism after reading Peter Singer's
"Animal Liberation", but you may have your own sources of inspiration.
It's a great book and I would highly recommend it to veggie/non-veggies
alike. It persuaded me to consider the idea of giving up meat and if I'm
ever drawn into an ethical argument about meat-eating I have some decent
arguments to fall back on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to be able to say that I'm a vegetarian purely out of
ethics but that's simply not the case. In fact being honest I was being
entirely ethically consistent with regard to meat-eating, I would have
to go vegan and right now I find that a step too far. I'm almost certain
that dairy cows and egg producing chickens suffer far more than their
meat-producing equivalents purely due to their lifespan(the average meat
producing chicken lives around 8 weeks).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My real reason for giving up meat was simply boredom. I was bored of
eating the same things at restaurants using the same ingredients for the
same dinners. My relationship with food was a sort of thoughtless and
comfortable, but not interesting. Like I suspect it is for many. I'm
certain we could all make our dishes more interesting but I figured a
grand act would push me to try new things and it certainly has. I now
cook with ingredients I'd never even heard of. In fact before the switch
I would argue I could barely cook at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vegetarianism is simply an inspiring limitation. Oh and also
&lt;a href="http://zenhabits.net/how-to-become-a-vegetarian-the-easy-way/"&gt;zenhabits&lt;/a&gt; has a really sweet list on why you should consider vegetarianism too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How?&lt;/strong&gt; The question is, how do you keep yourself motivated in a world
of meat-eaters. One fun thing I do, is cook a new dish every week until
I have enough dishes that I like that I can keep cooking everyday and
not get bored. Each week just find a new dish that you feel like
making(curry, pasta-based etc), pick up ingredients from the nicest
vegetable shop(having nice vegetables can be key to keeping you
motivated) around you and cook. Some things will be great and some will
be disasters, but it's all fun. Four months in and I'm already building
a great collection of recipes I find tasty. I've even started
my partner will eat, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Effects&lt;/strong&gt; I'm genuinely surprised how much vegetarianism has affected
me. For staters, when people hear about it they become incredibly
interested in it. Why do it? How difficult is it? Am I taking
supplements etc? It's a great chance to try persuade people to do the
same, I usually try by explaining just how easy the whole thing is. Some
people have been persuaded to try a vegetarian meal once a week, I
figure after that they can make their own enquires into becoming
entirely vegetarian.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm a much healthier eater that I was before. Vegetarianism is a
limitation that increases reflection. As a result you find yourself
dwelling on everything you eat. For me, for the first time in my life I
have this mental checkbox that says, "Does this contain meat?" that I
had to ask every time I wanted to eat something. Very soon after another
question appeared, "Is this healthy?" and if it wasn't "Do I really want
this?" and in most cases, I really didn't.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to the constant questioning of what I was eating and the fact that
I've been trying crazy new ingredients I found myself getting much more
interested in my snacking options. We all snack and it's something I
can't forgo at certain points in the day. As I tended to find myself in
alternative food stores perusing random ingredients I tended to pickup
weird nuts or some dried fruit I'd never tried. My snacking has gone
from chocolate, crisps and jellies(I'm a real sucker for those), to
nuts, fruit and cereals. This really was a surprising effect and as I
had originally said to calm myself "You may not be able to eat meat but
at least you can stick with sugary treats if gets you down!". It's not
gotten to the stage where when I eat, say a chocolate bar I find it
tastes stale, unpleasant, cheap and for the most part all the same. I
genuinely do not miss them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Difficulties&lt;/strong&gt; One difficult that will arise is social occasions.
Dealing with this is usually a matter of good preparations, but it
doesn't hurt to have a few minimal ingredients dishes in case of a worst
case scenario. I'd flown home to see my family, who had forgotten I'd
told them I wasn't eating meat and had thrown a BBQ as the weather was
nice. I went digging and found some potatoes, some vegetables, flour and
pitta bread in the back of a cupboard and threw together some awesome
veggie burgers(I'll throw up a recipe later). While it didn't stop
anyone from eating meat, most said they loved them and would have no
problem eating them as a substitute. I highly recommend them with sweet
chilli sauce!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is also the cases where you will just crave meat, that's almost
unavoidable. It's a rare occurrence for me, but hangovers are my
kryptonite. I crave a fry in the morning but thankfully I haven't given
in. Despite the obvious tastiness factor of fried meat, I tried to
figure out why a fry in question was such a difficult one for me to cope
with forgoing. I thought about it and realised that whenever I was
having a fry it was usually with friends, the smell of frying sausages
and bacon coaxing us out of our slumber and around a table chatting
about the prior nights silliness and wolfing down food. I realised the
subtraction of meat from this picture really doesn't change anything at
all that matters. The point being that, if you stop to think about what
you're craving you may realise that taste isn't everything. Though it
also helps that vegetarian fries are awesome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tips&lt;/strong&gt; I found when I first started looking for recipes I was
overwhelmed by choice. Eventually I came across &lt;a href="http://www.bbcgoodfood.com/content/recipes/vegetarian/"&gt;BBC's good food site&lt;/a&gt;, which
is just decided to awesome food, that's rated by users. It has a really
good vegetarian sections with some awesome recipes, I'll share the ones
that have worked for me at a later stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I often find myself with a ton of spare vegetables where recipes have
annoyingly required two onions and I can only find a pack of three. If
you find yourself with the same problem try a recipe that's very loose
with the ingredients. It might be a soup or a pasta dish with a nice
sauce, for me because I like to use quinoa and lentils in a lot of my
dishes I tried to find something that used both, with a lot of random
vegetables. Eventually I came across this &lt;a href="http://vegweb.com/index.php?topic=39142.0"&gt;recipe&lt;/a&gt;, its super
healthy and really filling. I'd highly recommend a spicy pasta sauce
with it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>The Power of Nightmares</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/the-power-of-nightmares-5717f5a92295.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-12-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2010-12-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2010-12-28:/the-power-of-nightmares-5717f5a92295.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I always wondered why, if the UK/US were at war with terrorism, why they
always made such fantastic declarations about how powerful terrorists
were and that they had infiltrated all elements of society? Surely this
would simply add more gas to the fire and prolong the effect of the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I always wondered why, if the UK/US were at war with terrorism, why they
always made such fantastic declarations about how powerful terrorists
were and that they had infiltrated all elements of society? Surely this
would simply add more gas to the fire and prolong the effect of the
initial attack in question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyhoo I guess my question has been answered, just watched &lt;a href="http://www.archive.org/details/ThePowerOfNightmares"&gt;The Power of
Nightmares&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adam Curtis you rock.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>The problem with God arguments</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/the-problem-with-god-arguments-c9543d98f6c8.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2010-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2010-11-05:/the-problem-with-god-arguments-c9543d98f6c8.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Atheists and theists alike have for centuries attempted to
debate the existence of God, desperately trying to reason out a
conclusive answer. The reality of this struck me while I was reading a
series of MIT lectures notes on arguments for and against the existence
of God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lecture notes …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Atheists and theists alike have for centuries attempted to
debate the existence of God, desperately trying to reason out a
conclusive answer. The reality of this struck me while I was reading a
series of MIT lectures notes on arguments for and against the existence
of God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lecture notes are very well written(so well written in fact the lazy
student in me probably wouldn't have bothered going to the lectures, if
I had the pleasure of taking the course in question). The course does a
decent job of explaining concepts such as deductive and inductive
reasons and a few other philosophical instruments, but this isn't the
source of my concern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;question grates on whenever I hear it. Lets take a small village in
England, a shopkeeper has just been murdered and a crowd has formed
around the scene of the crime. The police chief arrives sirens blaring,
barges through the crowd, quickly scans the situation and declares "Did
Mayor Dave do it!?". Everyone sighs, the Mayor is always blamed in such
cases. No-one remembers why the Mayor is blamed, it's just what's done.
The police chief along with his detectives then spend night and day
logically deducing if Mayor Dave is in fact the culprit. They always
come up short.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The obvious problem here is the police chief has taken the entirely
wrong approach, simply by asking the wrong question. I hope you know
where I'm going here, but the obvious alternative is instead to declare
"Lets look at the evidence and follow where it takes us". Why is this
approach not the same for the creation of existence? Why have we taken
only one, just one of the infinite amount of concepts, entities,
processes, whatever and decided to blow all our time reasoning about
this perfect being? A giant dragon by the name of Bill created the
universe, discuss. Why is this not getting the equilavent levels of
academic debate as Did God do it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pointlessness of these discussions hit me when the MIT lecture
notes went into detail on the specifics of what theists and atheists are
reasoning about. Theists say God is Omnipotent, Omniscient and
Good(OOG), then the atheists spend time arguing that if this is the case
you can infer(eventually) that because there is evil God must not exist.
The theists respond with, ah but if the evils that occur were always
outweighed by the future good generated by the original evil act(and
this is guaranteed by God), then in essence the overall good is
maintained. My counter point here would be, if God guarantees all evils
are outdone by future good, isn't it our moral obligation to always be
evil? But, I'm not going to be sucked into this rubbish debate. The
atheists have lost even by stepping into the playing field. I think
we've all forgotten that invention of God(I'm going back as far as
Dionysus here), was infact to counter a sensible lifestyle, to say screw
you to logic and reason and let emotions run wild. Two thousand years
later and we've forgotten this, blowing valid time reasoning about
effectively an emotional revolt against reason. Let the theists produce
all the reasoned arguments they can think of for God and when the exact
same argument doesn't just as validly apply to Bill the giant Dragon or
the Flying Spaghetti Monster I'll step up and listen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until then I applaud science and philosophers for at least attempting
to produce valid reasons for the existence of the world around us. It's
an incredibly slow process, but at least it's in the right direction.
One that's lately caught my attention is the `Anthropic
principle.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>Descartes, Second Meditation</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/descartes-second-meditation-f5d3426ef9ee.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-09-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2010-09-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2010-09-20:/descartes-second-meditation-f5d3426ef9ee.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In Descarte's second meditation, he moves onto classification of the
mind and body. The initial argument is that he must exist, even if there
is absolutely nothing in the world he must exist, even if all existence
is presented by a deceiver, he still must exist to be deceived. He …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In Descarte's second meditation, he moves onto classification of the
mind and body. The initial argument is that he must exist, even if there
is absolutely nothing in the world he must exist, even if all existence
is presented by a deceiver, he still must exist to be deceived. He runs
into an interesting question of what defines existence and he
me. This is a good starting point, but doesn't entirely answer the
question of self. For example, Determinism may entirely circumvent the
essence of self. He also seems to belittle the affects of sensory
perception. If everything I perceive through the senses is a deception,
are my thoughts truly my own or am I being led by a deceiver? Is my
definition of self as a thinking thing even valid? For example, Descarte
effectively defines imagination as "simply contemplating the shape or
image of a corporeal thing". In essence stating that even imagination
can be corrupted by the deceiver. He closes off the imagination as
superfluous to perception of your own nature. Essentially Descarte is
cutting off any contact to the physical world, even imagination that
begins with a perceived event or corporeal object. However, the mental
acts involved in say sensory perception or imagination, these can be
considered real.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually after repeated questioning he boils down to the reasonable to
"I am a thinking thing". He separates the corporeal with the mental by
de-construction a piece of wax and stating, surely we cannot be
naturally aware of all states of wax, we use perception through the mind
alone. It is a mental cognitive judgement on the nature of wax, which of
course is prone to error. Descarte has built up the importance of
'mind', and more specifically judgements and understanding over say
imagination. He cuts us off with reality and predicates all
understanding of anything(real or not) with the self. So, in every act
of understanding we establish the nature of our own minds a little
further, where his reasoning for this is, I don't know. Descarte draws
the line at comprehension so overcomes the deceiver argument. If a
deceiver gave me a sample of wax to play with, my comprehension of the
ultimate nature of this wax would be proof of self, not the imagining of
wax and not the physical contact with the wax. Essentially, the
foundation of all comprehension is 'self'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though I find myself agreeing with many sections of this chapter, it's
never through Descarte's reasoning, but purely I agree that they are
acceptable starting points. The question remains, I do not understand
the nature of existence, nor do I understand the true nature of
thoughts, yet we've made an inference anyway. Maybe the appearance of
thought is simply the motion of the deceiver, or a computing simulation
in action.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>Reflections on Descartes Meditations</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/reflections-on-descartes-meditations-a03fd614a3f0.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-09-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2010-09-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2010-09-11:/reflections-on-descartes-meditations-a03fd614a3f0.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So I've just finished Descarte's Meditations on First Philosophy and I'm
going to try put up a response to each Meditation in the next few days,
as well as the objections and responses Descarte added after the initial
six meditations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I whole-heartedly accept the I have the unfair advantage of …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So I've just finished Descarte's Meditations on First Philosophy and I'm
going to try put up a response to each Meditation in the next few days,
as well as the objections and responses Descarte added after the initial
six meditations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I whole-heartedly accept the I have the unfair advantage of about four
centuries of human advancement over Descarte, but I will try my best to
level the playing field. I'll take each meditation as a separate
argument and accept(to some extent) all initial assertions Descarte
makes in each meditation. So for example in the second meditation
Descarte attempts to reason the existence of God and I'll dispute any
flawed reasoning he uses, within this meditation. However, he uses this
existence of God to infer further claims in other meditations. For this,
I'll accept(purely for arguments sake) the existence of God as a valid
assumption and attempt to dismiss again, any flawed reasoning he uses
based on this assumption. To be honest, it's a testament to the extent
of Descarte's doubt and refusal to accept but a few initial assumptions
that I can do this effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This for me is mostly an exercise in discovering if I can effectively
detect flawed reasoning and I'd consider Descarte's book quite a
difficult one purely due to the abstract nature of the arguments(but
this may be purely due to my naivety).&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry><entry><title>The Museum-going Cannibal</title><link href="https://shanedowling.com/the-museum-going-cannibal-5d5bb1a3fbd.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-09-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2010-09-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Shane Dowling</name></author><id>tag:shanedowling.com,2010-09-11:/the-museum-going-cannibal-5d5bb1a3fbd.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;From the lastest issue of philosophy now. I find it's on the right side of
harsh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Museum-going Cannibal&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;by Yahia Lababidi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upright specimen, looking to be fine-tuned on weekends by the civilizing
influence of beauty, standing still and reflecting in the refracted
light of another's encounter with the sublime …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;From the lastest issue of philosophy now. I find it's on the right side of
harsh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Museum-going Cannibal&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;by Yahia Lababidi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upright specimen, looking to be fine-tuned on weekends by the civilizing
influence of beauty, standing still and reflecting in the refracted
light of another's encounter with the sublime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All polite smiles and hushed appreciation, sliding up to some mounted
painting and tilting its head to sip and drink in the brushstrokes, yet
downright vicious throughout the week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hankering after a bit of meat and blood in the shape of a live woman or
a dead man. Never mind that they know them or not, at times, any old
body warm or cold will do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;as charitable and vulnerable as a winged thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;© Yahia Lababidi 2010&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Random"></category></entry></feed>