<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Shane Dowling</title>
    <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Shane Dowling</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 21:11:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://shanedowling.com/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Homelab - Day 5 - The NAS</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/homelab---day-5---the-nas/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 21:11:54 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/homelab---day-5---the-nas/</guid>
      <description>So, it&amp;rsquo;s been a while and I have made some progress worth sharing!&#xA;After keeping an eye on the auction sites for a while I ended up pulling the plug and buying 2 12TB Seagate Ironwolf drives for my NAS and now wanted to get started with setting this up.&#xA;The hardware Off a recommendation from Joe at Late Night Linux I picked up a HP 290 G2 I5-8500. It comes with 8GB of RAM and a 256ssd.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Homelab - Day 4 - Self-Hosting Gitea</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/homelab---day-4---self-hosting-gitea/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Mar 2025 19:31:59 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/homelab---day-4---self-hosting-gitea/</guid>
      <description>Aims Today’s goal was to deploy Gitea on my K3s cluster, ensuring that:&#xA;It used persistent storage via my NAS. It was accessible externally through Traefik. It could eventually replace GitHub for my FluxCD setup. What I Did Storage and Permissions Woes Running Gitea as a stateless container worked fine initially, but as soon as I introduced persistence, things got tricky. I ran into permission issues almost immediately, thanks to the interplay between Kubernetes&amp;rsquo; user permissions and my NAS file system.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Homelab - Day 3 - The first software deployment</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/homelab---day-3---the-first-software-deployment/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 10:45:34 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/homelab---day-3---the-first-software-deployment/</guid>
      <description>Aims The goal for today was to get my first piece of software running on the cluster, ensuring that:&#xA;It leveraged the NAS for storage. It was accessible externally via Traefik. The process was repeatable for future deployments. I chose the Unifi Management Console as my first self-hosted application. Once migrated, I could wipe my Raspberry Pi 4, which was previously running the console, and add it as a worker node to the cluster.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Homelab - Day 2 - Setting Up a New K3s Control Plane and Node</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/homelab---day-2---setting-up-k3s-control-plane/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 23:57:09 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/homelab---day-2---setting-up-k3s-control-plane/</guid>
      <description>After going back and forth multiple times and making plenty of mistakes, I finally managed to set up a new K3s control plane and node. It turned out to be relatively straightforward once I got the steps right, so I’m documenting this for future reference!&#xA;Aims The goal was to set up a fresh K3s cluster, ensuring that:&#xA;The control plane and node are configured correctly. Flux is properly bootstrapped to manage cluster state.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Homelab - Day 1 - Really Ghetto Data Storage</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/homelab---day-1---data-storage/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 13:57:09 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/homelab---day-1---data-storage/</guid>
      <description>Setting Up Storage for the Kubernetes Cluster The first step in setting up my homelab Kubernetes cluster is ensuring some reliable data storage. Right now, I have two main categories of data in mind:&#xA;1. Operationally Critical Data Needs RAID with redundancy Requires both on-site and off-site backups Approximately 1TB of data 2. Media Data Non-critical, so no backups required Several terabytes of storage needed Since the Kubernetes cluster depends on Operationally Critical Data, I need to establish a RAID-backed storage solution with proper backups before moving forward.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Homelab Setup: The Journey to Kubernetes</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/homelab-setup-the-journey-to-kubernetes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 20:50:46 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/homelab-setup-the-journey-to-kubernetes/</guid>
      <description>Why I&amp;rsquo;m Migrating My Self-Hosted Services I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to migrate all my existing self-hosted services—and add a few new ones—to a Kubernetes (K8s) cluster that I&amp;rsquo;m going to build. There are several motivations behind this decision:&#xA;Learning Kubernetes Beyond Ephemeral Clusters My role as an Engineering Manager at Syntasso involves a lot of K8s development using Kind, but these environments are entirely ephemeral. I want to experience the long-term challenges of operating a cluster to build greater empathy for our customers.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Hybrid Cloud Show is Live!</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/the-hybrid-cloud-show-is-live/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Apr 2024 16:45:59 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/the-hybrid-cloud-show-is-live/</guid>
      <description>Exciting news – the first episode of our podcast, the Hybrid Cloud Show, is finally here, part of the awesome Late Night Linux podcast family! 💥 Join me and three very smart industry pros as we dive into the fascinating world of public cloud, private cloud, and everything in between. Check out our first episode here.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>I&#39;m launching a Platform Engineering Newsletter</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/im-launching-a-platform-engineering-newsletter/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2024 16:45:59 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/im-launching-a-platform-engineering-newsletter/</guid>
      <description>Hello! I&amp;rsquo;m excited to share the first issue of our monthly journey through the world of platform engineering. This newsletter is all about the latest trends, insights, and resources in our field whether you&amp;rsquo;re a seasoned expert or just starting out.&#xA;You can find the first month here.&#xA;Each month, I&amp;rsquo;ll bring you a mix of news, case studies, upcoming events, and cool projects to keep you in the know. Feel free to share your thoughts, feedback, or anything exciting you&amp;rsquo;ve come across in platform engineering.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kindle Scribe to Mastodon</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/kindle-scribe-to-mastodon/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 16:45:59 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/kindle-scribe-to-mastodon/</guid>
      <description>Kindle Scribe to Mastodon Over the holidays, I put together a fun little project to put out status updates on Mastodon. Of course, I used some spare time to make this as overly-engineered as possible.&#xA;Stringing It All Together I wanted this to be event-driven and serverless and to give me some experience toying with Terraform in AWS. Thankfully, what would be the most computationally challenging part is already handled by Amazon.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Make your smartphone a little dumber</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/make-your-smartphone-a-little-dumber/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2023 16:45:59 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/make-your-smartphone-a-little-dumber/</guid>
      <description>For many, MANY years, I&amp;rsquo;ve been an advocate for the simplicity of dumbphones. My go-to? The LightPhone 2. However, modern life sometimes demands the functionalities of a smartphone, such as banking or GPS navigation. Every once in a while, I wish my smartphone would be just a touch simpler, but I can&amp;rsquo;t abandon its smart features entirely. There are times I need them, especially for those updates or browser-based app handshakes.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Streamlining OS Development Pipelines for the Beepberry - A Fun Challenge</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/streamlining-os-development-pipelines-for-the-beepberry/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jun 2023 13:32:59 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/streamlining-os-development-pipelines-for-the-beepberry/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Imagine a cool device that brings together an LCD screen, Raspberry Pi Zero, and a Blackberry keyboard – that&amp;rsquo;s the Beepberry! It&amp;rsquo;s designed to work like a WiFi-only keyboard phone, and one of the main goals is to reach a super-fast boot time of under 5 seconds. Sounds challenging, right? Well, to speed up the development process and test boot optimization, using QEMU to emulate the OS is a smart move.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Harnessing the Power of NixOS for Platform Engineering</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/harnessing-the-power-of-nixos-for-platform-engineering/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Mar 2023 13:32:59 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/harnessing-the-power-of-nixos-for-platform-engineering/</guid>
      <description>Introduction NixOS is an innovative and powerful Linux distribution built on top of the Nix package manager. Its unique approach to package and configuration management sets it apart from traditional Linux distributions, making it an excellent choice for platform engineering tasks. In this blog post, we’ll explore the benefits of using NixOS for platform engineering and provide an overview of its key features. Immutable Infrastructure and Reproducible Builds&#xA;NixOS’s immutability and reproducibility are its most significant strengths.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>De-risk early when engineering platforms</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/de-risk-early-when-engineering-platforms/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Mar 2023 13:32:59 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/de-risk-early-when-engineering-platforms/</guid>
      <description>Platform engineering encompasses a broad domain with continually evolving frontiers that require overcoming new challenges to level up the solutions offered to engineers. However, this evolution can lead to situations where previously-made assumptions may no longer be applicable to new solutions.&#xA;Our team recently encountered this scenario when using AWS Stacksets across multi-account/region rollouts of our platform, which highlighted some interesting dependency challenges that we only discovered at the 11th hour of our project.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reduce developer cognitive load with nix</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/reduce-developer-cognitive-load-with-nix/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Mar 2023 13:32:59 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/reduce-developer-cognitive-load-with-nix/</guid>
      <description>Nixpkg is a package manager that uses a purely functional approach to package management, isolating packages and ensuring that there are no conflicts between them. It provides a powerful language for defining packages, which makes it easy to manage dependencies and ensure that software environments are reproducible and reliable. Additionally, Nixpkg makes it easy to manage multiple software environments and share projects with other developers.&#xA;In addition to Nixpkg, there are two other tools that can be used in conjunction with Nix to improve developer productivity: Homemanager and Direnv.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonviolent Communication</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/nonviolent-communication-a7bddf8d0805/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Aug 2021 13:32:59 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/nonviolent-communication-a7bddf8d0805/</guid>
      <description>What is Nonviolent Communication? Nonviolent Communication(NVC) helps us communicate clearly by breaking down and identifying our needs and communicating them compassionately.&#xA;Why? NVC can help reduce conflict towards others and ourselves. It can also help us to hear others out and recognise each other&amp;rsquo;s needs and support acting more compassionately day to day.&#xA;How At a high level, the steps involved are:&#xA;Observation Be present and listen carefully to what the other person is saying.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>5 Steps to a better Personal Development Plan(PDP)</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/wrangle-your-personal-development-plan-pdp-into-actionable-objectives-e448649b5db0/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Mar 2021 15:30:42 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/wrangle-your-personal-development-plan-pdp-into-actionable-objectives-e448649b5db0/</guid>
      <description>Reviewing your PDP can be a somewhat overwhelming process. So many areas of improvement can be highlighted, it can be a real challenge to discover what to focus on. Not only that but you also want to make sure your areas of focus have high impact benefits to the squad, so much to think about!&#xA;These 5 steps should help give you the direction needed to turn those PDP opportunities into something actionable, demonstrable and focused on what you care about.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Python as a Platform Engineer-First Steps</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/learning-python-as-a-platform-engineer-first-steps-911e59dd4af8/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 14:48:49 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/learning-python-as-a-platform-engineer-first-steps-911e59dd4af8/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve relatively recently moved into a Platform Engineering position after working in very developer oriented teams for many years. What&amp;rsquo;s interesting is that the engineers you work with have much more diverse and interesting backgrounds in terms of their experience, so there&amp;rsquo;s a real opportunity to grow and learn a lot more, as opposed to a more homogenous set of developers. With that in mind, I wanted to put together materials on how a more ops focused engineer can up-skill in Python(as that&amp;rsquo;s more my wheel-house), in particular what are the things that would help you move into a more Python-focused role.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Populate Ansible from Amazon secrets manager</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/populate-ansible-from-amazon-secrets-manager-8eac77127e37/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Sep 2020 18:06:58 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/populate-ansible-from-amazon-secrets-manager-8eac77127e37/</guid>
      <description>One of the ways to improve your security and avoid passing around env files is to follow the twelve factor app and start populating your secrets from the environment. Another improvement is to pull those secrets from a known secret store, with features like rotation, auditing etc.&#xA;Requirements Ansible Have some secrets stored in AWS Secrets Manager Ansible should have access to the latest aws-cli command(secrets manager is a recent addition) Jq if you&amp;rsquo;re storing json in your secrets It&amp;rsquo;s worth testing your AWS calls to just extract the secret you&amp;rsquo;re interested in to stdout, from the terminal tests some calls like:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Better local development for Serverless Functions</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/better-local-development-for-serverless-functions-b96b5a4cfa8f/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Feb 2019 20:15:38 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/better-local-development-for-serverless-functions-b96b5a4cfa8f/</guid>
      <description>Lambda is a terrific piece of kit for all the benefits listed on the AWS product page and Serverless is a very useful framework for developing Lambda functions. However, developing serverless applications locally is a total pain if what you&amp;rsquo;re solving isn&amp;rsquo;t totally trivial.&#xA;When things get complicated and your Lambda functions start to integrate with other AWS services, things really begin to break down. There are a few things that look like silver-bullets, I&amp;rsquo;ll share them here and explain why they didn&amp;rsquo;t work for me, then give you a working example that I myself struggled to find(hence me writing this).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Easy maintenance mode with nginx</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/easy-maintenance-mode-with-nginx-2d4d510a0980/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Aug 2018 18:51:42 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/easy-maintenance-mode-with-nginx-2d4d510a0980/</guid>
      <description>So I combined a few solutions I found online to come up with a quick way to set up maintenance mode using nginx. Ideally it shouldn&amp;rsquo;t happen but in times of emergency in can be good to knock up a quick maintenance page for everyone but your own internal ips.&#xA;Nginx Config So here&amp;rsquo;s the configuration I use for nginx, it starts with setting the internal ips of your company in the main nginx config file.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
