<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Productivity on Shane Dowling</title>
    <link>https://shanedowling.com/categories/productivity/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Productivity on Shane Dowling</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 02 Apr 2018 13:45:51 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://shanedowling.com/categories/productivity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Beware the todo list</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/beware-the-todo-list-7faac97dae4a/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Apr 2018 13:45:51 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/beware-the-todo-list-7faac97dae4a/</guid>
      <description>For the last few months, I&amp;rsquo;ve been working off a varying series of to-do lists to drive my life. I use a mix of the Things app, my bullet journal, and a calendar. Basically, my setup is to have annual Smart Goals, broken down into achievable chunks, then broken down into tasks to knock off todo lists. On the face of it, it&amp;rsquo;s a way to organise a wiggly world.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Freelancer Lessons – Part 3</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/freelancer-lessons-part-3-7015dc89b6fb/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jan 2018 14:54:41 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/freelancer-lessons-part-3-7015dc89b6fb/</guid>
      <description>This is part 3 in a series on lessons I&amp;rsquo;ve learned from several years of freelancing. You can find Part 1 here and Part 2 here, though you can read these in no specific order really.&#xA;Watch your mental state When you&amp;rsquo;re working a full-time job, you&amp;rsquo;ll have people around you who will get to know you over time. Professional relationships start to develop, people will start to recognise you &amp;lsquo;on a good day&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;on a bad day&amp;rsquo; with enough &amp;lsquo;bad days&amp;rsquo; on the trot almost always a caring co-worker or a good boss will check in on you, perhaps help with your workload or just lend an ear to listen.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Freelancer Lessons – Part 2</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/freelancer-lessons-part-2-e5700002d8b/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 16:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/freelancer-lessons-part-2-e5700002d8b/</guid>
      <description>This is a series of posts on lessons I&amp;rsquo;ve learned while freelancing for the past four years. You can find Part 1 here.&#xA;Focusing on &amp;ldquo;profits only&amp;rdquo; I&amp;rsquo;ve alluded to this in my previous post, but, now that you&amp;rsquo;re a business, you may start to make decisions that optimise being a business, not a person. It becomes easier to start making decisions that might lead to say personal burnout for the sake of professional business health.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Freelancer lessons – Part 1</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/developer-lessons-from-2017-part-1-14c31f45307c/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Dec 2017 19:20:04 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/developer-lessons-from-2017-part-1-14c31f45307c/</guid>
      <description>Looking back on this year, many of the lessons I&amp;rsquo;ve learned had less to do with specific technologies and more to do with long term career growth. I&amp;rsquo;ve been a developer now for 9 years and as a result, I&amp;rsquo;m starting to think more about longer term goals and happiness. As a result I made the decision to move from contracting back to full time work towards the tail end of the year so a lot of my reflections are tied around the costs of short term thinking and contracting in general.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Setting up git with Rescuetime highlights</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/setting-up-git-with-rescuetime-highlights-aa6d13128bb6/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/setting-up-git-with-rescuetime-highlights-aa6d13128bb6/</guid>
      <description>Recently I&amp;rsquo;ve written on another site how I use Rescuetime to provide metrics on my overall productivity that I can review each week. One useful feature I noticed was Rescuetime highlights, which gives you a good overview of your accompishments throughout the day. The first thing I wanted to add to this (obviously) was git commits.&#xA;Luckily it turns out someone had already thought of this and implemented it. The script itself is here, I&amp;rsquo;m just going to reproduce it below.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bulletproof productivity</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/bulletproof-productivity-c95958f3bbf9/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/bulletproof-productivity-c95958f3bbf9/</guid>
      <description>Over the last few months I&amp;rsquo;ve been trying different ways to increase my productivity, specifically during work hours. From todo lists to pomodoro&amp;rsquo;s, xeffect cards, the autofocus method and even back to GTD. I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed a pattern with a lot of these techniques. They all require a pile of maintenance and none of them actually give you much in terms of positive feedback. When you mark a task off a list, you&amp;rsquo;re often not getting the satisfaction of completion because that task is in the middle of a huge pile of other tasks you have yet to face.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Engineers Log</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/engineers-log-69525c451538/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/engineers-log-69525c451538/</guid>
      <description>Four years ago(to the day) I wrote a post on why I was Giving up on wikis and I have to admit, four years later my opinions on the topic really haven&amp;rsquo;t changed.&#xA;It&amp;rsquo;s been 4 years, 700 questions(with 800 answers) and several server moves later and by and large the process hasn&amp;rsquo;t changed all that much, everything is just little more streamlined.&#xA;Tagging: When I started I simply used tagging to reflect the technology the</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perfomance Enhancing Breakfast</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/perfomance-enhancing-breakfast-4a14f17ee20a/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/perfomance-enhancing-breakfast-4a14f17ee20a/</guid>
      <description>As Lance Armstrong has shown the world, putting the right thing into your body can greatly improve performance, I myself have been looking into more maintainable alternative. More and more I&amp;rsquo;m experimenting with diet as a means to improve my mental performance as well as my running ability week on week. Specifically ways of optimising the meals I&amp;rsquo;m taking in and turning them into more efficient forms of food consumption.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cutting caffeine</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/cutting-caffeine-20012941744d/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/cutting-caffeine-20012941744d/</guid>
      <description>A little while ago, I read a post on Sebastian Marshall&amp;rsquo;s blog about cutting caffeine, in which goes into the benefits and a method he uses for quitting coffee. He suggests cycling off it to reset your tolerance every so often. I figured that was a really good idea since I&amp;rsquo;d gotten to the point where in the morning I needed a coffee to feel normal, it was a good time to do something about it.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sleep as the fundamental habit</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/sleep-as-the-fundamental-habit-f9590f13c013/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/sleep-as-the-fundamental-habit-f9590f13c013/</guid>
      <description>Leo Babuta describes meditation as the fundamental habit, the underlying habits beneath all others. Personally, I disagree. I wrote recently on how I cope with meditation when you haven&amp;rsquo;t had a particularly good nights sleep.&#xA;Realistically washing your face is like taking painkillers after a serious injury, it&amp;rsquo;s only painting over the cracks of a deeper problem. Meditation and mindfulness truly can unlock the potential of your day, but a good nights rests can even more.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GYPYSs and unrealistic expectations</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/gypyss-and-unrealistic-expectations-f67a4927d9d6/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/gypyss-and-unrealistic-expectations-f67a4927d9d6/</guid>
      <description>This article was shared with me recently, it&amp;rsquo;s an excellent read and provides some good reasoning for why people feel that vague sense of living an unaccomplished life. I&amp;rsquo;ll admit it, I am most definitely a Gypsy. My garden right now it full of flowers of unrealistic expectations. I&amp;rsquo;d begun to discover this while meditating and watching my emotions daily.&#xA;In Headspace there&amp;rsquo;s a section called the discovery series. You begin to focus on watching your emotions throughout the day and when your mind gets distracted and wanders.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Performance gains by altering your routine</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/performance-gains-by-altering-your-routine-f44365b8972b/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/performance-gains-by-altering-your-routine-f44365b8972b/</guid>
      <description>In the mornings I had a very structured routine. The first thing I would do is meditate as for me, all other habits flow from this. Then after my meditation I would either go for a run or do some dumbbell based strength exercises. The reasoning being that as exercising was also a quiet periods, I could try extending the mindfulness and clarity gained from meditation into my exercises and have a better chance of remaining mindful throughout the day.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GSD 2 — Retaining Focus</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/gsd-2-retaining-focus-98ffdabf2a75/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/gsd-2-retaining-focus-98ffdabf2a75/</guid>
      <description>Xmonad - Xmonad is a Haskell based window manager for both Linux and Mac(sorry Windows users). It&amp;rsquo;s highly configurable but for me it&amp;rsquo;s lack of features and application bar crap is a real advantage. The application your currently working with takes up the entirety of the screen and you navigate to other applications using keyboard shortcuts. Using this and disabling notifications in your IM/Email/whatever clients forces you to work on the task in front of you.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GSD 3 — Keeping your habits in mind</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/gsd-3-keeping-your-habits-in-mind-ded639ef1e39/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/gsd-3-keeping-your-habits-in-mind-ded639ef1e39/</guid>
      <description>So you&amp;rsquo;ve removed your distractions and figured out how to maintain focus. You&amp;rsquo;ve a set of good habits you&amp;rsquo;d like to being implementing. Well firstly, read this. Don&amp;rsquo;t jump head first into habits you&amp;rsquo;ve never gone through before. You&amp;rsquo;re expectations will be too high and sadly, you&amp;rsquo;ll likely fail. Patience is a virtue. So, after you&amp;rsquo;ve chosen the habit you&amp;rsquo;d like to begin with, here are some tools to help keep you focused on those good habits.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GSD 4 — Reviewing</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/gsd-4-reviewing-8a7ab553a72f/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/gsd-4-reviewing-8a7ab553a72f/</guid>
      <description>So the final process I use to help me get shit done is reviewing. Each week I do a fairly lengthy review of the last week. I see what habits have been successful and which have been a struggle to maintain. I look to see if there are appropriate alterations I can use to help improve. Here&amp;rsquo;s a list of the things I tend to analyse while reviewing, and the questions I&amp;rsquo;ve asked.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GSD 1 — Reducing Distractions</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/gsd-1-reducing-distractions-a42c7b164ce0/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/gsd-1-reducing-distractions-a42c7b164ce0/</guid>
      <description>Most of my distractions currently come from within. I hit up social media or news sites. Also my email is a big time waster. I needed a way to remain connected but while preventing regular access. Here&amp;rsquo;s what helped.&#xA;Get Shit Done-A cross platform OS level site blocker. Simply install the script, add your distracting sites and run &amp;lsquo;get-shit-done work&amp;rsquo; in a terminal. You only notice sheer number of times you find yourself flicking to those distracting sites when a big error is thrown that the site is unavailable.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Getting Shit Done</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/getting-shit-done-99303b405d8c/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/getting-shit-done-99303b405d8c/</guid>
      <description>I created a number of long term goals recently and have been trying to work out a system within which I can continue to keep my focus on those long term goals and reduce procrastination. I try to promote a daily focus on long term tasks through reminders and regular reviews while reducing procrastination through a set of core tools. I tried multiple tools/tricks and what I&amp;rsquo;ll post a series on the tools and tricks I used.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Just Keep Going</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/just-keep-going-eebcba9f4076/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Apr 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/archived/just-keep-going-eebcba9f4076/</guid>
      <description>Productivity has never been my strong point. I&amp;rsquo;m the ultimate procrastinator. I will literally do anything other than the task at hand. In fact this post is likely being written purely as I don&amp;rsquo;t want to study. But, the post itself is useful in it&amp;rsquo;s function to push me forward.&#xA;I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten attracted to a very simple idea of &amp;ldquo;Just keep going&amp;rdquo;. In my head I imagine the Terminator, after being blown to bits, still getting up.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>For any active del.icio.us users I&#39;d highly recommend…</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/for-any-active-del-icio-us-users-id-highly-recommend-d89cee8880c7/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Dec 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/for-any-active-del-icio-us-users-id-highly-recommend-d89cee8880c7/</guid>
      <description>Pinboard: social bookmarking for introverts _For a few more bucks a year, Pinboard offers an archiving service which saves a copy of everything you bookmark, gives…_pinboard.in</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Top 10 webapps for programmers</title>
      <link>https://shanedowling.com/posts/top-10-webapps-for-programmers-38c75fba4a63/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shanedowling.com/posts/top-10-webapps-for-programmers-38c75fba4a63/</guid>
      <description>Evernote Although I use evernote as my brain online for everthing, it is incredibly useful for programmers too. Where I work things like requirements can be captured on almost anything, so snapping photos of whiteboards/notepads/beer mats that become OCR searchable is very handy. On top of that it&amp;rsquo;s nice to have all notes auto stored up on the web(I&amp;rsquo;d have a fit if I lost my developer diary over a hard drive crash).</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
